Subtitles ST' 501
This was the challenge undertaken by Pierre Capretz and his learning team.
as well as the television producers of WGBH Boston.
The result of their efforts is this 52-series program
called “French in Action”,
a multimedia course that opens a new era in learning.
The main principle of the course is immersion.
un process by which students are thrown into a French-speaking world from the very start.
It was frightening at first, but I think after a few lessons,
when you understood the way things were going to be handled,
you got used to it. It became a little less intimidating.
We talked with Beatrice Abetti, coordinator of the French in Action project.
The difference between immersion technique and, if you want, a more traditional technique
It's that, instead of giving French word by word, if you will, bit by bit, or, you know, feeding the students, in a certain way, we plunge them, we will put them in a fishing pole of French.
I think the most valuable part of the course is that you learn all of French at once.
On the first day of class, the teacher came in speaking French, and on day 1, we spoke French.
And as for the conversation, we got ourselves out of a situation by speaking French from the beginning.
And it was a faster way to learn a language I had known before.
In this course, we learned everything at the same time, which works really well.
I have studied other languages ​​in the past, and I learned the alphabet in two weeks.
And how to say table and chair, and then body parts,
And you can't say nothing.
And with the French class I took here,
It was more about what was happening in real life.
Ah, there you are, perfect timing. Come and help me.
Come on.
French in Action shows what is happening in French life
by presenting cultural documents,
like interviews with people on the street.
What is your name?
My name is France.
And you, what is your name?
Jacqueline, my name is Jacqueline.
And I'm Nicole.
May I ask how old you are?
Guess.
What is your first name?
Olivier.
And how old are you?
12 years old.
Do you go to school?
Yes, unfortunately.
Which school are you going to?
At the Buffon high school.
What's your name? My name is Hervé. Hervé what? Hervé Meunier. How old are you? I'm 20 years old.
What is your name, madam? Madame Jolyne. Do you live in Paris? JOULIN. Jolyne.
Do you live in Paris? Of course, it's the fifth arrondissement. It's Paris since I live there.
How long have you been in Paris?
Oh, it's been 35 years, sir. But I'm an old Parisian, you know.
35 years old. I was born near Saint-Gervais.
Have you always lived in Paris?
I have always lived in Paris.
These interviews are used to illustrate specific words, such as "tired".
Here, the elderly woman says she is 85 years old and tired.
I am 85 years old, so I am tired.
I don't feel well, I'm sick.
I am sick too.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
We always go to the bistro at the station, the women who have taste, the men who have a room.
In this food ad, the central characters help viewers understand the expression "no rush".
Obviously, these horses are not in any particular moment.
Subtitles ST' 501
Humour, like the French language, is hardly translated and can only be understood from within the French cultural system.
That's the goal of French In Action.
To achieve this goal, French In Action systematically avoids translation.
Hello, Miss Mireille, how are you?
Okay. Goodbye.
Goodbye, miss.
You see? She speaks French.
No English is ever spoken.
Only the everyday language of the French people.
Good morning.
Where are you going?
When you walk into the first class and you view the first video,
it's very intimidating and frustrating because you have no English to use.
Students do get angry and frustrated, especially at the beginning.
So it was kind of like a challenge to conquer.
They might be uncomfortable for a few weeks.
because there are so many French people who are put on them
and that they only understand the register of that.
But that's good, that's what we want.
I like the fact that there's a French barrier
who is loved by the student.
I like a course that is challenging.
It was funny, because when they spoke French right away,
We felt that we were really going to learn something.
We knew we were going to be immersed in it right away.
And we knew it would be difficult.
But that would be an amazing experience.
We talked with Pierre Capretz about the absence of English and about how you make sense of what you hear.
In this course, we throw lots of French at the students, and only French.
We don't use English. We don't translate. Why?
Well, because French is not a translation of English.
It is not English that has been coded into French.
No, French is French. It is not a code of English.
So that you cannot just replace a French word with an English word
It does not really work
When French people say something in French
It is not that they really mean something in English
But say it in French because they don't know better
Or to show off or out of perversity
No, when they say something in French
They mean something French
So, to understand what a French word means
What you need to do is observe the circumstances in which it is used.
That's what will tell you what that saying means.
Think of saying hello, for example.
What does that mean?
Hello, hello, hello, hello.
Well, not exactly.
But look at yourself.
Good morning.
Hello, Mrs. Nutigl.
Hello Sir.
Good morning.
Hello, Miss Bello.
Hello Sir.
You see that "bonjour" is something that French people say when they meet someone.
It's the meaning of "hello", the circumstances in which it is used.
Note that there are words that are used in different types of circumstances.
"Hello," for example. Look how it's used here.
You see, "hi" is something you say when you meet someone.
But now, look at this.
You see that "hi" is also something you say when you go out.
In this course, we do not translate the words, but we show them used in a number of situations.
so that students can understand what they mean through observation and deduction.
Here's how it works.
You see the teacher on the first day of the French class announcing nous allons apprendre le français.
Then you see a child learning how to read and you hear il apprend à lire.
Then you see a little girl studying her lessons and you hear elle apprend ses leçons.
Then you see her learning how to knit and you hear elle apprend à tricoter.
You see a young woman who's learning how to play the guitar and you hear
She is learning to play the guitar.
You see a man learning how to swim and you hear
He is learning to swim.
By then, you're beginning to suspect that this word, apprendre, apprend,
has something to do with the notion of learning.
Let's take another example.
You see someone in a hurry and you hear presser.
then you see someone who is not in a hurry and you hear pas pressé you compare
the two and you get a notion that pressé pas pressé has something to do with
being in a hurry or not being in a hurry or else you see a young woman who is
sick in bed and you hear elle est malade you see other people who look sick and
And you hear "sick, sick, sick, sick".
Then you see a young woman who does not look sick at all
and you hear pas malade.
You get an idea that sick, not sick
must have something to do with being sick or not being sick.
We don't have to tell you.
You figured it out by yourself, progressively, in a natural way.
All you have to do is to observe, to listen,
and to put two and two together.
Now, if you don't understand everything the first time around,
it's all right, it's perfectly natural.
It will come progressively.
French in Action présente French through a continuing story.
A light, almost fanciful tale about Albert,
a young American who meets a French woman, Mireille,
her impish sister, Marie-Laure,
her uncle, Guillaume,
her aunt, Georgette.
her friends, Colette,
Hubert, a young man who plays his part
like a nobleman, Jean-Pierre,
a chance encounter
and dozens of other French people
in all aspects of life.
Even if the details of this story
are true, it's not supposed
to be taken into account.
You really see the grammar used in action
as opposed to just learning it in a boring, dry lesson.
We talked with Barry Lydgate
about the role of the story in the course.
The drama on which this whole course is based
is a wonderful feature of the course in two ways.
First of all, it is motivational.
It's the student's way of getting access to the culture,
of understanding the characters,
of finding out about French life and language.
The situations were very real, and it was a story of the mind, and it was a good vehicle, I think.
This course gives you access to a very vital, exciting and creative culture.
And it's important to see it that way, and it's also important to have fun, to relax, to rest, to enjoy the class.
It is full of wonderful images, wonderful characters, wonderful languages.
We'll take care of you.
Hello, I am Marie-Claude.
Not well. What's wrong? Are you sick? No, I'm not sick. I'm not feeling well, I'm tired.
The second part of each lesson clarifies and illustrates the dialogue in the story.
She is tired. She too is tired. She is tired. She is tired. He is tired. He is tired.
He is tired.
I'm tired.
Fatigue.
Georgette is tired too.
It's tiring.
She is tired.
Listen.
One of the main functions of the course is that it involves students
to hear the language before they see it written down.
The course introduces spoken language before it introduces written language.
or before she asks students to read and write actively
for a very good reason.
French and English are written using the same alphabet, but the ways in which sounds are represented in French are different from the ways in which they are represented in English.
And it is important for students to hear the sound before reproducing it from a written representation.
If you take, for example, the word "how", which is written HOW,
English writers will instinctively see this.
through the prism of their own writing system
and will say how, when in fact the French word is pronounced how
and means something completely different.
An essential activity for students
is to imitate what they see and hear.
They should watch closely and repeat.
either to themselves, or, better still, in writing.
In all programs, there is a point where students can take on the role of one of the characters.
Here's how it works.
The students see an exchange between two characters, for example between Mireille and Mrs. Rosa.
The exchange is repeated.
Next, Miss Rosa's line is heard twice.
Then, a brake on the brake to give the students a chance to rehearse.
When they come to an interactive segment, students should try, if possible, to repeat it when they have time to do so.
And they should talk, they shouldn't be grumpy about it.
It's very important to say this in a moment,
as if you were talking to someone halfway across the room.
It felt weird to be talking to a slap-puncher.
And I often ask myself, who is listening?
And the only thing that matters is that I'm learning something.
After watching the program,
Students should work with the audio cassettes from French In Action.
This allows them to practice historical dialogue
by repeating...
How are you ?
How is Hubert?
Not bad.
I'm going to university. And you?
Subtitles ST' 501
Teachers who work independently can reinvent history
using printed elements in a grid at the location of each work lesson.
By selecting and recombining the sentences they see,
They create a new storyline or a new dialogue.
Jack, how are you?
Not too good.
Are you sick?
Yes.
Yes, I am sick.
Fido is sick too.
Where are you going?
I'm going to the library.
Bye.
Students who can work with partners can enact their reinvention.
For example, after watching these scenes...
Hello, miss.
Hello, Miss Mireille. How are you?
Okay. Goodbye.
Goodbye, miss.
Hello, my dear Mireille. How are you?
I'm fine, thank you. And you, how are you?
Oh, I'm not doing well.
What's wrong? Are you feeling unwell? Are you sick?
No, I'm not sick. I'm not feeling well. I'm tired.
Students can have fun combining them in a new dialogue, like this one.
Are you ready?
Yes.
Hey, hello, Mrs. Rosa.
Hello, Miss Mireille. How are you?
No, that won't do.
Are you feeling unwell? Are you sick?
No, I'm not sick, but I'm in a hurry.
Oh, you're going to university?
No, I'm not going to university, I'm going to Tahiti.
Hello!
Goodbye, Miss Mireille.
It's important to remember, when learning French,
to imitate gestures as well as words,
because we communicate not only with words,
but with our whole bodies.
Laurence Wiley Douglas Dillon, Professor Emeritus of French Civilization at Harvard
The university explains that the longer I've learned French over a long period of my life, the more I've realized the importance of communication.
It doesn't just come through words, it comes from the whole body and I have become more and more
I'm interested in this and I think it's incredibly important to learn to communicate in French.
Take for instance, the first scene you're going to see, it shows Mireille Ballot coming out of her apartment house, coming around the corner fast because she's on her way to an Italian class and she's late.
And there, it's her best friend who is in a cafe with three or four other people.
So, of course, she stops and moves away from each of them and gives her friend a kiss.
But she needs to be run, so what does she do?
She walks away with them all again.
This seems very strange to Americans, but it is very important to maintain a relationship with the French to learn these kinds of things.
People have a need to communicate with other parts of their body.
Jean-Pierre is the kind of person who can't break anything without putting his whole self into it.
But the way he uses his body is very stylized.
That is to say, he uses all the gestures that other people make, but he uses more of them.
For example, when they ask him if he is going to be a doctor or something like that, he says "No way" in English and in French.
Jean-Pierre
Robert is tired. He stops ordering a rooster, sir.
To pay him, he takes out his bill and hands over a note for 500 francs.
500 francs is 100 dollars, to pay for this small sandwich.
And the guy at the table, who's pointing towards the sky, you know, testing.
What a long-standing situation there. Oh dear.
Oh, yes, 500 francs.
The great advantage you have now, which I didn't have when I was learning French in the old Frasier and Square grammar, where there were only conjugations and so on, is that you can actually see people acting and see their bodies moving, and see their bodies moving in time with their voices.
And if you really pay attention to this and you're in this rhythm, you're going to learn to speak French, you're going to learn to communicate much better than I did when I had the opportunity to learn conjugations.
When learning to communicate in French with "French in Action", remember that in each lesson you will hear a large number of French people.
But you are warned that the first time you will only hear a part of what you hear, and to use an even smaller part.
part, your ability to understand and speak French will improve steadily if you remember
the rules of the game. Observe, imitate, speak up, and practice.
I don't think that I could have achieved any level of French proficiency if I hadn't
I practiced it. I took it on myself for at least part of each day.
either I was jogging or I was talking to my cat, trying to do it in French.
Do this on a consistent basis, not studying French every other day.
but studying French every day, perhaps for less time, but consistently.
Learning a language is like preparing for a piano concert.
or paint a picture, or sculpt a sculpture.
You cannot compress the experience.
You can't expect it to take place over 5 or 6 days,
and then at the end of cramping up for an exam or exercise of that kind.
Practice was the key.
The development is gradual, but there is very quickly an incredible understanding.
I had a lot of fun doing it.
I was in France and Switzerland for a while, and I made a lot of friends there.
and I promised to return to France as soon as I could.
I have a friend in Switzerland who is quite impressed by the fact that,
Then, well, when it was just after a year, I was able to hold a reasonable conversation with her, with more than just basic vocabulary.
I think if I went to a French country, I would do well now.
French in Action gives students access to hundreds of people who speak French.
Thousands of real-life situations.
Millions of individual images of contemporary France.
The result is a tool for communicating in French.
which is sophisticated and current.
In addition, French in Action gives learners
an overview of French culture,
the past and the present.
This cultural insight is what makes
A really effective and fun study of France.
...
French subtitles?
Subtitling by Radio-Canada