Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
In Tahiti, in Africa, or even in Switzerland, Belgium and France.
In France, we speak French.
In Alsace, in Rouen, in Chartres, they speak French.
In Paris, they speak French.
Hello, Mrs. Rosin.
Hello, Miss Mireille.
How are you ?
How are you.
Bye.
Goodbye, miss.
You see, she speaks French.
Now she will meet Colette and some of Colette's friends. They will speak French.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Now she's going to meet Hubert.
They will speak French.
Hi, how are you?
Not bad, and you?
How are you
Where are you going like that?
At university, and you?
Ah, I don't go to university.
Ah good ?
Okay, excuse me, I'm late, goodbye
Bye
You see, he speaks French.
Now she will meet another friend, Ousmane.
They will speak French.
Hey, Ousmane.
Hello, how are you?
Yes, yes, I'm fine, thank you. And you?
Okay. Where are you going?
I'm going to the library. And you?
I'm going to university. Hi.
Hello.
You see, he speaks French.
And now she's going to meet two friends.
Marc and Catherine, they are going to speak French.
Hey, look, it's Mireille.
Hi, how are you two doing?
It's good and you ?
Where are you going like that?
We're going to the university restaurant.
Already ?
Yes.
Enjoy your meal then.
THANKS.
Hello.
You see, they speak French.
And now, look, she's going to meet an old professor.
And they will speak French.
Oh, hello, Miss Bello. How are you?
I'm fine, thank you. And you, are you well?
I'm fine, I'm fine, thank you. Goodbye, miss.
Goodbye, sir.
You see, they speak French.
And now she's going to meet a lady.
Her aunt, Aunt Georgette. They will speak French.
Hello, my dear Mireille. How are you?
How are you, Mercier? How are you?
Oh, me, not too well.
What is it?
Are you unwell? Are you sick?
No, I'm not sick, no.
Things aren't going well, I'm tired.
Oh, it'll get better.
And you, my little Fido, how are you?
You're doing well. You're not tired, are you?
Oh, you're a sweet little dog. You're doing very well.
Oh, his health is fine.
He's not tired.
Oh dear, I'm going to be late
Goodbye, Aunt Jojo
But where are you going?
I'm going to be late for university.
Bye
Goodbye, my little one
Come on, Fido!
One
Where is she going?
She goes to university
She is going to learn Italian
We are going to learn French.
We are going to learn
Learn
Look at this little boy.
He is learning to read.
And she, she learns, it's the sound.
Put the crow in its perched tree.
And here, she is learning to knit.
She is learning to knit.
He's learning to swim.
And she, she's learning karate.
And they, they learn to ski.
She is learning to play the guitar.
And here...
She is going to learn Italian.
And what about us? Are we going to learn Italian? No, we're not going to learn Italian, we're going to learn French.
What are we going to do? We are going to learn French.
Yes, that's it, we're going to learn French. We're going to learn French.
To learn Italian, she goes to university. Mireille goes to university, to the faculty of...
letters the university the faculty the university the faculty the university Mireille goes to university and
And Ousmane goes to the library.
The library.
A library.
Ousmane is going to work at the library.
Ousmane goes to the library and Marc and Catherine go to the university restaurant.
They go to the Resto U, the university restaurant.
They go to the restaurant, they go to eat.
They go to the university restaurant, they go to eat.
He eats, he eats, she eats, she eats, she eats, he eats, she eats, he eats, he eats, he eats, he eats.
She eats at the restaurant
He also eats at restaurants
They eat at the restaurant
They also eat at restaurants
At the restaurant
They will eat at the university restaurant
Enjoy your food
Watch, he's going to say bon appétit
THANKS
Enjoy your meal, enjoy your meal! Watch, she's going to say "Enjoy your meal," "Good morning, sir," there you go, enjoy your meal!
Enjoy your meal, thank you. She says, "Enjoy your meal, enjoy your meal," and he says, "Thank you, thank you, thank you, good night, thank you."
Thank you. You too.
THANKS.
Thank you again. Everything was truly exquisite.
There you go.
THANKS.
Thank you. Thank you anyway.
Thank you, thank you so much, my dear, thank you.
Thank you, thank you, Julienne, for taking my turn.
You're welcome, Dad.
Thank you for your beautiful bouquet.
Well, say thank you.
THANKS.
Thank you very much, you are very kind.
Thank you, goodbye.
THANKS.
Generally, people say thank you.
Look, look at that lady over there.
She's going to say thank you.
Thank you, gentlemen.
You see, she said thank you
THANKS
I don't know why I said thank you
Mireille is in a hurry
Excuse me, I'm in a hurry, goodbye
Bye
She is in a hurry
And the cows, are they in a hurry?
No, they are not in a hurry.
Ah, it's ringing.
They are in no hurry.
Finally.
In a hurry?
No hurry.
They are in a hurry.
We're leaving in five minutes.
He's in a hurry.
He too is in a hurry.
But he's in no hurry.
They are in a hurry.
They are in no hurry.
In a hurry, not in a hurry.
Look at Ousmane here. He's in a hurry.
But not here. Here, he's not in a hurry.
He's not in a hurry, he's tired.
He is tired too.
She is tired.
She is tired too.
He is tired.
I'm tired.
Tired.
And look at that lady, she's tired.
I am 85 years old, so I am tired.
Georgette is tired too.
I'm tired.
She is tired.
She is tired, but she is not sick.
No, no, she's not sick.
No, I'm not sick, no.
She is not sick.
Sick.
Mireille is sick here.
I'm sick.
But here, she is not sick.
She is ill.
I don't feel well, I'm sick.
I am sick too.
He is ill.
She is ill.
And her.
How kind my daughters are.
Good morning.
I'm not sick, you know.
I can get up.
But we know you're not sick.
You're not sick at all.
But he is sick.
Her too.
She is sick, but not here, here she is not sick, sick, not sick, sick, not sick.
Now, the surprise: when we're surprised, we say, "Hey, hey, hey Ousmane, hey Hubert!"
Look, Miss Belleau! Look!
Well! How strange!
Hey, is that you?
Hey, is that you? What a coincidence!
Well, well, well! Listen!
Hey, Colette!
Good morning !
Hey, Marie! Hello!
Hello, Madame du Tiguel!
Hello Sir !
Good morning !
Hello, hello sir, hello sir, hello sir, hello sir, hello madam, hello miss, hello sir.
Hello, hello madam, hello, hello madam, hello.
Hello, yes, hello Mr. Mate, hello children, ah, Hubert, hello, hello sir, hello, hello, hello.
Good morning. Good morning everyone. Good morning, Mrs. René. Very early. Good morning, Antoine. Good morning, Mrs. René. Good morning to you. Good morning. Good morning. Good morning. Good morning, Miss Bello. Good morning, Mrs. Rosa. Good morning, Miss Mireille. Listen carefully. Good morning, Mrs. Rosa. Good morning, Miss Mireille. Good morning, Mrs. Rosa. Your turn now. Speak. You are Mrs. Rosa. Answer. Go ahead.
Hello, Ms. Rosa.
Hello, Miss Mireille.
Again.
Hello, Ms. Rosa.
Hello, Miss Mireille.
Observe.
Hi Véronique.
Hello.
Hi, Balut.
Ah.
Hello.
Hi. Hi, cowboy. Hi, Laristo. Hi, Antoine. Hello. Hi. Look. How are you? How are you? How are you? How are you? How are you? How are you both? How are you? How are you? How have you been since yesterday? I'm fine, thank you. I'm fine, thank you, Antoine. Are you alright? You didn't hurt yourself? No, no, I'm fine.
Observed, it's okay, but here it's not okay. It's okay, it's not okay. It's okay, it's not okay. It's okay, it's not okay.
What's wrong, Antoine? Are you okay?
I'm fine, thank you.
That's not right. It's okay. It's not okay. It's okay. It's not okay.
Yes, it's fine.
This isn't right, it's not right, I don't want to get angry, but your models are really bad
marked hi hi how are you it's going it's going it's going it's not going well now observe goodbye and there goodbye my
Goodbye, madam. Goodbye, Wednesday. Goodbye, goodbye, Commissioner. Well, I'm going now. Goodbye.
Goodbye, Mrs. Laurieux, goodbye, hello to your parents, thank you, goodbye, goodbye, safe travels.
Goodbye sir, goodbye, thank you, goodbye, goodbye madam, goodbye sir
To cut. Goodbye. Goodbye. Goodbye. Goodbye. Goodbye. Goodbye. And now, observe. Hi. Hi. Hi. Hi. Well, I have to go. Hi. Good evening. Good night. Hi. Well, then, bye. Hi. Come on, bye. Hi. Goodbye. Goodbye. Hi. Goodbye, you. Hi.
Observe.
Where is she going? Where is she going?
She's going to university.
How are you doing?
I'm doing well, thanks.
She's doing well.
She's going to university.
She goes to university, she's doing well, she goes to university, she's doing well, she goes to university, she's doing well.
go she goes go goes it's the verb to go it goes it goes it goes it goes it goes him it goes you're well you're very well
How are you? I'm fine, thank you. I'm fine, thank you. They're going
"Bien" is the verb "aller" (to go): I am well, you are well, he is well, she is well.
They're all fine, they're all fine. Where are you going? Okay, let's go.
Let's go, where are you going? Where are you going? Like that, we're going to the university restaurant. I'm going, you're going, he's going, they're going.
go we go you go I go you go he/she/it goes we go you (plural) go they go I go goes
allons, aller, vont is the verb; je, tu, il, nous, vous, il, ce are the pronouns
topics I'm going to we're going I'm going to we're going I'm going to college we're going to
To the university restaurant. You're going, you're going. Where are you going? Where are you going like that? You
Go, you go. How are you? Where are you going? You're doing well. How are you? And
Are you well yourself? Ah, Robert! How are you, my dear little one? Observe. You
Are you going to the library? Yes, I'm going to the library. He's going to the library. He's going to the library. You
They're going to university.
Are you going to university?
Yes, we're going to university.
They go to university.
They're going to university.
I go, you go, he/she/it goes, we go, you (plural) go, they go.
He goes, Ousmane goes, Hubert goes, Fido goes, it's okay, he goes, she goes, Mireille goes, Colette goes, Aunt Georgette goes, she goes.
They go, Hubert and Ousmane go, Mireille and Ousmane go, the students go, they go.
They go. Mireille and Colette go. The students go. They go.
Now you are going to speak French.
Listen and respond.
Hey Hubert, hi, how are you?
Not bad. And you, how are you?
How are you.
Where are you going like that?
I'm going to university. And you?
Oh, I don't go to university.
Now, you will be Hubert. Listen and answer.
I'm not going to university.
Oh, I don't go to university.
Observe.
How are you?
How are you doing?
Look, it's Mireille, she's in a hurry, she's going to university.
Look, it's Mireille! No, but he's in a hurry. Is he going to university? No, he
He's not going to college, he's going to eat.
Look, is that Mireille? Yes, that's Mireille. And that, is that Mireille? No, that's Georgette. Does she go to university? No, she doesn't go to university. And that, is that Mireille?
Yes, it's Mireille! Hello, Miss Mireille!
How are you, Miss Mireille? Are you well? Is everything alright?
You're not sick? You're not tired, are you?
How are you, health-wise? Yes, Mr. Guignol. I'm fine, thank you.
Ah, excuse me, I'm in a hurry.
Ouch, ouch, ouch!
And how are you doing, Miss Mireille?
At university!
Ouch, ouch, ouch!
Goodbye, Miss Mireille!
Goodbye, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye!
...
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501