Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
On May 28, a young man arrived at Charles de Gaulle airport.
His name is Robert.
He takes a taxi to go to Paris.
...
He stays in a small hotel in the Latin Quarter, the Latin Man.
Now it's May 29th.
The two main characters in this fascinating story may meet.
It's a beautiful spring day, obviously.
And there's a student strike, obviously.
Mireille has been studying at the Sorbonne for a year.
She is studying art history.
Right now, she just went out
of the Institute of Art and Archaeology
and she rests on a chair in the Luxembourg Gardens.
It is currently 10 AM.
Robert has been in Paris since yesterday.
He leaves his hotel.
He will explore the Latin Quarter.
A young man is walking in the Luxembourg Gardens.
He looks bored.
He notices a very pretty red skirt on a green chair
He approaches
The girl wearing the red skirt pretends not to see him
She looks up
They are very blue
His gaze drifts into contemplation of the sky, which is also very blue.
What beautiful weather, what a sky!
Not a cloud
Not a cirrus
Not a bigoted one
Not a stratus
Not a cumulus cloud
The weather is really beautiful
Don't you think so?
No response.
A little chilly perhaps, don't you think?
Finally, it's not really cold.
No, I'm not saying that, but it's less hot than yesterday.
Do you come here often?
I really like Luxembourg.
Even when the weather is bad.
Even in winter, under the snow.
In spring, when the chestnut trees are in bloom.
in summer when it's so pleasant in the shade near the Medici fountain in autumn
when you shovel up the dead leaves
You think I'm stupid?
You're not talkative, are you? I really like that. I don't like girls who
Don't talk to me too much. I'm not boring you.
You have a very pretty skirt.
Here, I'll tell you where it comes from. I'm never wrong.
So, these buttons, this pocket, that's from Dior.
Non ?
These buttons aren't from Dior?
Okay, so they come from FAT.
Non ?
So, from Saint Laurent?
Ah.
Okay, so, from Courrèges.
From Lanvin, Cardin, Givenchy.
Presunique. I always get my clothes at Presunique.
She's gorgeous, though.
Allow me to introduce myself, my name is Jean-Pierre.
Jean-Pierre Bourdon.
Our story is very interesting, isn't it?
It's a fascinating story.
Look, here's a fascinating story.
This is a fascinating program.
And there you have it, a program that is not fascinating.
What a fascinating man!
And here is a lady who is fascinated.
In our fascinating story, there are two main characters, Mireille and Robert.
There are also less important characters, secondary characters, for example Georgette, Fido, Cécile.
Today, the two main characters of our story may, it's not certain, may meet.
Today, in history, is May 29th.
Present today, May 29th.
Passed yesterday, May 28th.
Future, tomorrow, May 30th.
Today is May 29th.
Yesterday was May 28th.
Tomorrow will be May 30th.
It's May.
May, April, June, that's spring. Spring. Summer, autumn, winter.
In spring, the trees are in bloom. That's spring.
In spring, the horse chestnut trees, the trees that produce chestnuts, are in bloom.
That's summer. That's summer too. And that's autumn.
In autumn, the leaves are yellow.
The dead leaves are falling
There are dead leaves everywhere
We shovel up the dead leaves.
Dead leaves and regrets too
What is gently stirring
And then, winter arrived.
That's winter.
In winter, there is snow
It's cold
In spring, it's less cold, it's nice.
In spring, it's nice and sunny.
It's hot in the summer.
In summer, it's pleasant in the shade.
In summer, it gets too hot in the sun.
And it's cooler in the shade.
There is plenty of shade near the Medici fountain.
Mireille likes the sun, but Madame Belleau prefers the shade
It's hot in the sun, it's cooler in the shade
In summer, it's hot, it's sunny
In autumn, it's less hot, it's cooler
In summer, in autumn
In winter, it is cold
It's snowing, it's raining
In summer
In autumn
In winter
In spring
It's warmer
The weather is nice
In summer
In autumn
In winter
In spring
It's cold
It's cool
In summer
It's hot
The weather is nice
In winter
The weather is bad
It's cold
It's cool
It's hot
The weather is nice
The weather is bad
Look. What season is this?
Is it spring or autumn?
It's spring.
Is it winter or summer now?
It's winter.
Is it autumn or spring now?
It's autumn.
Is this summer or winter?
It's summer.
And now, what's the weather like?
The weather is nice.
The weather is beautiful.
Ah, the weather is splendid, it's very beautiful today.
The weather here isn't nice, it's bad.
It's cold, it's hot
Now look, the weather isn't very nice, there are clouds
When the weather is very nice, there are no clouds.
There is sunshine here
It's windy here.
In winter, there is sometimes snow. Look, here there is snow, here there is wind, and here there is sun, but here there are clouds.
In the story, the weather is beautiful. It's a lovely spring day. The sun is shining, the sky is blue, there isn't a cloud in sight. The chestnut trees are in bloom, it's pleasant in the Luxembourg Gardens.
And there's a student strike. The students are on strike. The students are striking. The students aren't working. The students aren't studying.
They're not working to protest. They're on strike. There are strikes happening here. It's the workers who are on strike. Mireille is a student. She studies art history. She's studying art history. She's a student. She studies. She's studying.
She studies prehistoric art, Egyptian art, Greek art, medieval art, Renaissance art, classical art, 19th century art, and modern art.
Mireille has been a student for a year.
One year.
Robert has been in Paris since yesterday.
He has been in Paris since May 28th.
May 28, May 29, Robert is in Paris today, May 29, he has been in Paris since May 28.
Robert is in Paris today, May 29th, and he has been in Paris since May 28th.
He's been in Paris for a day.
He has been in Paris for one day, 24 hours.
Robert has been in Paris for 24 hours.
Mireille has been a student for a year.
Right now, Mireille isn't studying. She's sitting on a chair, resting. Ousmane is resting. Here, he works, he studies. And here, he rests. Mireille has been resting for five minutes. She's been resting on her chair for five minutes.
She's just left the Institute of Art and Archaeology. There's the Institute of Art and Archaeology. And here's Mireille leaving the Institute. Here she is leaving her house. She's coming from her house and she's going to university. Here she is coming from university and she's going home.
Now, observe this carefully.
Right now, Mireille is in the Institute and she is going to leave.
Now she's going out.
And now, she's just come out.
She's going out.
She goes out.
It just came out.
Future, she will go out.
She is present, she leaves.
Past, she just came out.
Mireille has just left the institute and is resting on a chair.
It is 10 o'clock. 10 o'clock in the morning.
It's 10 o'clock here too, but it's 10 PM.
In the morning, in the evening.
A young man is walking in the gardens.
Does he go to university? No.
Is he going to the movies? No. He's not going anywhere. He's taking a walk. Look at Robert here. He's taking a walk. That gentleman is taking a walk too. They're taking a walk too. That young man looks bored. He has nothing to do, so he's bored.
He notices Mireille. He approaches. He goes in Mireille's direction.
Here, it is Marie-Laure who approaches Mireille.
Mireille pretends not to see him. She sees him, she sees him, but she pretends not to see him.
Observe Marie-Laure here. She hears her mother. She hears her, but she pretends not to hear her.
Marie-Laure, do you work?
Marie-Laure pretends not to hear
And here, she will pretend to be asleep.
You'll see
She doesn't sleep
But she pretends to be asleep
Now, look at Mireille
She will look up
So
She looks up
Now she raises her head
Now she raises one arm
Now she lifts one leg. Mireille looks at the sky. She looks at the sky. Look at Mireille's gaze. Mireille's blue eyes are lost in the blue sky.
Look at Robert here. He's getting lost in the crowd.
Here, the road disappears into the vineyards.
Here, the peak disappears into the clouds.
Mireille's gaze drifts into contemplation of the sky.
Mireille gazes at the sky.
Here, Marie-Laure is gazing in contemplation at her new boat.
Here, Marie-Laure is contemplating a box of chocolates.
What beautiful weather, what a sky!
The young man becomes lyrical. He exclaims.
Ah, what weather, what beautiful weather, what a sky, what a beautiful sky, what a beautiful blue sky!
Listen to what Mireille says.
The sporty ones!
Now, observe this small scene.
"Hmm, what a beautiful dress! Is it new?"
"No, I've had it for a year."
"What beautiful weather! What a beautiful dress! What beautiful eyes! What a beautiful hand! What beautiful weather! What a beautiful dress! What beautiful eyes! What a beautiful hand!"
That's a lady who talks a lot. She's a chatty lady. She's a chatterbox.
She will be delighted by your acquaintance, and we will consider you unworthy.
What a chatterbox!
Yes, yes, yes!
Look at the young man, he's talkative.
Mireille isn't talkative, no. She doesn't say anything. It's the young man who's talkative.
He notices Mireille. He talks to her, but he doesn't know her.
He notices Mireille. He notices her.
She sees the young man, she sees him
He notices Mireille's eyes, he notices them
He finds Mireille pretty, he finds her pretty
Mireille doesn't find this young man interesting.
She doesn't find it amusing, she finds it boring.
This young man bores him
He bores Mireille, he is boring
He bores Mireille, he bores her.
Okay, let's get back to Mireille and this young man she doesn't know and who bores her.
So, these buttons, this pocket, that's from Dior.
A pocket
Nothing in my hands
Nothing in the pockets
Hands in pockets
Where are my gumballs?
Ah, in my pocket
And this is the revolver pocket
And this is a paperback book
A button
Buttons
A doorknob
A flower bud
She's very pretty though
What do you think of it?
She is lovely, very chic.
It's at least from Dior, or not really.
She's very chic, though.
Now, look at this scene.
Okay, come on, you're a nasty little girl, you're annoying.
But I still like you.
Stop, you're going to get sick.
I know, but oh well, I'll take another one anyway.
Mireille's skirt is from Prisunique
Prisunique, Monoprix, Uniprix – these aren't very chic stores.
That's a dress that might be from Dior.
Hmm, they are beautiful
Where do they come from?
That comes from our place
You see, I'm never wrong
Oh really? You never make a mistake? Well then, nine times nine?
Seventy-two.
Ha ha! You're mistaken, my dear. Nine times nine in eighty-one.
Are you sure?
Yes. I never make mistakes.
Look at that young girl. She's gone through the wrong door.
Look at this gentleman. He's picked up the wrong bottle.
Everyone can make mistakes.
Of course Mireille makes mistakes sometimes.
But me, me, I never make mistakes.
It's professional.
You students make mistakes sometimes.
But I'm the teacher, I never make mistakes.
To be wrong.
Mireille is mistaken, you are mistaken, everyone is mistaken.
But I never make mistakes.
Now, pay close attention.
Look at Aunt Georgette here. What is she doing?
She's walking her dog. And what's that young man doing?
He is taking a walk.
Aunt Georgette is walking her dog, she's walking him,
and the young man goes for a walk.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
There, Marie-Laure looks at Mireille. She looks at her.
And here, is Marie-Laure looking at Mireille? No, she's looking at herself. And the gentleman in this drawing by Saint-Pé, what is he doing? He's looking at himself.
Let's take another example. Look at Mireille. She raises her arm, she raises her right leg, and now she stands up. She raises her arm, she raises it, and she stands up.
Look at Robert here.
He gets up.
Mireille gets up.
Look at Marie-Laure.
She dresses her doll.
Here, she gets dressed.
She dresses her doll, she dresses the doll, and she dresses herself.
Mireille says she gets her clothes at Prisunic.
She should buy all her clothes, dresses, skirts, and sweaters at Prisunic.
Prisunic. I always shop at Prisunic.
Finally, the young man introduces himself
Allow me to introduce myself, my name is Jean-Pierre, Jean-Pierre Bourdon
Look at this gentleman, he's going to introduce himself, his name is Jean-Pierre too
Allow me to introduce myself, Jean-Pierre Landru
My name is Mireille, Mireille Bello
What's your name ?
Marie-Laure
And you, what is your name?
My name is Colette, Colette Besson
"My name is Pierre."
Okay, let's recap.
Look at this drawing of Saint-Pé.
What is this man doing?
He is taking a walk.
He notices something.
They are ants.
And there, he observes the ants.
He is gazing in contemplation at the ants.
He is lost in contemplation of the ants.
Now you are going to speak French.
Watch the meeting between Mireille and Jean-Pierre Bourdon.
You will repeat Jean-Pierre's answers.
What beautiful weather, what a sky, not a cloud in sight.
The weather is really beautiful. Don't you think?
Now it's your turn. Now, you are Jean-Pierre.
What beautiful weather, what beautiful weather, what a sky, not a cloud in sight.
What a sky! Not a cloud in sight.
The weather is really beautiful. Don't you think?
Okay, now we're going to play a game.
Fun and useful for learning French.
What can we do?
You can go skiing.
Yes, you can go skiing. What else?
Water skiing.
You can go mountaineering.
Yes, you can go mountaineering, yes. What else?
You can go sailing.
You can go rock climbing.
We can study.
We can go on strike
We can take a nap
We can paint someone's portrait
One can be one meter seventy
Or one meter sixty-three like Mireille
We can pretend to be asleep
Okay, now what can he do?
The weather can be nice
The weather can be bad
It can get cold
It can get hot
Okay, we've been playing this silly game for an hour now.
It's starting to bore me.
Okay, that's enough.
We're going to take a nap.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
...
Subtitles ST' 501
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.