Subtitles ST' 501
and get involved. Very soon, you will see what is happening and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
In lesson 12, our American, Robert, explores the Latin Quarter. He follows
a few high school players in the Sorbonne district. Mireille, who is in
His path to school ended, purely by chance, in the same place.
What a beautiful spring day!
It's May 29th.
Today, the two main characters of this fascinating story
They will surely meet.
It is currently 10:30 AM.
Robert explores the small streets of the Lata district.
Oh !
Oh, damn bag!
Wait, madam, I'll help you.
It doesn't matter.
There you go.
Which way are you going?
Ah, yes.
I will accompany you.
Thank you, young man. You are very kind.
It's nothing, madam. Please.
A young man is walking in the Luxembourg Gardens.
He looks bored.
What beautiful weather, what a sky, not a cloud in sight.
Mireille goes home.
She finds her little sister at home.
What are you doing here? Aren't you at school?
No, my throat hurts.
Hey, you've got some mail. A postcard.
Brickton, England, 25 mai.
My dear Mireille, the weather is dreadful.
There's fog every morning.
It rains every afternoon
Even when it's not raining, the sky is overcast.
You can't play tennis
But the lawn is magnificent
Bruce too, I send you my love, Guylaine
Where is Brickton?
Brighton, pas Brickton
Yes, where is it?
In England, of course.
Ah, and Bruce, what's this all about?
It's a name
A name for what?
From boy
De gazon ?
Are you a boy, deaf or just stupid?
Is it English?
Obviously
Ah, and who is this Bruce?
He's Guylaine's boyfriend.
Is he English?
Well, yes, why not?
Well, my little friends aren't English.
And why is the grass so beautiful?
Because it's raining a lot.
Does it rain all the time in England?
Oh yes, just like in Brittany.
Poor Guylaine.
I'll call him, then.
Hello, hello Guylaine, is that you? It's me, Mireille. I just read your card. The weather isn't great.
So? Oh no, the weather's bad. What if it's nice? The weather's awful. The weather's
Magnificent. The sky is grey. The sky is blue. The weather is overcast. There isn't a cloud in the sky. It's raining.
It's sunny here. It's cold. It's hot. She catches rubs. She catches blows.
Sun. I'm going broke buying aspirin. I'm going broke buying sunscreen. And apart from that, how are you? Yeah, well,
Yes, it's fine.
You too ?
Yes, I'm fine.
When are you coming back?
The 2.
Well then, soon then.
Okay, kisses.
I send you a kiss.
Bye.
Hello.
Are you leaving?
Yes.
Where are you going?
At university.
Do you have any English boyfriends at university?
Mind your own business.
It is 10:40 AM
Robert continue son exploration
of the Latin Quarter
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Robert discovers the Pantheon.
He sees a group of protesters coming from Soufflé Street.
They are shouting incomprehensible phrases.
They take Boulevard Saint-Michel
and head towards the Place de la Sorgol.
Robert stops a passerby.
What is it?
What's going on?
I don't know. Is it a protest?
A demonstration.
Ah, this Robert.
and he follows the demonstrators, he enters with them into the courtyard of the Sorbonne
Meanwhile, Mireille arrives via the street of the schools
She enters the Sorbonne, crosses the corridor, and stops to look at a notice board.
She passes under the arches
And is located in the courtyard
Robert is also in the courtyard
She comes very close to him
He immediately notices her elegant figure
She is wearing a rather short red skirt
And a rather tight-fitting white sweater
He finds his face pleasing
And he smiled at him
She looks at him with amusement and smiles back.
Who is the main character in this story?
Mireille or Robert?
Robert
Mireille
Do you think it's Mireille?
No, it's Robert
Let's say that in this story, there are two main characters
Mireille et Robert
There are secondary characters like Aunt Georgette, Hubert, Colette and two main characters, Mireille and Robert.
Robert, one of the main characters, explores the Latin Quarter.
Here's Robert, the explorer. He's off to explore the Latin Quarter.
While exploring the Latin Quarter, he encounters an old woman with an old bag.
Oh, damn bag!
A shopping bag.
A handbag. A backpack.
The old woman is carrying an old, damaged shopping bag.
Oh, damn bag! What a piece of junk!
Ah, what a mess!
Robert helps the old woman.
Here, Mireille is helping Marie-Laure.
But wait! I'll help you.
Can I help you, madam?
Oh, you're very kind.
Wait, madam, I'll help you.
It doesn't matter.
It's not serious.
Now, look at this.
That's serious.
Look at this little girl crying.
This is serious.
Is it really that serious?
Very serious.
Very, very serious.
Look, that's not it either.
It's not serious.
The gentleman here is late.
But it's not a big deal.
Robert accompanies the old woman.
Here, a young girl offers to accompany an old lady.
Robert accompanies the old lady and she thanks him
Meanwhile, Mireille returns home.
There, she leaves her house
And here, she goes home.
She goes out, she comes back in
She goes out, goes out, she comes back in, comes back in.
Look at Marie-Laure here, she's going to school.
Attention, school.
Marie-Laure is 10 years old, normally she goes to school, she goes to primary school.
But today, Marie-Laure is not at school.
Isn't she at school?
She is not at school because she has a sore throat.
No, my throat hurts.
This little boy, however, has a stomachache.
And this gentleman has a sore hand. He hurt himself.
Yes. He hurt himself.
Marie-Laure, on the other hand, is in pain all over.
My head hurts. My neck hurts.
My throat hurts. My eyes hurt.
My fingers hurt. My leg hurts.
My ear hurts. My stomach hurts.
She has a headache, an earache, a stomachache, eye pain, and a toothache.
Look at poor Marie-Laure. Where does she hurt?
Her fingers hurt, her leg hurts, her stomach hurts, her eyes hurt, she has a headache.
There's mail for the children.
Marie-Laure, I have some mail for you.
Ah, so, letters, a postcard, leaflets, notes, a newspaper.
Hey, you've got some mail, a postcard.
This is a postcard from Guylaine, a friend of Mireille who is in England.
She says the weather isn't nice, it's awful.
The weather here is magnificent.
But the weather here is awful.
That's a hideous monster.
Here is a hideous beast, here is another hideous beast, and here is a hideous head, and here is hideous weather.
There is fog every morning.
Look, what is it? Fog.
There's fog here too. There's often fog in England.
It rains every afternoon.
In the morning, at noon, in the afternoon, in the evening, at night.
The sky is overcast.
There are clouds. The weather is overcast. The sky is overcast.
But the lawn is magnificent.
And why is the grass so beautiful?
Because it's raining a lot.
In England, the grass is magnificent because it rains a lot.
And because the English take great care of their lawns.
Does it rain often in England?
Not all the time, no. But often.
In England, it rains all the time. And there's often fog.
It's true ?
Yes, finally. The French say so. Look.
What do you think the weather is generally like in England?
Pretty bad. It's raining, it's foggy.
In England, there is mist and fog. The weather is not very nice.
Now you are going to speak French
Listen to this dialogue between Mireille and Guylaine
You will repeat Mireille's answers
The sky is grey
The sky is blue
It's raining
It's sunny here
It's cold
It's hot
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille
The sky is grey
The sky is blue
Now it's your turn.
It's raining
It's sunny here
Now it's your turn.
It's sunny here.
It's cold.
It's hot.
Now it's your turn.
Very well. Now, let's get back to Mireille and Marie-Laure.
The lawn is magnificent.
Bruce too.
Who is this Bruce?
He's Guylaine's boyfriend.
And he's English?
Of course, he is English.
Why not ?
Do you have any English boyfriends at university?
Mind your own business.
Mireille doesn't like people interfering in her affairs.
Who are you writing to? Your boyfriend?
Mind your own business.
Here, take care of your doll and leave me alone.
Marie-Laure also doesn't like people interfering in her affairs.
Are you working? Mind your own business.
But she enjoys taking care of her doll.
What are you doing ?
I'm taking care of my doll
Oh, you're taking care of your doll
Yes, I'm taking care of my doll, so what?
She is taking care of her doll
Are you taking care of your doll?
Yes, I'm taking care of my doll
She is taking care of her doll
Here, take care of your doll
Are you taking care of your doll?
"Take care of your doll. Look at Marie-Laure now."
"Marie-Laure, get up."
" Yeah ! "
"Well, are you getting up?"
"Yeah, I'm getting up!"
"Come on, get up!"
There are people who don't like getting up.
"But get up, it's already noon!"
"Oh, shut up, will you let me sleep in peace!"
"Are you getting up? Get up."
Mireille calls Guylaine on the phone.
Marie-Laure!
Mrs. Bello calls Marie-Laure.
It's the verb "to call".
They call their friends.
I think they're calling you.
He calls too.
Cle, Leva, Paul!
He calls his children.
To call.
She calls, I call, you call, they call, we call, you call.
She catches colds
The little boy catches the ball
The rugby player catches the ball
Look at Marie-Laure here
Oh my god, look at that!
Come on, go home, we'll change you
But you'll catch a cold.
She has a cold.
She caught a cold.
You can catch a cold, you can get sunburned.
Be careful, you're going to get sunburned.
Here, put on some sunscreen.
23 francs, 46, 69, 92, 115 francs.
I'm spending a fortune on sunscreen oil.
50.
You're going to ruin yourself, sir.
Yes, I'm spending a fortune on postcards.
Are you leaving?
Yes.
Mireille leaves, Mireille returns.
Marie-Laure leaves, Marie-Laure returns.
I'll be right back.
He's leaving, but he'll be back right away.
And there he is again.
Mireille enters the Sorbonne.
Mireille is leaving the Sorbonne.
Mireille enters the classroom.
Mireille leaves the classroom.
She enters the classroom.
She leaves the classroom.
She leaves her house.
She goes home. She leaves her house. She goes home.
To go out. She leaves her house. He leaves his house. I leave my house.
Are you leaving your house? We're leaving our house. Are you leaving your house?
They leave their homes.
Mireille takes the street of schools. The protesters take the boulevard Saint-Michel.
She takes. They take. It's the verb "to take".
Now they are taking Boulevard Saint-Michel.
That's a street, the street of schools.
That's a boulevard, Saint-Michel Boulevard.
That's an avenue, General Leclerc Avenue.
That's a square, Place Saint-Sulpice.
Robert stops a passerby.
Mireille stops.
The protesters are shouting.
Look at this man, he's going to scream.
I'm being pushed!
She screams.
They are shouting too.
So, you start shouting, you get angry, you get angry, you shout.
He is calm, but he is shouting.
So I'm calm and I'm listening to you!
The protesters are also shouting.
They are shouting incomprehensible phrases.
The protesters are shouting is a phrase.
"He shouts" is a sentence, but "he" is not a sentence, it's a word.
"Scream" is not a sentence, it's a word, a verb.
Robert doesn't understand the phrases the protesters are shouting.
These are incomprehensible sentences.
She too is shouting incomprehensible phrases.
Robert is following the protesters.
And I am Robert.
No, I am Robert.
Yes, you are Robert and I am following you.
Come on, come on, follow the protesters.
I am Robert, he follows Robert, that's the verb to follow.
I am Robert, he is Robert, it's the verb to be.
I am Robert, he follows Robert, he follows the protesters, follow the protesters.
He follows Mireille. He follows a young girl. He follows a gentleman. He too follows a gentleman. He follows a young woman. Follow the guide. You must follow the guide. Follow me. Follow the arrow. You must always follow the arrows. You must always follow the arrows.
Mireille arrives at the Sorbonne via the school street
She enters the Sorbonne, crosses the corridor
Stops to look at a notice board
The corridor, the courtyard, a notice board
That's an Ingres painting
A blackboard, a dashboard, a display board
Mireille is in the courtyard of the Sorbonne
Robert is also in the courtyard of the Sorbonne
He gets very close to her, and immediately notices her elegant figure.
There you have it, an elegant silhouette.
A less elegant silhouette.
Look at Jean-Claude here, he's elegant.
Mireille is wearing a rather tight-fitting white sweater.
Here, she is wearing a white sweater that is not at all clingy.
She is wearing a red skirt.
Here, she is wearing jeans.
Marie-Laure is wearing jeans.
She also carries her boat.
Here, she is carrying plates.
The old woman is carrying a bag.
Robert finds Mireille's face pleasant.
A pleasant face.
A less pleasant face.
Robert smiled at Mireille.
He smiled at her.
He smiled.
The Mona Lisa is smiling.
Look at this man.
The photographer says, "Smile, smile."
But he didn't smile.
Now he's smiling.
And this gentleman, he doesn't smile. The woman tells him to smile, smile, but he doesn't smile. Robert smiles at Mireille. Robert smiles. Mireille smiles back. She smiles back at Robert. It's the verb "to smile back." Observe.
Hey, give me back my gumballs!
Give me back my gumballs!
Yes, I'll give them back to you.
Give them back to me right now!
Here, here are your gumballs, I'm giving them back to you.
Mireille returns her gumballs to Marie-Laure.
She gives them back to him.
Okay, let's see what you have to say now.
Is Robert a minor character in our story?
No, he's a main character.
Alright.
What is Mireille doing here?
She leaves her house.
And then she goes home.
Look at Marie-Laure.
Where does it hurt?
Her leg hurts.
At the head.
In the eyes.
What is this man doing?
He calls.
And what is this young girl doing?
She smiled.
And what is Jean-Claude doing here?
He follows Robert.
I have gumballs, I have gumballs, you don't.
Oh, I'm being followed, I think someone is following me.
Who is following me?
Who could possibly be following me?
Why are you following me?
Hey, my gumballs, give me back my gumballs, give them back to me.
Would you please give me back my gumballs?
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501
the French NGO, the Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.
For more information on this and other ANENBERG programs,
Call 1-800-LEARNER and visit us at www.learner.org.