Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
The Latin Quarter in Paris.
It's a beautiful spring morning.
It is 11 o'clock.
It's May 29th.
There is a student strike, obviously.
Robert, a young American, has just arrived in Paris.
He is currently in the courtyard of the Sormone.
He smiled at a young girl.
Mireille, a young French woman studying art history,
is also in the courtyard of the Sormona.
She smiled at a young man.
Another young man crosses the Place de la Sormone.
He looks bored.
He approaches a young girl.
Excuse me, miss.
Do you have a light, please?
Meanwhile, on the second floor of the Sorbonne, about ten students are waiting in front of an office.
A young man arrives.
Hey, it's the same one.
He assesses the situation and immediately heads towards Phil's head.
He approaches a young brunette girl wearing a purple dress.
Is that you? What are you doing here?
How have things been since last year?
The young girl looks at him in astonishment.
What, you don't recognize me?
But yes, come on, we were last in Saint-Tropez.
Me? In Saint-Tropez? Impossible.
First of all, I hate Saint-Tropez.
Then there are the girls, the rich kids, and the idiots, that's really not my type.
And I hate summer.
I spend all my summers in Patagonia.
Because summer there is winter.
Elementary, my dear Watson.
You see, your thing with me, it doesn't work.
Voices are beginning to protest.
So, no cheating, eh?
No, the gatecrasher.
Ah, the queue!
But it's okay, I'll go to the back of the queue, if you can give me more pride.
And by the way, now, where are we going?
The young man will position himself at the end of the line.
He approaches a young girl wearing a green dress.
Excuse me, miss, do you have a light?
No, I don't smoke. Ask Jean-Luc.
And ?
There you go.
He holds out his Bic lighter.
THANKS.
My name is Jean-Pierre Bourdon. And you?
Jean-Luc Marchand.
And you ?
This is Annick. Her brother Philippe, Nadia, Ousmane, her friends.
What are you studying?
I study sociology and law.
Ah, you're right. Law can lead to anything.
And you ?
She's a math whiz.
Ah, yeah. That doesn't surprise me.
Today, all girls do math.
It's the new trend.
I have a friend who just started at Polytechnique.
But it's a brain, right?
She wants to specialize in computer science.
That's something that has a future, that's computer science.
Biology too, mind you.
Or astrophysics.
I don't really know what I'm going to do yet.
For now, I'm doing a master's degree in psychology.
I might study medicine.
Or... or psychoanalysis.
In any case, the psychologists are making a killing, that's for sure.
Or maybe I'll go to HEC, you know.
Or the IDEC.
You don't seem very settled, do you?
Oh, no.
I don't want to decide too young, it's too dangerous.
And how old are you, exactly?
Me? 29 years old, why?
Oh, nothing. Just like that.
You need to know.
Hey! Come see, come see! There's a great girl over there!
What ?
That's Gata Garbo's little girl.
Seriously, where?
There, there, in the courtyard on the right.
Which one? The one with the white trousers, the blue and green blouse, and the scarf?
No, not that one, the other one next to it.
Oh, the blondes?
No, not the one with the white sweater and that horrible red prison skirt smiling like an idiot.
No, it's the popular one, the redhead, with the grey jeans and black jacket.
I know her, the redhead. She studies Russian at the language school.
But she's not Greta Garbo's granddaughter.
Ah good ?
Moreover, Greta Garbo had never had any children.
Oh, okay. In any case, it's still very good.
Look, there's a strange-looking guy approaching her
A guy with a black raincoat and a black hat
He's going to try to flirt with her, that's for sure.
There he goes, he asks her for a light
It's classic, it's even a bit basic
Yes, I think we can say that, this thing probably doesn't work very often.
And how do you go about starting a conversation?
I don't know, there are loads of things
There's no shortage of things
Okay, for example, you say, hey, that's you.
What are you doing here?
How have things been since last year?
Okay, the girl looks at you with a surprised expression.
What? You don't recognize me?
You don't remember me? Of course you do, last summer in Saint-Tropez,
or last winter in Courchevel, or in Patagonia.
Or last year in Marionne-Bade.
What? You're not... And you say a name.
Catherine Deneuve, Créta Garbeau, Jacqueline Dupont.
Nonsense, no, it's crazy how much you look like them then, but where is it that
You spend your holidays, well, that's something that works.
Either every time, or I don't know, you're just pretending to fall
in front of her on a staircase, or maybe, I don't know, you leave her there.
If papers fall in front of her, she helps you pick them up; you thank her and...
Here we go, all this isn't exactly new, we know it.
had nothing better
It's not going fast, is it? You've been waiting for a good half hour.
Oh darn it, I can't stay myself. I have a date with a gorgeous girl at school. I'm off.
The young man leaves.
Oh my god, that guy stinks. A gorgeous girl, he sounds like he's talking about a horse.
Who does he think he is? What a horrible womanizer.
He imagines that girls are only there to fall into his arms, maybe.
He's not even handsome.
What an idiot.
It kills me, guys like that.
Well, he's not very clever, but he's harmless.
Well, that's it. Defend him.
You men are all the same, all equally sexist.
You're registered with the MLF now.
When I see guys like you, I really want to sign up, you know.
Okay, let's see now.
A young man crosses the boulevard
People are crossing the street
The bridge crosses the Seine
The young man crosses
This young man is Jean-Pierre, Jean-Pierre Bourdon
He's a womanizer
He tries to flirt with all the girls
Here, he's trying to flirt with Mireille.
Here, he's trying to pick up another girl
Here, he's trying to pick up another girl again.
He's a womanizer
This gentleman is also a womanizer
Jean-Pierre has several tricks for picking up girls.
Several systems
For example, he said
Hey, it's you, what are you doing here?
What, you don't recognize me?
It's a thing, a system.
Uncle Guillaume knows a few things too.
I'm going to take your nose.
There you go.
For me, it's not my nose, it's something.
Jean-Claude has some tricks up his sleeve too.
Look.
It's a trick that works every time.
You'll see.
That's not right, is it?
You see, it's a good idea.
That works.
But in this case, it doesn't work.
This phone doesn't work.
One of Jean-Pierre's tricks for starting a conversation with a young girl is to ask her if she has a light.
Excuse me, miss, do you have a light, please?
That's a traffic light. She has a red light, an orange light, and a green light. Jean-Luc has a light. He has a lighter because he smokes. But Annick doesn't have a light because she doesn't smoke.
Excuse me, miss, do you have a light?
No, I don't smoke.
Look at that man, he's smoking. That woman is smoking too. And there's a tractor smoking. That's a fire smoking. That's smoke.
About ten students are waiting outside an office at the Sorbonne. This is Mr. Bello's office at Renault. This is Mrs. Bello's office at the Ministry of Health.
These students are waiting
This lady is waiting, she's waiting for the bus
The bicycles are waiting for Mireille to have lunch
These gentlemen are waiting
They too are waiting
The students are waiting
They are queuing
They form a line
The front of the line, the tail
And there, the tip of the tail
Here's a finger and the tip of your finger
That's a street
And here's the end of the street
The students are queuing
They are waiting
It's not going fast
Now, yes, now it's going fast
Jean-Pierre arrive
He is examining the situation
He observes, he studies the situation
Here, Robert examines his map of Paris.
And then, Mireille examines the map
And here's a doctor examining a patient.
And this gentleman is examining a procession of ants.
When Jean-Pierre moves towards the front of the line, voices begin to protest.
He doesn't cheat the system.
In line, like everyone else.
He's cutting in line because he's not going to the queue like everyone else.
He's cheating the system.
Look at this man.
The French like to cheat the system.
Jean-Pierre Bourdon says there are many tricks to start a conversation
There are lots of things
There's no shortage of things
Finally, there's no shortage of things
Miss
Look here
Something is missing here.
Something is missing
What's missing?
Ah, the glasses
It's the glasses that are missing
Now, there's no shortage of glasses in France.
There's plenty of coffee. There's no shortage of cafes.
There are also many churches. There's no shortage of churches.
There are also many castles. There's no shortage of castles.
There's no shortage of things to do.
One of the tricks is to pretend to fall down a staircase.
And there we go, it's started.
A staircase, that's a staircase.
There's no shortage of stairs.
Obviously, you mustn't actually fall.
You have to pretend to fall.
You have to pretend like Mireille, remember?
She sees Jean-Pierre, but she pretends not to see him.
Here, Marie-Laure is pretending to be asleep.
Another trick is to drop papers in front of the girl.
The young girl helps you pick them up, you thank her, and there you go, off you go.
For that, you have to drop your papers.
Here, Jean-Pierre drops his papers.
Here, Marie-Laure drops the snack tray.
And this lady drops a statue.
But Jean-Pierre's big trick is to pretend to know the girl.
Hey, it's you. How have you been since last year?
You don't remember me? Of course you do.
Last summer in Saint-Tropez, or last winter in Courchevel, or in Patagonia, or last year in Marienbad.
Last summer, last winter, last year, last month.
Let's see.
If we are in May, then April was last month.
And June is next month.
Jean-Pierre pretends to have met the young girl last summer in Saint-Tropez.
Yes, of course, last summer in Saint-Tropez.
In Saint-Tropez? Why Saint-Tropez?
Well, because Saint-Tropez is very well-known, very chic
Everyone goes to Saint-Tropez
There are girls, rich kids who have money, yachts
In winter, everyone, well almost everyone, goes to Courchevel
Or perhaps, or perhaps in Patagonia
All of Jean-Pierre's stuff, it's all old stuff
It's not exactly new.
None of this is new, we're familiar with it.
But that, that, that's nothing new.
This is not a new house.
This house is not new.
None of this is new, we're familiar with it.
You have nothing better.
It's not very new.
Jean-Luc studies sociology.
He also practices law.
He is studying at the law school.
If you study law, you can become a lawyer, magistrate, judge.
The law leads to everything.
Ah, you're right. Law can lead to anything.
And this road leads to Montargis and Auxerre.
They say all roads lead to Rome.
And crime leads to prison.
I study sociology and law.
Ah, you're right.
He's right.
I'm going to bed.
Yes, you're right. Go to bed. Good night, my little one.
Good night.
Jean-Pierre's girlfriend is a math whiz. She's very intelligent.
Today, all girls are doing math. It's the new trend.
This is the new trend. Look.
But everyone is wearing dark glasses. It's the new fashion.
Jean-Pierre's girlfriend is a math whiz. She's very good at math. She's very intelligent. She's a brain.
And him, does he have a brain? No, he doesn't have a brain. He's all brawn, nothing in his head.
But Jean-Pierre's girlfriend, now that's a brain. She just got into IX, the Polytechnic School. Because she wants to specialize in computer science. She wants to work with computers. Or maybe astrophysics.
Jean-Pierre, on the other hand, studies psychology. He might go into medicine. To be a doctor, you have to study medicine. Or perhaps he'll become a psychoanalyst. Because psychoanalysts make a fortune. Psychoanalysts get paid a lot. They become rich.
Or perhaps he will go to HEC, the business school, to enter the world of business.
Or, he'll do IDEC, to become a filmmaker.
He hasn't made up his mind. He's hesitating. He can't decide, like Marie-Laure, look here.
I can't make up my mind.
Ben, make up your mind.
Jean-Pierre doesn't want to make a decision too young.
Because it's too dangerous
I don't want to decide too young, it's too dangerous.
Ice skating is dangerous too
Fencing is dangerous too
Very dangerous
And how old are you?
I'm 29 years old, why?
29 years old?
That's rather old for a student, isn't it?
Are you a student?
Yes, I'm at university.
How old are you ?
I am 21 years old.
Are you working?
No, I'm a student.
How old are you ?
I am 20 years old.
Okay, now it's your turn.
You will speak French.
Listen to this dialogue between the professor and the young girl.
Are you a student?
Yes, I'm at university.
Now it's your turn.
You are the young girl.
Answer.
Are you a student?
Yes, I'm at university.
How old are you ?
I am 21 years old.
What are your thoughts on psychoanalysis?
Psychoanalysis is interesting.
In any case, the psychologists are making a killing, that's for sure.
– Jean-Luc and Jean-Pierre are trying to identify people based on what they are wearing.
There is a young girl wearing a purple dress.
That's a red skirt.
And these are blue pants.
That's a blouse.
And this is a shirt, a pink shirt.
A blouse for a woman and a shirt for a man.
This is a black jacket and this is a scarf.
The young girl wearing a black jacket and jeans is a redhead.
She's a redhead too. She speaks Russian.
Is she Russian?
No, she's not Russian, she's a redhead
She's a red-haired French woman who speaks Russian.
She studies Russian and Oriental languages.
She's a French redhead who speaks Russian
She's a redhead, but she's not Russian.
Yes, that's a Russian woman, a red-haired Russian woman.
Now, pay very close attention, look
That's a dark-haired Russian woman.
Jean-Pierre says that one of the young girls in the courtyard is Greta Garbo's granddaughter.
Which one? The one with the white trousers, the blue and green blouse, and the scarf?
No, not that one, the other one next to it.
Look. Which one is it?
This one? That one?
The one wearing a skirt?
The one with the blue sweater?
The one next door?
Jean-Pierre leaves because he feels the queue isn't moving fast enough.
It's not going fast, is it?
How long have you been waiting?
A good half hour.
Oh darn it, I can't stay myself.
I have a date with a gorgeous girl at school.
Well, I'm out of here.
He doesn't stay, he leaves, he runs away.
Observe what Marie-Laure says here.
Are you coming?
No, I'm staying.
Okay, whatever you want.
Marie-Laure remains in Luxembourg.
Jean-Pierre is not staying because he has an appointment.
Here's a date.
That's a business meeting.
And that's a date.
Annick doesn't find Jean-Pierre very nice.
She finds it smelly.
Oh dear, that guy stinks.
It stinks. It stinks.
Oh dear, it stinks in here!
But what smells so bad?
It's that cheese that stinks.
Oh my god, that guy stinks!
Who does he think he is?
This Jean-Pierre fancies himself a Don Juan.
Here, look at this
That's Napoleon
And that's Robert, who thinks he's Napoleon.
That's Louis XIV
That's Robert, thinking he's Louis XIV.
He imagines that the girls are there to fall into his arms, maybe.
What an idiot.
It kills me, guys like that.
It's killing me.
Ah, it kills me, guys like that.
Well, Phil isn't very bright, but he's harmless.
That's a harmless animal.
But this is not a harmless animal.
Ah, you men are all the same.
Hey, you're registered with the MLF now.
MLF, Movement for the Liberation of Women.
Okay, look at this young man. What is he doing?
He's trying to flirt with Mireille.
Does it work?
Non.
And now, look at this young man.
Hey, it's you! What are you doing here?
How have things been since last week?
Oh, you have a very pretty red skirt.
You don't recognize me?
Oh, I'd kill guys like that.
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
French subtitles?