Subtitles ST' 501
You have to look and fly away.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few words in French yourself.
Robert and Mireille meet in the Sorbonne district.
They know each other.
When Mireille realizes she is late for an appointment,
She leaves,
leaving Robert to contemplate the spring day
and write a postcard to his mother.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Excuse me, miss, what's going on?
What is this about? What is he praying for? Why is he demonstrating?
I don't know, but they're probably right.
It's really beautiful, isn't it?
Yes, it's a beautiful morning.
Are you a student?
Yes, I study art history.
I come from the United States.
Ah, you're American.
Yes.
But you don't have an accent at all, for an American.
It's very kind of you to say that, but you know, I don't deserve any credit.
My mother is French.
Ah, your mother is French?
Yes.
When I was a child, I always spoke French with her.
How long have you been in France?
No, only since yesterday.
I just arrived.
And where do you live?
At the university residence?
The university campus?
The American house?
Oh no, I live in a small hotel in the neighborhood, the Home Latin.
It's not luxurious, but it's clean and not very expensive.
And do you come to France often?
No, this is the first time.
My mother is French, but my father didn't like France very much.
When I was little, we used to spend our holidays
in Bermuda or Latin America, where my father had interests.
Were you spending your holidays in South America?
But why do you say, my father didn't like it, had interests?
Is your father...
Oh no, no, no.
My father is still alive.
He is even in excellent health.
But my parents are divorced and I no longer live with them.
My mother has remarried, this time to an Argentinian.
So Bermuda, family holidays, all that is in the past.
I understand.
And what did your father do when you were little?
He worked in a bank.
In fact, he has been working at the same bank for 25 years.
Oh yes ?
And what kind of work does he do?
Is he a cashier, a night watchman?
He is the vice-president.
There's no such thing as a career leap, as my Aunt Georgette says.
Mireille remained silent for a few moments.
Excuse me, I have to go home.
Is it far from where you live?
Would you be willing to allow me to accompany you?
No, it's not far, it's very close to here.
And I'm happy to allow you to accompany me, as you say.
That's not what we say.
Yes, yes, but you look so ceremonious.
It's because I don't want to bother you.
You don't bore me at all.
Actually, to be honest, I think you're quite nice.
Finally, I mean friendly.
Look, if you like, we can go sit for a few minutes in the Luxembourg Gardens.
It's very close to here and it's right next to my house.
And they go to the Luxembourg Gardens.
That's the Senate.
This is where the senators meet.
I live right across the street.
Hey, let's be here
Oh dear, I forgot
I had to take my little sister to her dance class at 11:30.
What time is it? Noon? But what will Mom say? Excuse me, I'm off.
In the evening, on the corner of Place Saint-Michel, Robert is sitting on the terrace of a café.
He's going to write a postcard to his mom.
My dear mother.
What can I get you?
A coffee, please.
An express? Very well.
I am sitting on the terrace of a café in Place Saint-Michel.
THANKS.
The sun is setting.
The sky is completely red behind the Louvre.
The weather is very mild.
It's a beautiful evening.
Parisian women wear white sweaters and red skirts.
They are very nice.
Goodbye, Robert.
Do you have any shades available, please?
Oh no, you have to go to a post office or a tobacconist's shop.
Oh really? How much is it?
4 francs 50.
Where is there a post office?
There's one over there, on the other side of the bridge, to the right.
Okay, thank you.
Oh darn, it's closed.
It's May 29th.
It is 11 o'clock.
Observe.
It's May 29th. It's 11 o'clock. It's June 10th. It's 9:10 am. It's summer. It's noon. It's morning. It's 7 o'clock. It's Monday. It's 8 o'clock. It's Tuesday. It's 9 o'clock.
Let's see if you can answer. What date is it? It's May 29th. And what date is this? It's May 28th. Careful. Now, what day is it? It's Wednesday.
And what day is it now?
It's Saturday
It's Thursday
Now, pay attention!
What season is it?
It's spring
And what season is it here?
It's winter
What time is it?
It is eleven o'clock
It is 2 o'clock.
Look at this young woman.
She's going to ask what time it is.
What time is it?
8:30.
We also say what time it is.
Look.
Oh, but what time is it?
12:10, miss.
So, what time is it?
Oh la la!
Let's continue now.
What day is it?
It's May 29th.
What season is it? It's spring. What time is it? It's 10:50. Well, it's May 29th, it's 10:50, it's morning. It's a beautiful spring morning.
It's evening here.
It's a beautiful spring evening.
It's evening, it's a beautiful spring evening.
It's morning, it's a beautiful spring morning.
There are protesters.
Robert doesn't know what they're saying.
He doesn't know why they are protesting.
He doesn't know what's going on.
Excuse me, miss, what's going on?
Look at the little girl here.
That's not going well.
And his father doesn't know what's going on.
So, what's going on, my dear?
Robert doesn't know what it's about.
What's going on?
What is this about?
Mireille doesn't know what it's about either.
She doesn't know why he's protesting.
But she is sure they are right.
Why is he protesting?
I don't know, but they're probably right.
Okay, I'll stop.
You're right.
I think I'll take two or three
You're wrong, you're going to get sick
To be right, to be wrong
Do you want a candy?
No thanks
You're wrong, they're very good.
Are you a student?
Yes
What are you doing?
From the history of art
What are you saying?
I study art history
You are, you do, you say
I come from the United States
Robert comes from the United States
Now watch Mireille ask him if he comes to France often.
And do you come to France often?
I come from the United States
Listen carefully, there are three different vowel sounds in this verb
I come, you come, they come
I come from the United States
Oh, you're American?
Yes
But you don't have an accent at all for an American.
It's very kind of you to say that, but you know, I don't deserve any credit.
My mother is French.
Robert speaks French very well
He is American but he doesn't have an American accent when he speaks French.
That's normal because her mother is French.
He has no merit
And you? Is your mother French?
No, my mother is Spanish, so I have a slight Spanish accent.
Now, listen carefully to this dialogue. You are going to imitate Mireille.
I come from the United States.
Ah, you're American.
Now it's your turn. You are Mireille.
I come from the United States.
Ah, you're American? Ah, you're American?
Ah, you're American.
Yes.
Let's continue.
Listen to Mireille asking Robert where he lives.
And where do you live? At CITU?
Oh no, I live in a small hotel in the neighborhood.
Robert lives in a small hotel in the Latin Quarter.
Mireille lives in a house on rue de Vaugirard.
Robert's hotel is not a luxury hotel.
Now that, yes, that's a luxury hotel.
The Ritz in Paris is also a luxury hotel.
And this is a luxury apartment? Yes, it's a luxury apartment.
And this is a luxury apartment? No, this is not a luxury apartment.
It's not luxurious, but it's clean and not very expensive.
Robert's hotel is not luxurious, but it is clean.
Here's a clean room. Here's a less clean room.
Here is a gentleman who is clean, but here, he is not clean, he is dirty.
He is clean, but he is not clean, he is dirty.
Is this clean or is this dirty?
It's clean.
And is that clean?
No, it's dirty.
That's disgusting.
Robert's hotel isn't expensive, it's cheap.
120 francs isn't expensive, it's very cheap.
This is not a cheap hotel.
It's an expensive, luxurious, and expensive hotel.
Fruit is expensive here.
But here, fruit is cheap
Apricots for 4 francs, that's cheap
It's actually very cheap
Apricots at 5 francs are more expensive
But it's still a very good deal
This isn't a very expensive store.
It's a fairly cheap store
Yes, that's an expensive store.
That's not an expensive dress.
But that must be an expensive dress.
And this car?
Do you think it's an expensive car or a cheap car?
It's an expensive car.
And that's rather cheap.
And do you come to France often?
No, this is the first time.
Once, twice, three times.
Look there, I'm knocking once.
Now I knock twice.
And now, I'm going to strike three times.
And Robert, how many times has he been to France?
Four times? Three times? No
Twice? No
This is the first time
No, this is the first time
When I was little, we used to spend our holidays in Bermuda or Latin America
When he was little, Robert spent his holidays in Bermuda or South America
in Latin America, North America, Central America, South America, Latin America.
He always spent his holidays in Bermuda or South America.
It was a habit.
Mireille also has her habits.
For example, she usually sits on this bench.
Marie-Laure also has habits.
For example, she has the bad habit of picking her nose.
Robert and his parents used to spend their holidays in Latin America
because Robert's father had interests in Latin America.
He had businesses, financial interests.
Mireille wonders if Robert's father is dead.
No, no, no, he's not dead, he's still alive, he's alive
Oh no, no, no, my father is still alive, he's even in excellent health
Robert is alive too, Mireille too, she's alive, she lives, she's alive
Your teeth are also alive, if you brush them regularly
Your teeth are living things, remember to brush them
Uncle Guillaume is also alive. He's still alive. He's still alive. But Uncle Casimir is no longer alive. He's dead.
Sarah Bernhardt is dead too. Balzac is dead too. Edith Piaf is dead too. Chopin is dead too. They are no longer alive. They are dead.
They are alive, they are dead. Mireille is alive. She lives. She lives with her parents. She lives in Paris, on rue de Vaugirard.
Question: Does Mireille live with Robert? No. She lives with her parents.
Robert's mother lives in Argentina because she remarried an Argentinian.
Robert's father lives in the United States. He is a banker. He works in a bank.
That's a bank, a French bank.
That's a French bank too. Crédit Agricole is also a French bank.
These are French banks. But Robert's father works at an American bank. He's a vice president. This gentleman also works at a bank. He's a teller. He's at the cash register.
This lady is also at the checkout.
She's a cashier, but in a cafe, not a bank.
This lady is also a cashier, but in a cinema.
And this gentleman is a night watchman.
Being a cashier is a job.
It's a useful, honorable profession.
Being a night watchman is a job.
It's a useful profession.
Aunt Georgette says that all professions are useful and honorable.
Even being a vice-president of a bank is a useful and honorable profession.
There's no such thing as a career leap, as my Aunt Georgette says.
Obviously, Mireille is being ironic when she says that.
She's mocking; she makes fun of the bank vice-presidents a little.
Mireille remains silent
She says nothing, she remains silent, she keeps quiet
Silence, silence, silence
Excuse me, I have to go home.
Mireille has to go home, she must go home.
She probably has work to do.
Mireille has to go home; it's not far, she lives very close by.
Robert and Mireille are at the Sorbonne and Mireille lives here, on rue de Vaugirard
It's not far, it's not far from the Sorbonne, it's very close.
The Eiffel Tower, yes, the Eiffel Tower, that's quite far away.
But Rue de Vaugirard is very close.
Is it far from your place? Would you mind allowing me to accompany you?
No, it's not far, it's very close to here.
And I'd be happy for you to accompany me.
As you say.
Mireille makes fun of Robert because he looks ceremonious.
He didn't say, "Can I come with you?"
But he said, would you allow me to accompany you?
It's very polite, but it's a little, a little ceremonious.
That's a ceremony.
That too is a ceremony.
A wedding is a ceremony.
And here is a very cerebral gentleman.
Mireille is frank. She says things directly.
I'm not bothering you.
Yes, you're boring me.
You can see that she's frank.
Frank, frank.
Actually, to be honest, I think you're quite nice.
Finally, I mean friendly.
Look, if you like, we can go sit for a few minutes in the Luxembourg Gardens.
They are going to sit on a bench. They sit down. It's the verb "to sit down." They sit down. Look at that man and that woman. They are going to sit down.
Mireille lives opposite the Senate and the Luxembourg Gardens.
The Senate is on one side of the street and Mireille lives opposite, on the other side of the street.
This lady and this gentleman are sitting opposite each other.
Here, Mireille and Robert are sitting next to each other.
Opposite, next door.
Oh dear, I forgot.
She forgot that she was supposed to take Marie-Laure to her dance class.
Marie-Laure also forgets sometimes.
Look here, she forgot what 9 x 6 equals.
9 x 6.
I forgot.
Mireille has to take Marie-Laure to her dance class.
Look.
You are going to see Marie-Laure who is bringing Fido to Robert.
She brings Fido to Robert.
She brings it.
Robert writes a postcard to his mother.
The sun is setting.
The sun sets here too.
And here, it's Marie-Laure who goes to bed.
The weather is very mild.
It's not cold.
It's not warm.
The weather is mild.
The weather is nice.
The temperature is mild.
Parisian women wear white sweaters and red skirts.
Robert is not a very objective observer.
Mireille lives in Paris. She is Parisian.
Hubert lives in Paris. He is Parisian.
This gentleman does not live in Paris. He is not from Paris.
Goodbye, Robert.
Robert blows kisses to his mother.
This is Rodin's kiss.
Here, Marie-Laure is giving her father a kiss.
Here, Marie-Laure is giving Aunt Georgette a kiss.
Here, Marie-Laure is giving Uncle Guillaume a kiss.
Here's a big kiss.
A kiss. Do you understand? Yes?
Here, sir, give the young lady a kiss.
May I, miss, learn French?
Yes? Then, sir, give her a kiss.
There you go! Very good, that's it. You understand.
You learn French very well.
Now Robert needs a stamp to send his card.
Do you have any stamps, please?
Here are some stamps.
Stamps.
You can buy stamps at the post office or at a tobacconist's.
Where can I buy stamps?
At a post office or a tobacconist's shop.
To buy stamps, you can go either to a tobacconist or to the post office.
The post office is after the bridge.
That's the bridge, the bridge to change.
That's the Pont Neuf.
And this is the Mirabeau Bridge.
That's a Roman bridge.
And that's a bridge from the Middle Ages.
This is the Avignon bridge.
That's a small bridge.
And this is a big bridge, the Tancarville bridge in Normandy.
Now, observe this carefully.
My mother is French, but my father didn't like France very much.
When I was little, we used to spend our holidays in Bermuda or Latin America, where my father had interests.
Were you spending your holidays in South America?
Loved, was, plane, had, passenger.
That's the past. That's the imperfect tense.
Let's see what you've learned. Look.
What number is it?
It's May 29th. Okay, now, what time is it? It's 11 o'clock.
Has Robert come to France often? No, this is the first time.
Does Mireille live alone? No, she lives with her parents.
Does Mireille live far from the Sorbonne? No, she lives very close by.
Where can I buy stamps?
At the post office
Well, to be honest, I think that's enough as it is.
Goodbye everyone, see you next time
Applause
Subtitles ST' 501
the Ministry of Culture and Communication,
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.