Subtitles ST' 501
and get involved pretty soon you will figure out what's going on and be able
to say a few things in French yourself
Robert is looking for Mireille just as he has given up hope she comes up to him
at a cafe and they walk again to the Luxembourg garden lo and behold they
discover they have an acquaintance in common Robert then makes another
interesting discovery Mireille has a younger sister
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
in front of a tobacconist's shop
and he enters
I would like to send a postcard; it's for Argentina.
By plane? By plane, then it's 6 francs 30.
There you go. 6 francs, 6 francs, 6 francs, 57.
57 and 3 lives. There you go, sir. Thank you.
Where is he? There's a mailbox over here.
On the left as you leave, sir.
Thank you, goodbye madam. Goodbye sir, thank you.
Robert is walking through the streets of the Latin Quarter.
He crosses the Place de la Sorbonne.
He enters the courtyard of the Sorbonne.
He seems to be looking for something.
Something or someone.
He passes under the arches.
He crosses the corridor.
He exits through the gate on school street.
He enters the Luxembourg Garden
He goes before the Senate
Look, there's a young girl on the bench.
Who is it ?
This is not Mireille
What is he going to do?
He's not going back to the Sorbonne?
Yes, but something's wrong. What's wrong with this boy?
Come on, come on, the Latin Quarter is very nice, but there's more to Paris than that, you know.
There is the Île Saint-Louis, the Éal, Beaubourg, the Eiffel Tower,
Les Invalides, the Champs-Élysées, the museums, the Louvre.
Orsay, Montmartre, l'Opéra.
No, you're not interested.
You prefer to return to the Sorbonne.
How strange.
Hubert !
Are you here?
Yes, I do come to the university sometimes.
Actually, I wanted to see you.
Later.
Yes of course.
But tell me, if your father is a banker, you must be rich.
So why are you staying in a small, shabby hotel?
First of all, my hotel isn't bad at all.
It's a very decent little hotel.
And besides, my father may be rich, but I'm not.
I prefer to be independent.
Oh really? But then how do you do it?
How do you make a living?
To come to France like that, you need to have money.
Well, when I was little, my grandparents, my father's parents,
they always gave me about a hundred dollars at Christmas.
And also for my birthday.
This is the money I'm spending now.
Ah, I see.
You don't want to take your father's money,
But you have nothing against your grandparents'.
But tell me, if this is your first time here, you must not know anyone in Paris?
No, not yet. But I have a letter for some people who live on Quai de Grenelle. I plan to go see them tomorrow.
Quai de Grenelle, in one of the towers?
Totem Tower, 59 Quai de Grenelle, Mrs. Jacques Courtois. She is a childhood friend of my mother.
Mrs. Courtois? Well, that's fantastic! What a coincidence!
Do you know her?
Yes, I know her, of course I know her. She's my godmother.
She was my mother's best friend when she was studying medicine.
Madam, is your mother a doctor?
No. Madam, my mother, as you say, is not a doctor.
But she is a department head at the Ministry of Health.
However, my grandfather was a surgeon.
And my father is at Renaud's.
And what do you do?
I'm studying art history.
And I do karate on Saturday mornings.
It might come in handy, you never know.
As my aunt Georgette would say.
What are you doing here? Aren't you supposed to be at school?
No, that's not right. It's Wednesday today.
And what are you doing here?
Actually, Mom was looking for you.
Isn't she at the office?
No, she was at home and she was looking for you.
And what did she want?
That, I don't know. It's a mystery.
Okay, I'll go see.
That's it, go and see.
And you, where are you going?
I want to go sailing and I'm going to try out Uncle Guillaume's new boat.
Wait for me if you want, I'll be right back.
Are you Mireille's boyfriend? Are you English?
Why do I look English?
Non.
So, what am I?
Japanese? Spanish?
Italian American, what's your name Marie-Laure, and what are your names?
Robert, do you think she's good, my sister?
Robert buys a stamp at a tobacconist's, then he looks for a mailbox.
Letters, there's a mailbox on the left here, there's a cafe on the left here, there's a cafe
To the right, and here there's a cafe on the left. Careful now, this is going to be a game. Look closely here.
The cafe is on the right or the left, left yes. The taxis are on the right or the left, left, okay.
Okay. And here, are the taxis on the right or the left?
To the right. Okay. And the buses?
Left.
The mailbox is on the left as you go up.
Going up, going down.
Are you looking for a mailbox?
You have one there, on the left.
Are you looking for a cafe?
"There's one there on the right. Looking for a phone booth? There's one there on the left. Looking for a travel agency? There's one there on the right. Looking for a hotel? There's one there on the left."
Marie-Laure seems to be sleeping here. Marie-Laure seems to be looking for something. Robert seems to be looking for something.
something or someone here you see someone here you see something someone
Someone, something.
Now, be careful, this is going to be a game.
What do you see there? Someone or something?
Someone.
And here, what do you see? Someone or something?
Something.
And here? Someone.
And here? Someone else.
And here? Something.
And here? Something. And here? Someone. Look, is this woman looking for someone or something? Something. And here, what is the gentleman looking for? Something or someone? Someone.
Okay, now, look at this. This is the Sorbonne. Robert is at the Sorbonne. This is the hotel. Robert is at the hotel. This is the Luxembourg Gardens. Robert is at the Luxembourg Gardens.
That's the United States. Robert's father is in the United States.
Now it's your turn. Watch.
That's a café terrace. Where's Robert?
He's sitting on a café terrace. Good.
That's the Sorbonne library. Where is Ousmane?
He is at the library.
That's Mireille's house. Where is Mireille?
She's at home, that's the airport. Where's Robert? He's at the airport.
This is the school where the children are at school, this is the Latin Quarter where
Robert is in the Latin Quarter, that's the café where he left off.
Robert is at the café, at the café by the departure point, that's the tobacconist's shop where is
Robert is at the tobacconist's. That's Luxembourg. Where is Robert? He's in Luxembourg.
Now, look at this. This is the Sorbonne. This is the courtyard of the Sorbonne. This is
The Odéon and the Place de l'Odéon. That's the Latin Quarter. This is a street in the district.
Latin. That's the street with the schools. Yesterday, Mireille was in a hurry because she had to
Bringing Marie-Laure to her dance class. Here, Marie-Laure is bringing Fido to Robert. And
She'll take him here. Take him, take him. Today, Mireille isn't in a hurry. Neither is Robert.
He's in no hurry. He's doing nothing.
So Mireille suggests
Robert should go for a trip to Luxembourg.
Shall we take a trip to Luxembourg?
I'm not in a hurry.
Would you like that? Robert agrees.
He's willing. He accepts.
NOW,
Marie-Laure will propose
A candy for Mrs. Belleau.
And Mrs. Belleau will accept.
Listen to what she says in order to accept it.
Do you want a candy?
I'd like that.
Robert and Mireille are going on a trip to Luxembourg.
They are going for a walk in Luxembourg.
Aunt Georgette and Fido are out for a walk.
Here, it's Aunt Georgette who's leading Fido.
Here, Fido is in charge of Aunt Georgette.
Aunt Georgette has Fido in Luxembourg.
Aunt Georgette calls Fido.
I think.
To bring.
Take
Walk
But tell me, if your father is a banker, you must be rich.
So why are you staying in a small, shabby hotel?
Robert's father has money
But Robert prefers to be independent
Here is a young boy who is also very independent
Robert wants to be independent
So he doesn't have much money.
He checks into a small hotel
This is not a shabby hotel
But it's not a luxury hotel either.
That's a crappy hotel.
Robert has a little money
Because his grandparents always gave him money at Christmas
And then his grandparents always gave him money for his birthday too.
This is Robert's first birthday, he is one year old
This is Robert's fifth birthday. He is five years old.
Robert was born on October 23rd. His birthday is in October, in the month of October.
Madame Eva's birthday is also in October.
What are we going to wear?
Happy birthday, Ms. Eva! Happy birthday, Ms. Eva!
And when is your birthday?
For me, it's in January.
January is the first month of the year.
It's winter, it's cold. It's cold in February too.
In March, it rains, it's windy, sometimes it snows.
April is almost spring. The first flowers, the buds.
In May, there are flowers everywhere, and little birds.
In June, we make hay. There are cherries.
July is the month of vacation.
In August, we harvest.
It's very hot.
September marks the end of the holidays and the start of the new school year.
The grape harvest has begun.
October, autumn, the leaves turn yellow.
We're going hunting.
November, the sky is grey, it's All Souls' Day.
December, winter begins again, the Christmas holidays
During the Christmas holidays, we're going skiing
Let's see if you know the months of the year.
Look, is this May or November?
The month of May
And is this March or December?
The month of December.
And is this October or February?
The month of October.
Is this January or July?
The month of January.
And is this February or August?
The month of August.
Robert's grandparents gave him about a hundred dollars at Christmas.
A hundred, a hundred.
9, 10, 11, that's about ten
12, a dozen
15, about fifteen
100, a hundred
1000, a thousand
Let's see how much money Robert has
In the first year, Robert's grandparents gave him $100 for Christmas.
And then $100 for his birthday
That makes 200 dollars
At age 5, Robert has $1000
At 10 years old, he has $2000
And at 21, he has $4,200.
This is the money Robert is spending now.
He spends his grandparents' $4,000.
He spends this money in France.
He spends this money on the trip, the plane.
He spends this money on the hotel.
He spends this money in cafes.
He spends this money on postcards and stamps to write to his mother.
Marie-Laure spends her money on gumballs
And Mireille in earrings
Here, look
You spend all your money on gumballs
And you, you spend all your money on earrings
Robert spends French money
Pieces
One franc
Two francs
Five francs
Ten francs
Tickets
Twenty francs
Fifty francs
Two hundred francs
200 francs plus 100 francs makes 300.
Add 100 francs, that makes 400.
Add 100 francs, that makes 500.
Plus 500 francs, which makes 1000.
Okay, let's see if you recognize French money.
That's a 1 franc coin.
That's 2 francs.
That's a 5 franc coin.
That's a 10 franc coin.
That's a 20 franc note.
That's a 50 franc note.
That's a 100 franc note.
That's a 200 franc note.
And this is a 500 franc note.
This is Robert's first time in Paris.
He probably doesn't know many people.
No not yet.
Not yet.
He will meet people later.
But for now, he doesn't know anyone.
Look at Marie-Laure here. Has she finished her work?
Are you finished?
Not yet.
Look at this young man. Do you think he has children?
Do you have children?
No, not yet. I'm not married yet.
Robert doesn't know anyone in Paris yet.
But he has a letter for people who live in Paris.
And he plans to go see them the next day.
I plan to go see them tomorrow.
He plans to go see them.
He intends to go and see them.
Observe what Mireille says here.
She asks Marie-Laure what she plans to do.
So, what are you planning to do?
Well, go play in the garden.
Have you done your homework?
No, not yet.
So you're going to do your homework and then we'll see.
Oh !
The people Robert plans to visit live on Quai de Grenelle, on the banks of the Seine, in a tower called the Totem Tower.
Here is a tower, the Montparnasse Tower, the Eiffel Tower, a medieval tower, a round tower, a square tower, another medieval tower.
The people Robert plans to visit live in a modern tower block.
Totem Tower, 59 Quai de Grenelle, Mrs. Jacques Courtois
She is a childhood friend of my mother
Madame Courtois is a childhood friend of Robert's mother
Here you see Robert's mother and Mrs. Courtois when they were children
They were friends when they were children
They are childhood friends
Robert's mother knows Mrs. Courtois because she is a childhood friend.
And Mireille also knows Mrs. Courtois
Madame Courtois, that's wonderful, what a coincidence!
That's quite a coincidence. That's an exceptional encounter. Look, here are some other coincidences.
My mother is French.
Is your mother French? Mine is too. What a coincidence.
I love flowers.
I love flowers too. What a coincidence.
Madame Courtois is Mireille's godmother. Look.
This is Mireille's baptism.
Here's Mireille, this is the baby
And here is Mireille's mother
And that's Mireille's godmother
This is Madame Courtois, Mireille's godmother
Mireille has a father and a mother
And then, since she was baptized in the Catholic Church
She also has a godfather and a godmother
Mrs. Courtois and Mireille's mother
studied medicine together
They studied medicine
These are people who are studying medicine.
Here's a doctor.
To become a doctor, you have to study medicine.
A doctor, a person, medicine, science, the profession.
Mireille's grandfather was a surgeon, a doctor specializing in surgery.
A surgeon, a person, surgery, science, the profession.
Mireille does karate because it might be useful.
It can be useful. Of course, karate isn't useful every day.
But it might come in handy someday, you never know.
You never know what might happen. You never know what might be useful.
It might come in handy, you never know, as my Aunt Georgette says.
You never know. Look, observe this little scene.
Here, take your sweater.
But it's not cold.
It doesn't matter. Take it anyway, you never know. Go ahead.
Today, Marie-Laure is not at school.
What are you doing here? Aren't you supposed to be at school?
No, that's not right, it's Wednesday today!
Marie-Laure is not at school because it's Wednesday.
There is no school on Wednesdays.
There is school on Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, Friday, and Saturday morning.
But not on Wednesdays, nor on Sundays
These are the days of the week
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, Saturday, Sunday
On Sundays, we go to church if we are Catholic, or to the temple if we are Protestant.
On Mondays, we work.
There is no school on Wednesdays.
We work on Thursdays and Fridays.
Saturday is the weekend.
On Saturdays, we go to the synagogue, if we are Jewish.
Well, that's all very good.
Now you are going to speak French.
Listen to the dialogue between Marie-Laure and Robert.
You will repeat Robert's answers.
Listen carefully, you're Mireille's boyfriend, you're English, why do I look English?
So what, I'm American now? You're Robert, you're the boyfriend.
Mireille, you're English, why do I look English? Why do I look English?
Why do I look English when what am I?
So, what do you know about me? I'm American. Let's see what you know if you want to send a...
For a postcard or a letter, you need a stamp, that's it, and then you need to find a
One, one, one, a mailbox.
You have one there, on the left.
Yes, the mailbox is on the left, but the cafe is on the right.
What do you see there? Something or someone?
Something.
And there? Someone.
Look at Mrs. Belleau here. Is she in the office?
No. Where is she?
At home. She is at home.
What is this garden? Do you recognize it?
This is the Luxembourg Garden.
Where is Marie-Laure? Is she at home?
No. Where is she?
In Luxembourg.
She is in Luxembourg.
That's French money.
How much is the bill worth?
It's a 500 franc note.
Look at these two young women. They're studying medicine because they want to be...
What do they want to be? They want to be doctors.
Robert's grandparents always gave him about a hundred dollars at Christmas and also for his birthday.
$100, $100 for his birthday. Well, do you get $100 for your birthday?
Nobody ever gives me $100 for my birthday. Never, it never happens to me, $100.
Tell me, do you think he's good, Sir Robert?
Not me.
But don't say anything, I think I can hear it.
I'll go see.
Ah, my stick!
It might come in handy, you never know.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada