Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on.
And be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Marie-Laure has sent her sister on a wild goose chase.
When Mireille returns, Robert tries to persuade her to join him in calling on Madame Courtois.
It's just his luck that Mireille has already planned a trip to Chartres.
Ever resourceful, Robert has a brainstorm.
Could he join her?
The Luxembourg Gardens in Paris, on a beautiful spring day.
There are flowers, little birds, the weather is beautiful.
There isn't a cloud in the sky. Ah, ah, yes, yes, there are a few clouds.
A young man, dark-haired, quite tall, and friendly.
Yes, he's quite nice, isn't he?
is sitting on a bridge.
He is talking to a little girl
who owns a boat.
This young man is not French.
He has been in France for two days.
In the distance, a young girl arrives.
Hey, look who's back, my sister.
Well, I'm leaving now.
I'm going to enjoy the wind while it lasts.
My sister doesn't seem happy
When I told her that Mom was looking for her earlier
That wasn't true
It was a joke
You don't tell him anything
Mystery and bubblegum
THANKS
Bye
Bye.
Where is Marie-Laure?
She just left that way in her boat.
She told me she was going to enjoy the wind while it lasted.
What a nasty little girl.
She said my mother was looking for me, but there was no one at home.
Another one of his stupid jokes.
She's impossible, that girl.
Is it that...
Are you familiar with the Basque Country?
So, you, we can say, have some rather unexpected questions.
Why are you asking me that?
I really don't see the connection.
Yes, I know him a little.
Last summer, we went to Saint-Jean-de-Luz.
Back when I was little, we used to go to Belle-Île-en-Mer, in Brittany.
I liked Belle-Île, it was peaceful.
There were fewer people.
We went sailing, we fished for shrimp, we caught crabs.
And when it rained, we played portrait.
We used to go see old movies.
But my sister thought it wasn't trendy enough.
I mean fashionable.
So last year, we went to Saint-Jean.
It's more lively.
But why are you asking me that?
I want to go.
My mother often talked to me about it when I was a child.
It's a very beautiful country. And is your mother from there?
No, not really.
But she spent several years there as a child.
My grandfather, my mother's father, was a judge.
His first post was in La Rochelle.
My mother was born while my grandparents were in La Rochelle.
Then my grandfather went to court in Bayonne, when my mother was 4 or 5 years old.
They stayed in Bayonne for 6 or 7 years, I think.
It was while they were in Bayonne that my mother met this Madame Courtois.
Indeed, she was born in the Basque Country.
And his parents were shopkeepers.
They had a small fabric shop opposite the cathedral.
And your grandparents, where are they now?
They are both dead.
They died when I was 9 or 10 years old.
But tell me, I was thinking, I'm going to the Courtois' place tomorrow.
You wouldn't happen to want to go see them tomorrow, would you?
Since Mrs. Courtois is your godmother.
No, I can't tomorrow. I have to go to Chartres.
See the cathedral? I want to go see it too, one day.
No, I know the cathedral.
I visited it at least 5 or 6 times with my parents
And just as many times with school
Tomorrow I have to go see an exhibition
In a small museum located right next door
Would you please allow me to...
To accompany me?
Oh, but you can if you want.
But you forget that tomorrow you're going to the Courtois' house
I can go another day
The day after tomorrow, for example
Mireille !
Mireille! What? What's wrong now? I've broken down. You've broken down? Yes, my boat has broken down.
There's no more wind, he's in the middle of the pool. He's not coming back. Come on! Listen, you're bothering me.
Figure it out yourself. Come on! No! Come on! I'm going. But how annoying is that kid?
Hey, are you kidding us?
No, no, no, my boat is broken down, it's in the middle of the basin, oh!
Yes, he was there a little while ago, in the middle of the pool.
The wind has returned, that's all.
Oh, it's all a melee now.
Hey, figure it out yourself.
It's not a problem. I'll fix it.
And there you have it.
Well, say thank you.
THANKS.
You are too kind.
But tell me, with all that said, what is your name?
Robert Taylor.
No relation to the actor.
And you?
Mireille Bello. No relation to the poet.
What a pedant, that Mireille!
She is referring to Rémi Bello, a somewhat forgotten 16th-century poet.
We are in Luxembourg.
There are flowers.
One flower, several flowers.
There are birds.
One bird, several birds.
The weather is nice.
It's a beautiful spring day.
One morning, one morning.
One day, one day.
One evening, one night.
One year, one year.
Marie-Laure is talking to Robert.
She owns a boat.
Here, she is holding a biscuit in her right hand.
Here, she is holding a candy.
Here, she is holding Fido in her arms.
To have.
We hold, you hold, they hold, you hold, I hold.
It's like the verb "to come".
We come, you come, they come, you (feminine) come, you (plural) come, I come.
Or come back.
We're coming back, you're coming back, they're coming back,
She comes back, you come back, I come back.
Hey, here comes my sister again.
Well, I'm leaving now.
I'm going to enjoy the wind while it lasts.
It's windy.
It is the wind that makes the windmills turn.
It is the wind that makes sailboats move.
When there is wind, the boats sail.
When there is no wind, sailboats are at a standstill.
They are not walking, they are not moving forward.
It's windy.
Marie-Laure wants to take advantage of the wind to play with her boat.
There isn't always wind.
You have to take advantage of the wind when there is any.
The weather isn't always nice.
We should take advantage of the good weather to go to Luxembourg.
But when the weather is bad,
We should take advantage of bad weather to work.
to do homework.
That's Mireille's opinion, but not Marie-Laure's.
Listen.
It's raining. You should take advantage of it to do your holiday homework.
No, I'm going to take advantage of this time to have a nap.
It's definitely calmer when the children are at high school.
Yes, when they're not here, I take the opportunity to get some work done.
The man is taking advantage of his children's absence to work.
But Marie-Laure doesn't want to go to work.
She doesn't want to go to work.
She doesn't feel like working; she'd rather take a nap or go play with her boat.
Look at Jean-Claude, he wants something.
What are you having for dinner tonight?
Do you want to have dinner with Irina and me?
Mireille is not happy.
My sister doesn't look happy.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She is happy.
Owl !
He is not happy.
She is not happy
Now observe this couple
Mireille is not happy because Marie-Laure played a joke on her
She told him that Madame Bello had been looking for her.
So Mireille went home
But that wasn't true, Madame Bello wasn't there
It was a joke.
When I told her that Mom was looking for her earlier, it wasn't true.
Marie-Laure likes to tell jokes.
Here, look.
Look, I caught a snake.
Oh!
Oh my God, you're crazy.
Drop it right now.
Oh, but don't be scared, it's a joke.
Look, it's a fake snake.
It's not a real snake, it's a fake snake.
Give it to me, look, that's a real snake.
But no, that's not a real snake, it's a fake snake.
Now, this is going to be a game.
If I say that Mireille is a brunette, is that true or false?
That's wrong.
If I say that Marie-Laure has a boat, is that true or false?
It's true.
If I say that there are flowers in Luxembourg, is that true or false?
If I say there isn't a cloud, is that true or false?
That's wrong.
And when Marie-Laure told Mireille that her mother had been looking for her, it was a lie.
And that's why Mireille is not happy and says that Marie-Laure is a nasty kid, a nasty little girl.
What a nasty little girl! She told me my mother was looking for me when there was nobody at home.
This is just another one of his stupid jokes.
That girl is absolutely impossible.
Robert smiled because he knew it was a joke.
He changes the course of the conversation.
He asks an unexpected question.
Are you familiar with the Basque Country?
Mireille doesn't see the connection between Marie-Laure's joke and the Basque Country.
Well, you guys, it's safe to say you have some rather unexpected questions.
Why are you asking me that? I really don't see the connection.
Similarly, when Marie-Laure says she got a ten in French at school because she doesn't want to go to bed, her mother says she doesn't see the connection.
Go to bed, my little one.
Oh, Mom, I got a ten on my Franceuf homework.
That's very good, but I don't see the connection.
There is no connection.
Are you familiar with the Basque Country?
Mireille is surprised.
That's a strange question.
The Basque Country has nothing to do with Marie-Laure's jokes; that's an unexpected question.
Look here, what are you doing here? You're not at school, Mireille is surprised because she
Marie-Laure wasn't expecting it. Marie-Laure's arrival was unexpected; what an unexpected visit!
The lady is surprised because she wasn't expecting this visit; that too is unexpected.
In an unexpected turn of events, Robert asks Mireille if she knows the Basque Country.
You know the Basque Country, you know Australian cuisine, you have
I tried it, it's good, Australian food, you know it, right? But look at Sonia, who is she?
Is it Antoine? She knows him. Sonia and Antoine know each other. Sonia, my friend, good evening. I know.
Very well, who is it? We've already got him started, haven't we? And you know the country.
Basque, you know where it is, you know the Basque Country, you know
You don't know where it is, it's in the southwest of France, it's partly in France
and partly in Spain, it's a very beautiful country, there are mountains and the sea, Basque houses
Basque, frontons for playing Basque pelota, there are beaches, Biarritz, Saint-Jean-de-Luz.
In the summer, it's very crowded, with lots of tourists, it's very lively.
Mireille finds it more lively than Brittany.
In Brittany, there are fewer people, it's more peaceful.
Saint-Jean-de-Luz is more lively.
Here is a lively street, a quiet street.
But Cécile felt that Brittany was too quiet, not lively enough.
Not fashionable enough, not trendy enough.
These Breton women are not fashionable, they are not trendy.
These young women are more in tune with the times.
These young men are trendy, but this young woman is not.
This one is in vogue.
Mind, hein, mec, là!
These ladies are not in vogue.
These people are not trendy.
In Brittany, it was a peaceful holiday.
We fished for shrimp, we fished for crabs.
Robert wants to go to the Basque Country because his mother often talked about it.
His mother's father, his grandfather, was a magistrate.
He was a judge in a court.
First, he was a judge at the court in La Rochelle.
on the Atlantic
then he became a judge
at the Bayonne court
the parents of
Madame Courtois were shopkeepers
In Bayonne, they had a fabric shop
they were selling Basque linen
Madame Courtois
and Robert's mother
met in Bayonne
when they were children
it's the verb to be
I was
You were, he was, they were, we were, you were.
Robert plans to visit the Courtois the next day.
He suggests that Mireille go and see them too.
since Mrs. Courtois is her godmother.
She can go see her if she wants.
I'm going to the Courtois' place tomorrow.
You don't happen to want to go see them tomorrow, do you?
since Mrs. Courtois is your godmother.
But Mireille cannot, because she has to go to Chartres.
No, I can't tomorrow, I have to go to Chartres.
Robert also wants to go to Chartres, to see the cathedral.
But Mireille is not going to see the cathedral, she is going to the museum.
A small museum located next to the cathedral.
A museum, you know what that is.
Like the Louvre Museum, the Petit Palais Museum,
like the Mecca Gallery in the South of France, for example.
She is going to see an exhibition of paintings.
In Chartres, there is a cathedral and a museum.
Let's ask some French people if they know Chartres.
Are you familiar with Chartres?
Not very good, but I know its cathedral well, like everyone else.
What is interesting about Chartres?
Beautiful cathedral.
There is the cathedral, which is very well known.
Robert asks Mireille if he can go to Chartres with her.
Would you please allow me to...
Mireille replies that Robert can accompany her if he wants.
But you can if you want to.
Power and will.
We can if we want to.
You can if you want.
They can if they want to.
She can if she wants to.
You can if you want.
I can if I want to.
Where there's a will, there's a way.
Yeah, that's what people say, but it's not always true.
You can't, you can't, you can't, you don't want to.
Would you please allow me to...
To accompany me? But you can if you want.
But you don't have to go see the Courtois tomorrow?
I can go another day, the day after tomorrow for example.
If today is Wednesday, tomorrow will be Thursday.
And the day after tomorrow, it will be Friday.
Look at Marie-Laure.
Mireille !
She has a problem.
His boat is broken down in the middle of the basin.
But Mireille doesn't want to help him.
She doesn't want to deal with it.
Oh, listen, you're bothering me. Figure it out yourself.
Look at this string.
It's all tangled up, all confused.
There's a problem.
Now she's cleared up.
Look at this man.
He's all confused.
He had a problem. Now he's sorted it out. He doesn't have a problem anymore.
SO ?
So, I don't know exactly what you all signed.
Fine. Figure it out yourself. What do you want me to say?
But Marie-Laure cannot manage on her own.
Help me, I can't get down.
You managed to get up. Well, now you manage to get down.
Now you will speak.
Listen to this dialogue between Mireille and Marie-Laure.
You are Mireille and you are going to answer Marie-Laure.
Mireille! What? What is it now?
I'm broken down. Are you broken down?
Yes, my boat isn't moving anymore. There's no wind, it's in the middle of the basin, it won't come back. Come on!
Okay, listen, you're bothering me, sort it out yourself!
Now it's your turn. You are Mireille.
Mireille! What? What is it now?
What? What else is there?
I'm broken down. You're broken down.
You're broken down.
Yes, the boat is broken down.
Listen, you're bothering me, sort it out yourself.
Mireille doesn't want to go to the pool to help Marie-Laure.
But Robert is going.
I'm going.
Robert goes to the pool.
Robert and he goes.
He plans to go to the Courtois' house the next day.
But he can go another day.
"I can go another day."
"I can go to the Courtois' place another day."
She has to go to Chartres.
He wants to go too.
He wants to go to the Basque Country.
He wants to go.
Marie-Laure told Mireille that her boat had broken down in the middle of the basin.
"Yes, my boat isn't moving anymore."
There is no more wind, he is in the middle of the basin, he is not coming back.
But when Robert and Mireille arrive at the dock, the boat is not broken down in the middle of the dock at all.
He is on the edge.
So Mireille thinks that Marie-Laure has played another joke on her.
She believes that Marie-Laure is making fun of her.
Are you kidding us?
No, Marie-Laure is not making fun of Robert and Mireille.
This is not a joke.
Now the boat is at the edge of the basin.
But just five minutes ago, he was in the middle of the pool.
Ah yes, earlier, he was there, in the middle of the pool.
Now the boat's lines are all tangled up, all tangled up.
Oh, it's all tangled up.
Mireille doesn't want to help him.
Figure it out yourself.
But Robert will help him. He's a kind man, that Robert.
It's not a problem. I'll fix it.
And he ties up the wires.
And there you go, it's sorted.
Now, Mireille is going to ask Robert what his name is.
She has known Robert for two days and she doesn't know his name.
You're too kind. But tell me, with all that said, what's your name?
That's the verb "s'appeler".
My name is Mireille, Mireille Bello. And you, what is your name?
Notice, this child doesn't want to say what his dad's name is.
And your dad, what's his name? You don't want to tell me?
And what's your name?
You do know your name, though.
In addition, he is mute.
My name is, your name is, her name is, his name is, our names are, you (plural) are, she will be called.
Call, call, call, let's call, call, call.
It's the same with the verb "amener".
"I apologize for yesterday, but I had to take my little sister to her dance class."
She's bringing him, she had to bring him.
Bring, bring.
The girl's name is Mireille.
The young man will be called Robert.
Robert Taylor. No relation to the actor.
Robert Taylor is an actor. A movie actor.
A French actor?
No, American.
Is it or was it?
Is he still alive? Is he still alive?
Or is he dead?
In any case, he was a very well-known actor, a bit forgotten now, but around 1950 he was very famous.
Robert's name is Taylor, like the actor, but there is no connection.
It's a coincidence, a chance occurrence.
And Mireille's name is...
Mireille Bello. No relation to the poet.
Rémi Bello was a poet.
He wrote poems.
He was born in 1528.
And he died in 1577. He was a 16th-century poet.
Victor Hugo was also a poet. He was born in 1802 and died in 1885.
He is a 19th-century poet.
Rainer Maria Rilke is also a poet. He is a German poet.
He was born in 1875. He died in 1926. He was a 20th-century poet.
Garcia Lorca was also a poet, a Spanish poet. He was born in 1899 and died in 1936. He was a 20th-century poet.
Okay, let's see what you know. Let's see if you can distinguish between true and false.
Those are flowers. True, that's true. They are flowers. It's a beautiful spring day. False.
Marie-Laure is working, she's doing her homework. Wrong. She's holding her boat under her arm.
Marie-Laure goes to school on Wednesdays. No way! That's wrong. She doesn't go to school on Wednesdays.
There is no wind. The boat has broken down. False.
Robert's mother's father, that is to say his maternal grandfather, was a merchant in Bayonne.
That's false. He was a judge.
Oh, but don't be scared. It's a joke. Look, it's a fake snake.
Marie-Laure is holding a fake snake. That's true.
She is holding a fake snake.
Victor Hugo was a 19th-century French poet.
TRUE.
Rémi Bello is a very well-known 20th-century poet.
Faux.
What a pedant this professor is.
A 16th-century poet.
Do you know this Rémi Bello?
I don't know who that is.
He's definitely not very trendy, that one.
Ah, a 16th-century poet.
I don't see the connection.
Oh yes yes yes.
This professor is tiring me out.
What a pedant.
I'm leaving.
I'm going to take a nap.
You don't tell him anything, right?
Okay, I'm going.
What? What else is there?
Ah, my stick.
I forgot my stick.
It might still be useful.
You never know.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
to the French language,
the Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
and the National Endowment for the Humanities.
For information about this
and other Annenberg Media programs,
call 1-800-LEARNER
and visit us at www.learner.org.