Subtitles ST' 501
and fly away. Very soon, you will see what happens and you will be able to say a few things.
things in French yourself. Robert and Mireille talk about surnames, like Taylor, which are
They also include names of trades and professions. They compare notes on their childhood ambitions,
remembering their dreams of being a fireman, a traveler, a nurse, an actress.
French subtitles?
Paris, in the spring.
There are flowers in the Luxembourg Garden.
A little girl is playing gently with her boat.
It is 10 a.m.
In the Senate, the senators are debating.
In the garden, on a bench, two young people are talking.
Who are these young people?
Ah, but it's Mireille, Mireille Bello and Robert Taylor.
Your name is Taylor? But that means tailor in English.
Uh, I don't know.
Yes, Taylor means tailor in English.
But everyone knows that, My Taylor is rich, it's in all the English books.
Yes, no, of course not. But I mean, my name is spelled with a Y, and the English word for tailor is spelled with an I.
But that doesn't matter. It's probably the same thing. Spelling, you know, doesn't mean anything.
In fact, there are lots of people whose names are professions. Take Boucher, for example. It's a proper noun, a family name.
There are lots of people named Boucher, like Boucher the 18th-century painter, or Hélène Boucher for example, she was an aviator.
And Boucher, of course, is also a job title, the butcher who sells meat.
That's how I remember once seeing Mr. Boucher, pharmacist, on a pharmacy.
He was a gentleman who was a pharmacist by trade, but his name was Boucher.
And have you ever seen on a butcher's shop, Mr. Pharmacist Butcher, a pharmacist's name is a
It's a job title or occupational name, but it's not a proper noun; nobody calls themselves a pharmacist.
As far as I know, I'm not a computer scientist, but there are plenty of people named baker, like
the one who makes bread or carpenter like the one who makes the frames Gustave carpenter by
For example, he was a composer. Messenger, too, is a job title. The one who
It carries messages or goods. It is also a proper noun. André Messager is
A composer. A charcoal burner, someone who sells charcoal. It is also a proper noun.
And also forester, tailor, cattle herder. Cattle herder? That's my mother's maiden name.
But it's not a job title
Yes, of course it's a job title
Finally, it was a job title, in the past.
The herdsman was the one who drove the oxen.
Obviously, this isn't done much in France anymore.
Profession or cattle herder, that's not something people say much anymore.
We usually talk about a tractor driver.
Chevrier is also a family name
The goatherd is the one who takes care of the goats.
And then there's also the shepherd, like the one who takes care of the sheep.
And then miners, sailors.
Sailors, that's what I wanted to be when I was 12 or 13 years old.
Yes, it's funny the ideas we have when we're little.
Do you know what I wanted to be when I was little?
I wanted to be a nurse and an actress.
Nurse by day and actress by night.
I also had some rather strange ideas.
When I was little, when I was 7 or 8 years old, I wanted to be a firefighter.
to drive at full speed through the streets and make a lot of noise.
Climb to the top of the tall ladder
and dive into an open window that is spewing flames and smoke.
And to save the babies asleep amidst the flames.
Mireille !
Where did you come from like that?
From the basin.
Did you go diving in the pool?
No, not really.
I fell, I tried to grab my boat,
So I leaned over, then I slipped, then I fell, that's it.
Ah, that's clever.
Go get changed, come on, go home right away
And you had a sore throat, what will Mom say?
That girl is unbearable, luckily she knows how to swim
She will surely become a swimming champion
Or she might go on underwater exploration with Cousteau's team
You never know
No, you never know how things will turn out.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
The seamstresses.
Observe.
Dad, if you wanted, you could be a seamstress?
Tailor, if you don't mind.
Yeah, a tailor, basically.
Being a painter is also a profession.
He's someone who makes paintings.
Courbet, for example, was a painter.
The baker is the one who makes the bread.
And his wife, who helps him make the bread or who sells the bread, is the baker.
The carpenter is the one who makes the frameworks.
The butcher is the one who sells meat.
Beef, veal, mutton
A charcoal seller is someone who sells charcoal
A pharmacist is someone who sells medicines
A computer scientist is someone who works with a computer.
A nurse is someone who works in a hospital.
A sailor is someone who works on a ship, and a miner is someone who
A composer works in a mine to extract coal; a composer is someone who composes music.
In music, an actor is someone who performs in theater or film; an aviator is...
It's someone who pilots an airplane.
A tractor driver,
It's someone who drives a tractor.
A driver is someone who drives a car.
A taxi driver, for example.
And a cattle herder was someone who used to drive oxen.
But nowadays, that's not done much anymore.
And then there are also the shepherds who take care of the sheep, the goatherds who take care of the goats, the foresters who take care of the forests.
Now, we are going to ask this gentleman if he knows any people who have job titles.
Do you know anyone named Boucher?
The painter.
Do you know anyone named Charpentier?
The musician
Now you are going to talk
Listen to this short dialogue between Robert and Mireille
And you're going to repeat what Mireille says.
Being a sailor is what I wanted to be when I was 12 or 13 years old.
Yes, it's funny the ideas we have when we're little
Do you know what I wanted to be when I was little?
I wanted to be a nurse and an actress
Now it's your turn.
Yes, it's funny the ideas we have when we're little.
You know what I wanted to be when I was little.
I wanted to be a nurse and an actress
Forester, shepherd, cattle herder – these are job titles.
But they are also proper names, family names
There are people named forester, or Mr. and Mrs. Shepherd, or Miss Cowherd.
In fact, there are lots of people who have a job title.
Lots of people, many people. A lot of people, lots and lots. Look. One person, lots of people. One orange, lots of oranges. Fruit, lots of fruit. Peaches, lots of peaches. One cherry, lots of cherries. People, lots and lots of people.
There are lots of people, lots of men, lots of women
And then there are plenty of women.
Isn't that right, Antoine?
There are lots of people named Boucher
Like the 18th century painter
Or Hélène Boucher, the viatrician
Or like this pharmacist, observed
A pharmacist, a female pharmacist
a computer scientist, a technician, a pharmacist, a baker, a shepherd, a shepherdess, a farmer, a farmer
A male nurse. An actor, an actress. A male pilot, a female pilot.
Aviator, aviatrix, that's not how we say it anymore. It used to be said, around 1930. But now, it's not said anymore. It used to be said, but it's not said today.
That was said, but it's in the past.
That's no longer how it's said, it's the present tense.
That used to be said, but it's not said anymore.
It's over, finished.
That's what people said, that's what was said.
In the past, we used to talk about aviators.
Now, we no longer say aviator.
Today, we're talking about pilots.
In the past, we used to talk about messengers.
A messenger was someone who carried messages.
Mercury, for example, was the messenger of the gods.
Today, we no longer speak of messenger as a profession.
But there are still messages.
Look, for example, at Marie-Laure taking a message.
In the past, the herdsman was the one who drove the oxen.
Today, we drive tractors.
When Mireille was little, she wanted to be a nurse and an actress
She was, that's the past
She is, that is the present
She wanted to, that's in the past
She wants, present
Now, Mireille is grown up
She no longer wants to be a nurse or an actress.
When she was little, Mireille had a doll.
Now she has a little sister.
She had, she has.
Now, let's see if you've understood.
That's what people used to say.
That's in the past.
Today, we don't say that anymore.
This is the present.
Okay, your turn.
"In the past, people drove oxen. That's history. Today, we drive trucks, tractors, cars. That's the present."
"Mireille wanted to be a nurse and Robert, a firefighter. That's the past. Robert wants to go to the Basque Country. Present."
His mother often talked about it.
Fits.
He spent his holidays in Bermuda.
He spent a year in France.
Here.
The weather is nice.
The weather was nice.
Fits.
Robert was a student in the United States.
Mireille is a student
Here
Watch out!
Robert was a student
Pass
Mireille is a student
Here
She is leaving the institute
Do you know how to spell "sort"?
It's spelled SORT
It's spelled with a T.
It's pronounced SORT, but it's spelled SORT.
It's a matter of spelling.
Spelling, you know, doesn't mean anything.
Oh, well, all the same, yes, spelling is important.
You need to know how to write, right?
What do you think?
But yes, look, Mrs. Belleau, she thinks that spelling is important.
She thinks that you need to know how to write, that you need to do dictations, spelling exercises.
You need to know how things are written.
Go ahead, write "spelling".
Spelling?
Yes, spelling.
It's a spelling exercise, a dictation.
How do you spell "orthographe"?
Orthography, with TH and PH.
It's simple.
So, you write?
Yes, yes, I am writing.
I am writing.
You write.
We write.
They write.
Spelling is interesting. Look, see. We write: Third person singular present tense. We write:
It's spelled with a T. Well, there are many verbs that are spelled with a T in the third person singular of the present tense. We don't pronounce the T, but it's spelled with a T.
For example,
There are others that are written with a D, but the D is not pronounced.
But there are verbs that are written with an E.
She arrives, she listens, she speaks, she begins, she continues, she tries, she gets bored.
And then, there are verbs that are written with an A.
She goes, she has.
The third person plural usually ends with ENT, which is written but not pronounced.
They arrive, they continue, they try, they choose, they learn, they come, they persevere.
And there are some verbs that end in ON, ONT.
They have, they go, they do.
And what are Robert and Mireille doing?
Ah, hey, Robert and Mireille, I'd forgotten about them.
Well, Robert and Mireille are on their bench in the Luxembourg Gardens.
And they talk, they talk about what they wanted to do when they were little
It's funny the ideas we have when we're little
Do you know what I wanted to be when I was little?
I wanted to be a nurse and an actress
So, nurse by day and actress by night
Yes, being a nurse during the day and an actress at night is a bizarre idea, a strange idea.
It's funny, it's amusing, isn't it?
Look, that's funny too, that's amusing, isn't it?
Don't you find that funny?
And you don't find that funny?
I find it funny.
Robert also had some strange ideas.
He wanted to be a firefighter.
It's good to be a firefighter.
That has advantages, because if you're not a firefighter, you can't drive very fast in the city.
Speed ​​is limited.
You cannot go faster than 60 km/h.
But if you're a firefighter, you can drive at full speed.
Here is a man driving at full speed.
In fact, he's going too fast.
You're going too fast.
I like speed.
If you're not a firefighter, you can't make any noise.
You cannot honk your horn
Come on, come on, come quickly, and without making a sound
But if you're a firefighter, you can make all the noise you want.
If you're not a firefighter, you can climb onto a chair
You can climb onto the table
or you can climb a small ladder.
But the firefighters, they have tall ladders.
And if you are a firefighter, you can climb to the top of the tall ladder.
It's more interesting, it's more exciting.
If you're not a firefighter, you can dive into a swimming pool with water.
Or you can dive into a pool without water.
Or you can dive into the sea.
But if you're a firefighter, you can dive through a window
that breathes flames and smoke and saves sleeping babies.
Or to save the little girls who fell into the Luxembourg basin.
Mireille !
Where did you come from like that?
From the basin.
Did you go diving in the pool?
No, not really. I wanted to grab my boat and then I slipped.
I fell, and that's that.
Marie-Laure fell into the pool.
Here, Robert falls from a balcony.
Here, he falls off his horse.
Here, the apple falls on Newton's head.
And this gentleman has teeth that are falling out.
Look at this young man, he's going to fall.
Marie-Laure fell because she leaned over.
Jean-Claude, do you want to lean over?
It's dangerous to lean over. You could fall.
Look at this man. He's leaning over, he's leaning over, he's going to fall.
There he goes, he falls. He has fallen.
Marie-Laure bent down to grab her boat.
Here, she catches Fido.
Here, she caught a snake.
She leaned over and slipped.
He slipped too.
Look at this dancer.
He's going to slip and fall.
Jean-Claude, do you want to slide?
She leaned over, she slipped and whoosh, she fell into the pool.
Luckily she went swimming.
Luckily she knows how to swim
Here's a young girl who knows how to swim
He doesn't know how to swim
It's good to know how to swim
Marie-Laure is a very good swimmer
She will become a swimming champion
Okay, she's going to do some underwater exploration.
Meanwhile, she's completely soaked.
She's soaked
She's going to catch a cold.
She should go change
Go on, get changed, go home right away
Here is a young woman who is going to change her clothes.
There, she's changed.
Marie-Laure is going to change her clothes.
She doesn't look like a swimming champion, but that doesn't mean anything.
She might become a swimming champion.
You never know. You never know how things will turn out.
No, you never know how things will turn out.
So, let's see what you know.
If you want to buy bread, you go to the baker.
But if you want to buy meat, you go to the butcher.
If you want to buy medicine, you go to the pharmacist.
If you are sick in the hospital, who takes care of you?
A nurse.
And if you are a sheep, who takes care of you?
A shepherd, what made this painting? A composer? A baker?
pharmacist, a painter, an 18th-century painter whose name was butcher
Besides, you know there are tons of people who have job titles like
job titles like butcher, for example, and aviators (male and female) were used.
That was the case in the past, around 1930, but today it's no longer said.
We're talking about a pilot, not a pilot.
And there, there, is an orange.
And there, there's a pile of oranges.
Look at Robert and Mireille on their bench.
They're grown up now.
She is 18 or 19 years old and he is 20 or 21 years old.
They are talking. What are they talking about?
They talk about what they wanted to do when they were little.
When she was little, Mireille wanted to be a nurse and an actress.
And Robert wanted to be a firefighter.
Is Robert a firefighter now? No.
Do you think Mireille will become a nurse?
We don't know.
She's studying art history, but you never know how things will turn out.
No, you never know how things will turn out.
Here, take the meeting of Mireille and Robert.
This could go wrong.
Or it could turn out well.
Oh dear! That's not done anymore!
That's no longer done!
I think this is going to end badly.
Idiot!
Ha! What did I tell you!
I knew it was going to end badly.
Okay, goodbye!
Until next time!
...
French subtitles?
Subtitling by Radio-Canada