Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Oh no, no, no, he's not her, no.
It's his little sister Marie-Laure's boat.
Marie-Laure was playing with her boat, and then she fell into the pond.
So she went home to change her clothes.
She lives very close by, just opposite, on the other side of the street.
No, you never know how things will turn out.
Look, I had a friend in the United States who loved the violin.
He played wonderfully well, a true virtuoso.
He dreamed of giving concerts in all the major cities of the world.
Well, do you know what he's doing now?
He's not a violinist at all.
He makes sausage at the Chicago slaughterhouses.
She's like my friend Guylaine's sister.
She wanted to be a pianist and in the end, she works in her dad's office as a typist.
Is that you again? What are you doing here?
Are you bothering me?
Stop, you're annoying me and leave this bench alone.
Well, it's a public bench, isn't it?
This bench is not yours.
It belongs to everyone.
It's a public bench, public bench, public bench.
It's a public bench in a public garden.
And the garden belongs to the state, and so does the bench.
So they belong to me as much as to you.
Non !
Well, here's a young girl who will surely become a lawyer.
Or to the Council of State.
And will defend the interests of society and the state.
Being a lawyer, no, always being on your feet, making big gestures, shouting, it's tiring.
The Council of State, meh, the Senate, maybe, it's almost across the street from the house.
It's convenient, no subway to get to work, but politics doesn't interest me.
So what do you want to do then?
I don't know, maybe a plumber.
Plumber? Why? Are you interested in pipes and taps?
Yes, I like playing with water.
And then, Dad said that plumbers earn more than him.
Besides, when you're a plumber, you work when you want.
If a client calls you and you don't feel like going to work,
Well, we'll just stay home.
Whereas if you want to be an engineer or work in a government ministry,
You have to go to work every day, even if you don't want to.
In life, you never do what you want.
Look, my dad, when he was young, he wanted to be my sister.
Not Mireille, because Mireille is my sister, yes.
Yes, but that's not what I mean. I mean, my sister, like that, it's for people, for those who have back pain.
Well, my dad had cold hands. So, when you have cold hands, you can't succeed like my sister.
Customers can't stand that. So now they're making cars, because cars handle cold hands very well.
Note that this does not prevent my father from being a very warm man.
Cold hands, warm heart, as they say.
Is that what they say?
Yes, that's a common expression. At least, Aunt Georgette says so. And Grandma too.
My father wanted to become a professional athlete, or a boxer or a football player.
Now he is vice president of a major international bank.
Sport can lead to anything.
And all the paths interrupt me, as my aunt Georgette says.
In the family, we always talk about a friend who was sure that one day his son would become an ambassador.
But now, the son in question is a representative for a toy company.
My brother-in-law, Jean-Denis, the husband of my sister Cécile,
He wanted to be a truck driver to drive huge trucks.
One of those 20-ton trucks with 9 or 10 pairs of tires speeding along in a cloud of diesel.
Well, do you know what he's doing now?
He designs jewelry at a jeweler's shop in Place Vendôme.
I have a friend who, in his youth, wanted to become a priest.
However, since last year, he no longer believes in God.
This is a problem for someone who wants to be a priest.
So, he just joined a large insurance company.
La Providence
All my friends want to be in the movies
And they all think they're felines, curosaoua, or truffons.
They are illusions
Maybe, but you never know
In any case, making films is still more interesting than being in the industry.
Agriculture, commerce, business, the judiciary, the military, or education
Yes, that's true, but not everyone can work in film or television.
We need industrialists, farmers, traders, businesswomen and businessmen,
judges, teachers, even military personnel.
We also need filmmakers and videographers.
The trouble with cinema is that, even with a lot of talent, you're never sure of succeeding.
You can never be sure of anything. You never know what's going to happen.
But that doesn't matter. Tell me anyway what you're going to do.
Me? You really want to know.
Well, I think I'll invite you to have something on the terrace of the Closerie des Lilas.
And what are you going to do?
Well, I think I've accepted.
And can I come?
But you're still here? What are you doing here?
Do you know your lessons for tomorrow?
Yeah
And have you done your homework?
And you've finished them?
Almost
Then go finish them, right away.
Oh, can you be annoying?
Since you are American, you must know English.
Yes, a little.
Can you help me with my English homework?
Maybe.
So, this afternoon, at two o'clock, here, okay?
Mireille and Robert are still in Luxembourg.
They are talking about a friend of Robert's who played the violin.
and who wanted to become a professional violinist.
And from a friend of Mireille's who played the piano
and who wanted to become a professional pianist.
If you play the piano very well, you can become a pianist.
If you play the violin very well, you can become a violinist.
If you play the clarinet very well, you can become a clarinetist.
If you play the trumpet very well, you can become a trumpeter.
Robert's friend dreamed of giving big concerts.
It was his dream.
A dream. The little girl is dreaming.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's dreaming.
Orange juice.
Oh, sorry. Thank you.
She's dreaming.
They dream.
Generally, we dream when we sleep.
Have a beautiful dream.
Robert's friend dreamed of giving big concerts.
But you never know how things will turn out.
He does not give concerts today.
They work in Chicago, at the slaughterhouses.
Because in Chicago, there are two specialties.
Large slaughterhouses and...
What else is there in Chicago?
Wind.
Ah yes, wind, yes.
It must be an American idea.
For the French, there are two things in Chicago.
Slaughterhouses and gangsters.
In Chicago, there are slaughterhouses and gangsters.
What is there in Chicago?
There are gangsters and slaughterhouses.
You see? What was I telling you?
And what about New York?
Skyscrapers.
And there you have it, in New York, there are skyscrapers.
And in London, fog.
And in Paris?
In Paris, the Eiffel Tower and the Folies Bergère.
And that's how you do geography.
Okay, getting back to Robert's friend,
Robert works at the Chicago slaughterhouses. He makes sausage. That's fresh sausage. Those are sausages. Dry sausages. One dry sausage, two dry sausages, three dry sausages, four dry sausages, five dry sausages, six dry sausages. Can you say that? Six dry sausages?
Six dry sausages.
Well, Robert's friend, who wanted to be a violinist, makes sausage
And Mireille's friend, who wanted to be a pianist, is a typist.
She's a typist; she does word processing.
In the end, she's not a pianist; in the end, she's a typist.
Let's look at this one
Ultimately, I think this is the one I prefer.
Mireille and Robert are sitting quite peacefully on their bench.
And here comes Marie-Laure to disturb them.
Is that you again? What are you doing here?
Am I bothering you?
Of course it bothers her
Jean-Pierre Andrew, am I bothering you?
No not at all
Am I bothering you?
But no
You don't mind if I work there?
No, no, it doesn't bother me.
Are you sure that doesn't bother you?
No, you're not bothering me.
Marie-Laure is annoying.
You can never have any peace and quiet with her.
You are having a quiet conversation with a friend in Luxembourg.
And poof, she falls into the pool.
Oh dear, but we're never at peace.
Look at it here again
She never leaves her sister alone
Stop
Stop it, Marie-Laure
Oh dear, but we're never at peace.
No, we're never at peace.
Stop it, you're annoying me, and leave this bench alone.
So what? This bench belongs to everyone. It's a public bench, isn't it? It's not yours. It's a public bench, a public bench, a public bench. It's a public bench in a public garden. And the garden belongs to the state, and so do the benches.
– The bench belongs to the state. It belongs to everyone.
It belongs to Marie-Laure, as well as to Mireille or Aunt Georgette.
Look at Marie-Laure, she's holding a boat.
Whose boat is it? It belongs to her, it's her boat.
The boat belongs to him.
Here, she is holding Fido, but Fido does not belong to her.
He doesn't belong to her. Fido belongs to Aunt Georgette.
Marie-Laure might become a lawyer.
A lawyer, me?
No, always being on your feet, shouting, making big gestures, it's tiring.
The judges are seated, but the lawyers are standing.
So you work standing up, then?
Yes.
That's right, just like me.
You work standing up, too.
You're a nurse, I bet.
Oh really? I thought that...
Well no.
Note that it's not just the nurses who are standing.
The lawyers are standing and making grand gestures.
Jean-Claude, please use grand gestures.
The Council of State, meh. The Senate.
The Senate, yes. That's what interests Marie-Laure.
She lives almost opposite.
It's convenient for getting to work. No need to take the metro. Because the problem when you work in Paris is that you have to take the metro to get to work.
We spend all our time on the subway and then at work, at work. That worker over there is at work. And over there, Marie-Laure is asleep, in bed. Subway, work, sleep.
The Senate wouldn't be bad, but politics doesn't interest Marie-Laure.
Politics doesn't interest me.
Plumber, yes, that interests Marie-Laure. It's a good job.
We play with pipes, with taps.
We earn well, we earn a lot of money.
If you want to work, you work.
If you don't want to work, you don't work.
We stay home and take a nap.
Look at the Bélots here. They're at home.
Aunt Georgette, she's at home here.
This gentleman is at home.
They are at home.
She is at home. He is at home. We are at home.
Mr. Bello wanted to be a masseur to massage people who have back pain.
A woman who gives massages is a masseuse.
And a man who gives massages is a masseur.
And a lady who has the same parents as me is a masseur.
That's a masseur.
Masseuse, a masseur.
Is Mr. Bello my sister?
Non.
He is an engineer at Renault.
He manufactures cars.
For what ?
Well, because he always had cold hands.
And my sister's customers don't like cold hands.
Look at this woman.
She doesn't like cold hands either.
That's not right, is it?
Clients of massage therapists don't like cold hands.
They can't stand it
And Mireille can't stand being tickled, look
Stop, I can't stand being tickled.
Clients of massage therapists cannot tolerate cold hands.
So, naturally, one cannot succeed as a masseur.
If your hands are cold
We cannot succeed
Here's someone who succeeded
And here's someone who didn't succeed.
Look at Robert here.
He tries, but he doesn't succeed.
And you know how to say that?
Are the archduchess's socks dry and bone dry?
The archduchess's socks...
He tries, but he doesn't succeed.
To succeed, I succeed, you succeed, he succeeds
We succeed, you succeed, they succeed
Mr. Bello always had cold hands
So, obviously, you can't succeed like my sister if you have cold hands.
Look, Madame Bello thinks Marie-Laure looks tired.
Of course, it's not surprising, it's inevitable, she works all the time.
"You look tired."
"Of course, I spend my nights doing homework. That's why I look tired."
Mr. Bello has cold hands, but a warm heart. He is warm and cordial.
Mr. Bello has cold hands, but that doesn't stop him from being very warm. It doesn't stop him.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She's preventing Mireille from working.
He was a little...
Stop, you're preventing me from working.
Go do your homework.
My throat hurts.
That doesn't stop you from doing your homework.
She may have a sore throat, but she can still do her homework.
Mireille is short.
She looks fragile, but that doesn't stop her from being very athletic, very strong.
Robert's father wanted to be a professional athlete.
He is the vice president of a bank.
Sport leads to everything, and all roads lead to Rome.
One path, one path that leads to Rome, another path that leads to Rome.
All roads lead to Rome.
Rome, Italy.
Cécile's husband wanted to be a truck driver.
Truck drivers drive the trucks.
A 4 or 5 ton truck.
A large truck weighing 10 or 20 tons.
With 9 or 10 pairs of tires.
One tire, several tires.
But Cécile's husband is not a truck driver.
He doesn't drive huge trucks, no. Ultimately, he works for a jeweler. He designs jewelry. He invents jewelry. He creates jewelry.
He works at a jeweler's in Place Vendôme, where there are some very chic jewelers.
I have a friend who, in his youth, wanted to become a priest.
He wanted to be a priest when he was young, in his youth. The trouble, the problem, is that he no longer believes in God. Look at this woman. She used to believe in God, and now she doesn't.
She used to believe in God, but she no longer believes in God.
She believed, she no longer believes
Robert's friend no longer believes in God
He no longer believes
So now he's an insurance agent.
He works for an insurance company
He sells insurance against fire, theft, and accidents.
His insurance company is called Providence
All of Mireille's friends want to be in the movies
They think they're great filmmakers.
They believe they are great filmmakers.
But they are deluding themselves.
Look at Marie-Laure here
She's deluding herself, too.
She believes Mireille will solve her problem.
Look, I don't know how to solve my problem
If you think I'm going to solve your problem, you're deluding yourself.
Oh dear, you're not nice, you're not classy
Everyone is deluding themselves.
We believe we are going to be a great violinist
And then we make sausage in the Chicago slaughterhouses
Note that not everyone can be a violinist or a filmmaker
We also need manufacturers, farmers, and retailers.
Businessmen and women, judges, teachers, military personnel
He's in the army, he's a soldier.
And he, he makes films, he's in the film industry, he's a filmmaker.
The problem with cinema is that even with talent, you're never sure of succeeding.
That's the trouble, that's the problem.
Look, observe Marie-Laure who wants to buy some gumballs.
I feel like going to buy some gumballs.
Ben vas-y.
The problem is that I don't have any money.
If you think I'm going to give you money to go buy your gumballs
You're deluding yourself.
The problem with filmmaking is that you're never sure of succeeding.
You can never be sure of anything
We think we're going to be priests, and then we become insurance agents.
Mireille agrees completely; she knows that you can never be sure of anything.
"Oh, you can never be sure of anything. You never know what's going to happen. But that doesn't matter. Tell me anyway what you're going to do."
Do you know what Robert is going to do? Well, he's going to invite Mireille to have something at the Closerie des Lilas.
Here are Robert and Mireille having something at the Closerie des Lilas. They're having a drink.
"Would you like something?"
Marie-Laure also wants to go and get something at the Closerie des Lilas.
And can I come?
Now you will speak.
Listen to this dialogue between Mireille and Marie-Laure.
And can I come?
Do you know your lessons for tomorrow?
Yeah.
And have you done your homework?
And you've finished them?
Almost.
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille.
And can I come?
Do you know your lessons for tomorrow?
Yeah !
And have you done your homework?
And you've finished them?
Almost !
Then go finish them right away.
The problem for Marie-Laure is that there are always lessons to learn, homework to do.
Phew, I'm done.
Have you done all your homework?
Yes.
Always homework, always lessons.
She's never sure she knows her lessons.
Do you know your lessons for tomorrow?
Yeah.
Do you know your lessons?
Uh, yes.
Do you know them?
Are you sure?
Observe. Marie-Laure knows her lessons.
She knows what 8 x 8 equals.
8 x 8, 64.
She doesn't know who Bruce is.
Who is this Bruce?
She knows how to jump rope.
It's the verb "to know".
She knows, it's the sound.
She knows Robert.
She knows Colette.
She knows the Latin Quarter.
She knows Brittany.
She doesn't know Bruce.
She doesn't know who it is.
She doesn't know what she's doing there.
She doesn't know where he lives.
Let's see if you remember some professions.
That gentleman who is playing the trumpet is a trumpeter.
And that's a lawyer.
Those are magistrates, judges.
And that's a masseur.
That's a plumber.
And he, the truck driver, he's a truck driver. And this gentleman who makes films, he's a filmmaker. Filmmaking is all very well, it's very interesting, but the trouble with filmmaking is that you're never sure of succeeding, even if you have talent.
Do you know how to spell it, talent?
With a T at the end or a D?
I have talent, I'm going to be a filmmaker
You, talented?
Yes indeed, Mr. Guignol, I have talent.
I have a lot of talent and I'm going to be a filmmaker
I am sure I will succeed as a filmmaker
No, Mr. Robert, you cannot succeed as a filmmaker.
You don't have enough talent
So, I'm going to be a lawyer.
No, Mr. Robert, you don't speak well enough.
Yes, yes, I'm sure I'll succeed as a lawyer.
No, you can't succeed as a lawyer.
Yes, it does.
But no.
You can never be sure of succeeding.
You can never be sure of anything, no.
You can never be sure of anything.
Subtitles ST' 501
...
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada