Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Paris, the Latin Quarter.
The district of schools, faculties, the district of studies and students.
His name is Robert.
Her name is Mireille.
Are they students? Yes, probably.
Look, they're talking.
The students study, they demonstrate, and the rest of the time they discuss.
Robert invited Mireille to have something.
What? I don't know.
At the Lilas farm.
They crossed the Luxembourg Gardens,
passed by the Institute of Art and Archaeology,
where Mireille is taking a course.
The room on the right is the Institute of Art and Archaeology.
I'm taking a course in Greek art there.
And they sat down on the terrace of the Closerie des Lilas.
It was 11:15 on the observatory clock
And 5:15 on Robert's watch
What time is it?
11:00, 11:15, 11:15
I still had the New York time
Why did you want to come here?
You know, I don't know many cafes in Paris.
I knew this one because of Hemingway, Scott Fitzgerald, and Gertrude Stein.
You never come here?
No, this is the first time.
You don't like it?
Yes, yes. But it's a bit too fancy and too expensive for a poor little student like me.
When I want to have coffee with my friends, I usually go to a small bistro in the neighborhood.
What can I get you?
Let's see.
Hemingway probably drank whisky, but that's not particularly French.
What are some typical French aperitifs?
You have the Dubonnet, the Martini.
That's Italian, isn't it?
The Ambassador, Pernod, Ricard.
I love Pernod, but it's a bit too strong.
Suze, Pinot des Charentes, Saint Raphaël, Bir, Kir.
That's it, I'll have a Kir.
And what about the gentleman?
The same.
So you're studying art history.
Yes, I have always loved drawing and painting.
Even as a very young child in kindergarten, I would delight in plunging my fingers into pots of colors.
And I dabbled in admirable abstract paintings.
I was unbeatable. I was the class champion.
And I kept the title until the end of kindergarten.
Later in primary school, the teacher showed us reproductions of Matisse murals.
Overwhelmed with admiration, that very evening I set about covering the walls and ceiling of my room with frescoes.
My parents didn't appreciate it. In France, great artists are always misunderstood.
Matisse's paintings must have been an avant-garde school.
An avant-garde school? Why?
You know, Matisse was considered an avant-garde painter around 1910.
Was it a private school?
No, the local school. A public school.
It must have been a good school.
Meh, like all the others.
You know, in France, all schools are pretty much the same.
Generally speaking, it is the State that finances and controls national education.
And the system is the same throughout France.
Then later in high school, you continued to make art and study art history.
But no, you might think. There are so many other subjects to study.
Just in history, for example. We study ancient history, the history of France,
the Middle Ages, modern times, the contemporary era, the history of foreign countries.
It never ends, not to mention the geography.
That doesn't leave much time for art history.
THANKS.
I took a course in European history.
When I was in high school in the United States
I didn't like it very much.
Too many kings, too many wars
But are you obligated to study history?
Of course, history is mandatory
Like almost all materials, for that matter.
You know, until the first year of high school, we don't have many choices.
Which course did you take?
Well, I did A in my first year
That is to say, the letters section
I studied Latin, but not Greek.
And then I took the courses common to all sections.
I studied French, naturally.
Maths, unfortunately, because I've always been terrible at maths.
I almost failed my baccalaureate exam because of math.
And then I studied natural sciences.
Zoology, geology, physiology, botany.
I really enjoyed botany, because of the flowers.
I love flowers. I was very good at botany.
And then I did chemistry, physics, what else?
De la philo en terminale.
The last year of high school before the baccalaureate exam.
And then I studied languages, German and English.
Ah, you know English?
Yes, a little. But I didn't learn it in high school.
I completed three years of study in England.
Foreign languages ​​are taught rather poorly in high school.
And you can imagine that with all the subjects on the curriculum,
You never really know anything completely.
Even if you don't learn anything thoroughly, it all gives the impression of an enormous amount of work.
Yes, there's work to be done.
The worst part is working from home.
Homework to do, lessons to learn, written tests to prepare for.
Not to mention the obsession with getting the baccalaureate at the end of studies.
In short, you must be very glad to have finished with high school.
Yes, you can say that again.
Now, at university, I feel much freer.
I enjoy all the courses I'm taking.
Especially the Greek art courses.
The teacher is a sweetheart.
He is as handsome as a god and so spiritual.
It's a delight to listen to him.
Okay, so be careful.
Today, we're going to talk about schools.
Let's go.
Last time, Robert and Mireille were in Luxembourg.
Robert invited Mireille to have something at the Closerie des Lilas.
They got up, they crossed the garden,
They passed by the Institute of Art and Archaeology, arrived at the enclosed garden and sat down.
Mireille sat down, then Robert sat down.
That's in the past.
That happened last time.
These are verbs in the past tense.
He avoided it, they crossed, they passed, they arrived, they sat down.
Note that these verbs are composed of two parts.
That's why we call this past tense the passé composé.
The passé composé is composed of a form of the verb, the past participle, invited, crossed, past, arrived, and an auxiliary.
A, on, that's the verb "to have." It's the present tense of the verb "to have." And "son" is the verb "to be." The present tense of the verb "to be."
In summary, the passé composé is composed of an auxiliary verb, avoir or être, and the past participle of the verb.
So now we have two past tenses: the imperfect and the passé composé.
For example, if I say last time Robert and Mireille were in Luxembourg, they were talking sitting on a bench, they were sitting, they were talking, that is the imperfect tense.
But if I say Robert invited Mireille, they got up, they crossed the garden, they arrived at the enclosure, they sat down, invited, got up, crossed, arrived, sat down, that is the past tense.
When Robert and Mireille sat down on the terrace of the enclosed garden,
It was 11:15 on the observatory clock
and five o'clock, fifteen, five and a quarter according to Robert's watch.
That's a clock.
And this is a watch.
And that's a clock.
A watch, a clock.
Let's see, what time is it?
It is 4:15 AM here, 4:15 AM.
It is 3:20 AM here.
It is 10:30 here, 10:30.
And what time is it here?
Here, it is 3:45, or a quarter to 4.
Here, it is 8:50, or 7:40.
And here, it is 9:55, or 8:55.
And here, it's 4:10, well, not exactly, it's about 4:10.
And here, it is 3:46 PM.
When you want to be precise, you don't say approximately 4:45, you say 3:46 PM.
Train schedules and flight schedules, for example, use this 24-hour system.
Look. What time is this train?
17h51.
17h49.
And this bus, it leaves at 2:10 pm and arrives at 2:43 pm.
When Robert and Mireille arrived at the farmhouse, it was around 11:15 on the observatory clock and 5:15 on Robert's watch.
When you come from the United States, you have to set your watch forward 6 hours because of the time difference
The Paris Observatory is very close to the Closerie des Lilas.
Robert chose La Closerie because it is a fairly famous cafe, a literary cafe where many poets and writers used to come, Hemingway, Scott Fitzgerald, Gertrude Stein and many others.
Does Mireille come to the Closerie often?
No, this is the first time.
This isn't a cafe for students, it's a bit too posh and too expensive.
But it's a bit too fancy and too expensive for a poor little student like me.
It's chic, it's elegant. Look at that. Is it chic? Yes, it's quite chic.
And that, that too, is chic. And this, is that a chic café? Yes, it's chic.
It's chic and it's expensive. Generally, chic places are expensive.
When Mireille wants to have a coffee, she doesn't go to a big, fancy, expensive cafe.
She usually goes to a small bistro.
It may be less chic, but it's also cheaper.
That's a great coffee shop.
That's a small bistro.
Mireille doesn't want to order whisky because it's not French.
She's looking for a very French aperitif.
What kind of typically French aperitif do you have?
There are many appetizers.
There's Dubonnet, Martini, Pastis, Suze, Ricard, Muscat,
and many others.
Finally, she chose a kheer.
Okay, I'm going to have a kheer.
It's a little crème de cassis with white wine.
Robert is not familiar with all of these aperitifs.
He doesn't know what to take.
So, he takes the same thing.
The same applies to the gentleman.
And enjoy!
And then, you're going to play the role of Mireille.
You have the Dubonnet, the Martini.
That's Italian, isn't it?
The Ambassador, Pernod, Ricard.
Ah, Pernod, I love it, but it's a bit too strong.
Suze, Pinot des Charentes, Saint-Raphaël, Bir, Kyr.
Okay, I'll have a Kyr.
To you, you are Mireille.
You have the Dubonnet, the Martini.
That's Italian, isn't it? That's Italian, isn't it?
That's Italian, isn't it?
The Ambassador, Pernod, Ricard.
I love Pernod, but it's a bit too strong.
Suze, Pinot des Charentes, Saint-Raphaël, Bir, Kyr.
Oh, that's it, I'll have a Kyr.
Robert resumes the conversation.
SO?
So, you're studying art history.
Mireille loves drawing and painting.
Here's a drawing.
Ah, and what about my drawing, huh?
Here's someone who paints.
Here is a painting.
She is a painter, she paints.
He also paints.
Even when she was little, Mireille loved painting.
She dipped her fingers into the paint pots and daubed admirable abstract paintings.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's all covered in chocolate.
Look, you're all smeared with sweat.
She's all smeared with jam.
Mireille was very good at drawing and painting.
She was the champion of the class.
A champion, a female champion.
She was unbeatable.
Look at Marie-Laure here
She is very good at arithmetic.
She is unbeatable
9 x 6
7 x 7
9 x 9
You're unbeatable
Yeah, I'm a champion.
She is very strong
She is unbeatable
When she was very little
When she was 5 years old
Mireille went to nursery school
Then she went to primary school. After primary school, she went to secondary school, then middle school, and finally high school.
She passed her baccalaureate and went to university. Now she's at university, at college.
This is a nursery school. Nursery school is for toddlers.
Primary school is for slightly older children, roughly between 6 and 11 years old.
We learn to read, to write, to count.
After primary school, there is secondary school, middle school and high school.
When Mireille was in primary school, the teacher showed the children reproductions of Matisse.
Mireille thought it was very beautiful. She liked it.
She was very impressed. She was filled with admiration.
Ah, how handsome he is!
Here, Marie-Laure is filled with admiration for her new boat.
She likes him a lot; she finds him very handsome.
Ah, how handsome he is!
And this one, do you like it?
And Degas, do you like him?
Do you like your room?
Oh, she's magnificent!
So, do you like this big house?
Yes.
Observe this.
I like it, I enjoy it.
Mireille likes it, Mireille enjoys it, she likes it.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
Does she like chocolate mousse?
Does she think it's good?
Mmm, that's delicious.
Yes, she likes it, she enjoys it.
Now, look at Marie-Laure.
Do you find her pretty? Do you find her cute?
Do you like it?
Yes, I quite like her.
And Mireille, do you like her?
And Robert, do you find him handsome? Do you like him?
I see a guy every morning, I think I like him.
It's the verb "to please".
Mireille really liked the Matisse reproductions.
He liked them very much.
He likes them, that's the present.
They pleased him, that's the past, the past perfect.
So Mireille started painting on the walls and ceiling of her room.
That's a room, that's Marie-Laure's room.
That's a room too, it's a hotel room.
And this is Mireille's parents' bedroom.
Generally, a room has four walls and a ceiling.
A wall, a wall, a wall.
And he, he paints the ceiling.
A ceiling.
Mireille set about covering the walls and ceiling of her room with drawing.
She undertook, she began, that's the verb to undertake.
She set about covering the walls with drawings.
These are walls covered in drawings and graffiti.
A wall covered in posters.
And here's a table covered in numbers.
It's the verb "to cover".
But Mireille's parents didn't like her drawings.
They didn't understand that it was art.
Parents are stupid, they don't understand children.
Children are misunderstood.
Great artists are always misunderstood.
To understand, understood, misunderstood.
In France, there are two types of schools.
Public schools and private schools, generally religious.
Mireille went to a public school.
The local school, a school like any other.
In France, all schools are pretty much the same.
Did you go to primary school?
Yes.
Was it a public school or a private school?
It was a public school.
The school system is the same throughout France.
The state finances and controls national education.
After primary school, Mireille went to high school.
She studied a whole range of subjects.
She studied ancient history, Egypt, Greece, Rome.
She studied French history, all periods of French history,
the Middle Ages, modern times, and also the history of foreign countries,
Russia, England, Germany.
When you're French, Germany is a foreign country.
When you're German, France is a foreign country.
Everyone studies history in high school.
Are you studying history? Yes. Is history good? I like it. Robert took a European history course, but he didn't like it. He didn't enjoy it. He thought there were too many wars, too many kings. But I didn't really like it either. Too many kings, too many wars.
Of course, in European history, there are many kings.
Look, just in France, you have François I, Henri II, Henri III, Charles IX, Louis XIII, Louis XIV, Louis XV.
There have been many kings and many wars.
The Gallic Wars, the Hundred Years' War, the Wars of Religion, the Napoleonic Wars, the First World War, the Second World War.
Mireille spent seven years in secondary school.
She entered sixth grade when she was eleven years old.
Then she did her fifth year, and then the fourth, the third, the second, the first and finally the final year.
Botany, that's what she really enjoyed. She liked it a lot.
She was very good at botany.
But math, no. She didn't like it. She didn't enjoy it.
She wasn't good at math. In fact, she was very bad at math.
She was useless, zero.
She always got bad grades, zeros.
So she didn't like it.
She hated math.
She is not the only one.
I hate math.
And do you like math?
None.
But that's not true, they're rubbish, rubbish, rubbish.
Mireille was so bad at math
that she almost failed her baccalaureate exam because of math.
Note that she did not fail her baccalaureate exam.
She didn't miss.
No, she succeeded.
Look at Jean-Claude here.
Okay, very good, he succeeded.
But there, I missed.
That's a failure.
But that's very good, it's a success.
Failed, succeeded.
That's a failure.
Look at that man over there.
He missed his train.
He didn't get it, he missed it.
He missed his train too.
And here, he didn't miss, he got it.
He caught his train, but he almost missed it.
Robert almost got run over
He almost had an accident
He too almost had an accident
And look at Jean-Claude here
He almost fell
Mireille almost failed her baccalaureate exam because of math.
But she didn't miss, she got him
She worked a lot
Because there is a lot of work in high school
There are too many things to take in
So we don't do anything thoroughly
We study everything superficially
Look at Mireille. She's studying superficially. Look here. The swimmer is on the surface. Here, she's at the bottom. Here, the miner is working on the surface. But here, he's working at the bottom.
Look at this woman. She's cleaning superficially. Here, she's cleaning thoroughly. There, the doctor is examining the patient superficially.
Here, he examines it thoroughly.
When you go to primary school, but especially to high school, there is a lot of work to do.
We don't feel free, we can't do what we want.
There are always lessons to learn or homework to do
Look, see Marie-Laure here
Have you done your homework?
No, not yet.
So you're going to do your homework and then we'll see.
You see, she is not free.
The prisoners are not free.
Children are not free either.
Since she started university, Mireille feels freer.
She feels freer.
Look at her. She's feeling good.
Not here. She doesn't feel well.
I'm sick.
Please stop. I don't feel well. I'm sick.
Are you not feeling well?
It's the verb "to feel," to feel good or not good.
Now, Mireille feels good, she feels freer.
Yes, you can say that again.
Now, at university, I feel much freer.
I enjoy all the courses I take, especially the Greek art courses.
The teacher is a sweetheart.
He's a little sweetheart, he's cute.
He is as handsome as a god.
Like a Greek god, I suppose.
For the Greeks, the gods, in general, were beautiful.
Mireille's teacher is handsome, or at least she finds him handsome and witty.
He's very quick-witted, he's funny.
It's a delight to listen to him.
It's very pleasant, it's a treat.
It's a treat.
Okay, so now it's your turn to speak.
Look, what time is it?
Five past five or five fifteen?
Or 5:15 PM?
And here, it is 10:30.
Is this a large cafe or a small bistro?
A small bistro.
Look at Jean-Claude here. Did he fall?
No, but he almost fell.
Look at this man. What is he doing?
Does he do mathematics, music, or motorcycling?
No, he paints.
Robert didn't much like the European history course.
because there were too many kings and too much war.
We study history, we study geography,
We study Latin, we study Greek,
We do French, we do math, unfortunately.
We study natural sciences, naturally.
We do physics, we do chemistry,
to infinity.
French subtitles?
...
Subtitles ST' 501
for humanity.