Subtitles ST' 501
Paris, the Luxembourg Gardens.
The Lilac Farm.
Two young people, a young girl and a young man, are talking about their studies.
He's handsome, he's handsome, he's so handsome. You can't imagine how handsome he is.
Who?
And the Greek art teacher, he has the head of Michelangelo's Moses.
I swear.
Oh really? Is it that old?
Excuse me, I'm sorry.
There's some on your skirt.
Add a little water, it will come off right away.
Oh, never mind, it doesn't matter.
It's not a big deal, it's nothing.
It's an old skirt, I almost never wear it.
There we go, here we go.
So, if I understand correctly, you enjoy your studies at university.
Ah yes, you know, after high school, in high school, you don't have a minute to yourself.
We are never at peace. We are not free.
There's always something to do. It's forced labor.
At university, it's more relaxed. We work, we work a lot if we want to,
But we're not forced. We do what we want.
In high school, I never had time to read for myself, for my own pleasure.
Now I can take the time to read.
Actually, these past few days I've been reading Hemingway.
Ah, Hemingway, mademoiselle.
He always positioned himself where you were.
Oh yes, really?
Yes, miss, at this very table
Impossible, is that true?
Yes, miss
Ah, what a man!
Did you know him?
No, miss, I'm too young
I've only been at the farm for a year.
But I was told that, miss
People who knew him
What a writer, what talent!
Have you read it?
No, miss, I don't have time.
You know what it's like: work, family, garden.
I am not familiar with his work, but I have heard of it.
It seems he drank a lot.
Well, he was a genius writer.
Well, I'm not a writer and I'm not a genius,
But I think I'll drink it anyway.
The same, please.
Are you a student?
Yes.
Non.
Well, I was. I guess I'm still a student.
But right now, I'm not studying.
I have just left university after two years of study.
I decided to take a year off work.
Hey, you've taken some time off.
You take a year's vacation, just like that.
How convenient. What a great idea.
And why didn't I think of that?
Why did you take leave?
To find me.
To find you?
Poor little thing, you were lost.
Are you making fun of me?
Me, never. I never make fun of anyone.
But what do you mean when you say I want to find myself?
Well, I want to think about it.
I want to take stock.
I want to see where I stand.
I want to discover what I really want to do.
to know if I want to continue or do something else.
I see. In short, you'd had enough.
You didn't like studying.
No, that's not it at all.
I think we are taught too many useless things.
I find the teaching method far too authoritarian.
Far too top-down.
I find that education is not adapted to modern life.
That's all. That's all.
But tell me, were you a good student?
Ah yes, not bad at all, very good.
I have always been a good student.
I always got good grades, I always passed all my exams.
I have never failed an exam. Never.
I am what you would call gifted.
My teachers even said I was gifted.
I learned to read almost entirely on my own.
No kidding. And to write as well.
Did you learn to write all by yourself?
Yes. And I've always been one of the best students in my class.
And you also received the prize for modesty.
There you go again, making fun of me.
Me? Not at all.
Never in my life. No, but I understand perfectly. You're just saying things as they are.
So today, Mireille and Robert are still on the terrace of the Closerie des Lilas.
They talk about their studies. Well, Mireille mostly talks about her Greek art teacher who is so handsome.
He's handsome, so handsome. He's handsome, but you can't imagine how handsome he is.
Robert pretends not to understand who she's talking about.
Who?
The Greek art teacher. He looks just like Michelangelo's Moses. I swear.
I swear to you, it's true. I swear it's true.
These are people who swear.
In a court of law, you must swear to tell the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth.
Mireille says the Greek art teacher is very handsome.
He has a beautiful head. He has the head of Michelangelo's Moses.
He has the head of Michelangelo's Moses. I swear.
Oh yeah, he's that old.
Oh, Robert doesn't like that at all.
It annoys him. He thinks he's more handsome than Michelangelo's Moses.
What do you think?
Mireille thinks her teacher is very good.
Robert doesn't like that, so bam, he spills his drink on Mireille's skirt.
Oh, excuse me, I'm sorry, there's some on your skirt.
Oh, never mind, it doesn't matter
It's not a big deal, it's nothing.
It's an old skirt, I almost never wear it
Robert s'excuse
Ah, excuse me, I'm sorry
We say "I'm sorry" to apologize.
But we also say "I'm sorry" when we disagree.
We agree, 250,000
No, Mr. Caladien, no, no, I'm sorry, but it's impossible.
Look here. The old professor apologizes.
Excuse me.
Here, Mireille apologizes.
Excuse me, I'm in a hurry.
I apologize.
Excuse me, I'm late. I had an appointment, so I couldn't do otherwise.
No, it's not a problem.
Excuse me, miss.
Excuse me for yesterday, but I had to take my little sister to her dance class.
Excuse me, I'm sorry.
Robert apologizes, but Mireille doesn't take it seriously.
It's not a big deal, it's nothing.
It's an old skirt, I almost never wear it
She never wears it?
Oh, what a liar!
Look, she wears it almost every day
Here, she's wondering which dress she's going to wear.
Here, Marie-Laure puts on her socks
Here, she is wearing earrings
And here, she wants to wear her pink dress.
Mom, can I wear my pink dress to go play?
No, you look much better this way.
Oh, I want to wear my pink dress
Infinitive, to put
Present tense: I put, you put, he/she/it puts, we put, you (plural) put, he/she/it puts
To allow, I allow, you allow, he/she/it allows, we allow, you (plural) allow, he/she/it allows
Past tense, I put, I allowed
Robert spilled his kir on Mireille's skirt.
Then the boy rushes off
Add a little water, it'll come off right away
With a little water, it will come off
Look at Marie-Laure, she's covered in jam
But it's going to start
Here we go, it's started!
Mireille protests
She doesn't want the boy to bother
Don't bother, it's not worth it.
Now it's your turn.
You are Mireille
Imagine Robert spilling his leather on your skirt
What are you saying?
It's not a big deal, it's nothing.
The boy rushes off
Add a little water, it'll come off right away
What are you saying?
Don't bother, it's not worth it.
Robert resumes the conversation
So if I understand correctly, you enjoy your studies at university?
Yes, Mireille prefers being at university to being in high school
In high school, there's too much work, we're not free
It's like forced labor.
We are always forced to work.
You are being forced to work.
Look at Mireille here.
Come on, eat Marie-Laure.
Don't force yourself if you're not hungry.
She wants to force Marie-Laure to eat.
But here, she doesn't force her.
She lets her go.
Do you want to come with me to Luxembourg?
I don't know.
Okay, do as you wish.
You are not forced.
She is being forced.
In high school, you're always forced to work.
But at university, it's more relaxed.
We are not forced to work if we don't want to.
Now Mireille can read if she wants to.
But she is not forced.
She can read for pleasure.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
Does she read for pleasure? No.
Here, yes, she reads for pleasure.
Now Mireille can read for pleasure.
Actually, these past few days I've been reading Hemingway.
You know Hemingway, he's a writer, an American writer, he was a writer, he wrote
Mireille also writes, but she's not a writer yet. Marie-Laure also writes, but she isn't.
Robert wasn't a writer, not yet. Hemingway also wrote, but he wasn't a writer.
A writer, a great writer, a talented writer. What a writer, what talent! He had...
Genius. He was a genius writer. The boy didn't read Hemingway. He didn't read his work. He
He hasn't read his books. He doesn't know his work. But he's heard about it. He's heard
hear.
Hemingway, you know him?
Yes, of course I know him. He was a great writer.
Listen, can you hear?
Yes, Hemingway is very good.
Did you hear that?
I heard about it. I heard
someone who was talking about Hemingway.
I can say that I have
I've heard of Hemingway.
And Lacan, do you know him?
Have you heard about it?
Marie-Laure, however, has none.
Never heard of it.
Who is this Lacan?
A psychoanalyst
I've never heard of it.
It's the verb "to hear".
I hear, you hear, he hears, we hear, you (plural) hear, they hear
What is that noise we hear?
Waiting, I'm waiting
Hear
To wait for
These people are waiting, Robert is waiting here, Mireille is waiting, and there she hears something, Marie
Laure hears her mother and here the teacher waits, waits (present tense: I wait; past tense: I have waited)
to hear present I hear past perfect I heard the boy did not read Emingway but he
I've heard of him; I don't know his work, but I've heard of him, apparently.
They say he drank a lot, they say Emingway drank a lot, look at Mireille and Robert here, they
They are drinking kir.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's drinking.
She drinks an Orangina. She doesn't drink alcohol.
I drink Orangina.
No, you know, young people don't drink alcohol anymore.
They drink water.
But there are people who drink alcohol, cognac, rum, wine.
Hemingway, on the other hand, drank alcohol, whiskey, wine.
Mr. Courtois also drinks quite a bit.
And they, they drank a little
I drink, you drink, they drink, we drink, you (plural) drink
In the imperfect tense, we drank, they drank, etc.
And in the past tense, he drank, you drank, etc.
Robert drank a Kia
And now he's going to drink a second one
Well, I'm not a writer and I'm not a genius, but I think I'll still drink the same thing, please.
And Mireille resumes the conversation.
Are you a student?
Robert hesitates.
Yes. No. Well, I used to be. I suppose I'm still a student, but right now, I'm not studying.
I have just left university after two years of study.
He is no longer at university because he left university.
Here is a young man leaving university.
He's leaving, he's going away.
You can leave university, you can leave your friends.
Robert left university.
He went on vacation, he took a leave of absence.
I decided to take a year off work.
"Look at these people. Are they on vacation? No, they're not on vacation. They're working. And these people, are they working? No, they're on vacation."
"Observe Mr. Bello and Hubert."
"Hello, sir. I didn't expect to find you here. Are you ill?"
"No, I simply took a day off."
Ah, look at Mireille here. Is she working? Is she going to university? Is she studying? No, she's sick. She's on sick leave.
And Robert, is he on sick leave? No, no, no, no, no. He's not sick. He just took leave. An idea. It's a good idea, isn't it?
Hey, you've taken a leave of absence. You're taking a year off, just like that. How convenient. What a great idea.
That's a good idea. It's convenient. It's easy.
Look at Marie-Laure. She's carrying everything in her arms like that. It's not easy.
But with a tray, it's easier. It's more convenient.
Take a tray, it's more convenient.
Hold.
Yes, that's true, it's more convenient.
Okay, so Robert has taken leave.
He took leave of absence on his own, all by himself.
To put, to get into.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She sets the table, she puts the glasses on the table,
But she doesn't know where to put the knife.
The knife on the right and the fork on the left.
She doesn't know where to put herself here.
Where do I put myself?
You, you're going to sit there, next to Dad.
Here, they sit down at a table.
And here, where is Robert going to put himself?
In front or behind?
Stand in front.
No, I prefer to sit behind.
He was there, and he positioned himself behind.
Past tense, he went on leave.
He took a leave of absence, he left university to find himself.
To find himself, Robert.
Why did you take leave?
To find me.
To find you? Poor little thing, you were lost.
Look, he's lost. He doesn't know where he is.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's lost her Asterix.
Now she has found it.
Hey, where are my glasses?
I can't find my glasses! I've lost my glasses! Oh no, no, no, no, no, there they are!
I found them. You can lose your glasses, you can lose a book, you can lose a button.
You lost a button, yes, but I have it in my pocket. When Robert said he took leave to...
Mireille found him, mocking him, poor little thing, you were lost, you're mocking me, me never
I never lack for anyone, that's not true. Mireille is mocking, she likes to make fun of people.
People Marie Laure is also mocking; she makes fun of Uncle Guillaume when he jumps rope.
Mireille is mocking Robert, but what do you mean when you say "I want to..."
to find, well, I want to think, I want to take stock, I want to see where I stand, Robert wants
think, look at Rodin's Thinker, he's thinking, he's reflecting, look at Mireille there, she
Robert thinks, wanting to know where he stands. He doesn't know where he stands; he's a little lost.
Look at Aunt Georgette here.
She no longer knows where she stands.
So many Georgettes!
Oh, attends, attends, attends.
Oh, I don't know where I stand anymore.
Now it's Marie-Laure who doesn't know where she stands anymore.
Marie-Laure!
Come here!
Yes, one minute!
Oh, I don't know where I am now.
Robert wants to know where he stands.
He wants to take stock.
When you want to know where you are on a boat, you need to take a bearing.
Here is a sailor, a naval officer, taking stock.
Look at this drawing by Dubou. The train is lost.
The driver takes stock of his position to determine where he is.
Mireille thinks Robert left university because he'd had enough.
Because it bored him. Because he didn't like it.
In short, you'd had enough. You didn't like studying.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's eating too much candy.
Mireille thinks she's had enough, that it's time to stop.
No, you've had enough.
Here, Marie-Laure is bothering Mireille. Mireille has had enough.
Stop, I've had enough.
Robert criticizes the teaching.
He thinks that many useless things are taught.
He finds that the teaching is not adapted to modern life. It's not adapted. Look. This, this, yes, that's adapted, it's well adapted, yes. But this, this, no. This, this, that's not adapted. That won't do.
Look at that
That, that's suitable
It's well suited, it adapts
But that, that's a poor fit
It's not, it's not, it's not well suited
Robert makes a lot of criticisms
First, too many useless things are taught.
Second, the teaching is too authoritarian.
Third, the teaching is directive.
Four, not suited to modern life
Mireille makes fun of him
That's all.
That's all, nothing more, that's all. You have no other criticisms, that's all. Observe, Marie-Laure.
Just one
That's all, yes. Now observe Mireille's reaction, and next time, what would you like me to bring you?
A Walkman, a camera for making movies, and a bicycle—that's all.
Mireille thinks that Robert criticizes teaching because he was a bad student.
But tell me, were you a good student?
But Robert says that he was always a very good student, that he always passed all his exams, that he was very intelligent, very gifted, even gifted.
I've always been a good student. I've always gotten good grades. I've always passed all my exams. I've never failed an exam. Never.
I am what you would call gifted. My teachers even said I was gifted.
Were you a good student in high school?
Yes, a rather good student.
In primary school, I was a good student.
I've been a good student sometimes and a bad student sometimes too.
Robert passed all his exams. He never failed. He never missed an exam.
Observe Mireille and Catherine here.
Catherine passed her Italian exam, but Mireille failed it.
It's stuck.
Oh, I got it. I passed.
Formidable.
Oh darn, I'm stuck.
Robert is very strong.
A very good student.
Very intelligent.
He's talented.
He is even gifted.
Very, very, very, very, very strong.
What does he do? Does he work?
Ah yes, he's an artist.
He plays the guitar.
He is very talented and highly regarded.
Robert never failed an exam.
None. Not a single test.
The boy hadn't read a single book by Hemingway.
He hasn't read any of Hemingway's books.
Have you read many of Hemingway's books?
No, miss, none.
No books.
Now, observe Mrs. Bello.
She doesn't know where Marie-Laure's book is.
She has no idea.
Hey, do you know where my Asterix is?
No idea.
A book, no book. An idea, no idea.
Robert taught himself to read. Well, almost.
I learned to read almost entirely on my own.
No kidding. And to write as well?
Mireille doesn't believe him. She makes fun of him.
No kidding.
No kidding. Mireille is surprised.
You know, my sister speaks Italian, Russian, Japanese, Swedish.
No kidding.
No kidding. Robert is making fun of Marie-Laure. Mireille is making fun of Robert. She doesn't believe what he says.
No kidding. And to write too. You taught yourself to write?
Yes. And I've always been one of the best students in my class.
And you also received the prize for modesty.
Sometimes, in schools, prizes, usually books, are given to the best students.
A prize for French, a prize for mathematics, a prize for history.
Robert may have won many awards, but he certainly didn't win the award for modesty.
Because he's not very modest.
Modest, not modest.
Mireille makes fun of Robert because he is not very modest.
And you also received the prize for modesty.
There you go again, making fun of me.
Me? Not at all. Never in my life.
Mireille protests.
Oh no, I'm not making fun of you. Not at all. No, no, no, no, no. Never in my life.
Observe.
Can I borrow it?
Never in my life.
Hey, what are you doing? You're hiding a card.
Me? No, never in my life.
Okay, now consider this.
The boy is talking about Hemingway. Mireille asks.
Did you know him? Did you read him?
Did you know him? Did you read him? I didn't know him.
Now, let's see what you've learned. Let's take stock.
Listen, think, speak.
Imagine Robert spilling his leather jacket on your skirt.
He's sorry, he apologizes. What do you say?
What did you say?
It's not a big deal, it's nothing.
Now the boy rushes to clean the skirt
What are you saying?
Don't bother
The boy tells you that Hemingway used to come every day to drink a kir at the table where you are sitting.
What are you saying?
You say
Impossible, is that true?
Or you say
No kidding
You are asked if you knew Napoleon
What are you saying?
You say no
But I've heard about it.
Robert says you're making fun of him.
What is your answer?
You answer...
Me? Not at all. Never in my life.
Okay, let's see where we stand.
Let's take stock.
Yes, that's it. What a great idea.
Let's take stock. I love taking stock.
I like to know where I stand.
Oh, and we're not going to do any review at all.
Never in my life. No, but seriously.
I have other things to do.
And besides, I've had enough. Come on, come on, let's stop it.
No, but to take stock?
Take stock? Me, I'm going to take a nap, yes.
...
Subtitles ST' 501