Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Good morning ladies, good morning young ladies, good morning gentlemen.
"I am the teacher. We are going to learn French."
Do you agree? Does everyone understand?
Yes, indeed. You are the teacher, we are the students, and we are going to learn French.
Oh, but you speak French. Are you French?
Non.
But do you know French?
A little bit.
Oh, okay. Well then, listen carefully.
We are going to learn French.
All right ?
And to learn French
We are going to invent a story
A story?
Yes, a story
A story like the story of Babar
Like the story of Asterix
A story like the story of Peter and the Wolf
A story like the story of the fox and the wolf
A story like the story of Little Red Riding Hood.
We're going to invent a story. Why?
We are going to invent a story to learn French.
We are going to invent a story because it will be useful for learning French.
Will this be useful?
Yes, of course, it will be useful.
To learn French?
Yes indeed! Inventing a story will be useful for learning French.
Okay, then it's settled. We're going to invent a story.
Yes, but who will invent the story? You or us?
What will invent history? Why, we will! You and I.
I'm going to propose the story.
Well, what about us then?
Well, you're going to invent the story with me. We're going to invent the story together. You and I together. Okay?
All right.
All right ?
Okay. So, we're going to invent a story. A story.
The story of an elephant?
Non.
The story of a man and a woman?
The story of Ansel and Gretel?
The story of Paul and Virginie?
Non.
Listen, this is going to be the story of two young people.
The story of two young people?
Yes, the story of two young people.
The story of a young man and a young woman, okay?
Why not ?
Okay, very good. It's going to be the story of a young man and a young woman.
What will the young man be? Will the young man be Italian?
Good morning, how are you?
No, not Italian.
No? The young man isn't going to be Italian? What will he be then? Will he be Spanish?
Hi how are things ?
Non.
So, what will it be? Will it be English?
Why not ?
No, he's not going to be English.
So, what will it be? Will it be Japanese?
Konnichiwa, hajimemashite.
No, he's not going to be Japanese.
So, what will it be? Will it be Norwegian?
Good dog, you big dog.
No, he's not going to be Norwegian.
So, what is it going to be?
American?
If you wish.
Okay, very good.
The young man is going to be American.
And what will become of the young girl?
Is she going to be American?
Non.
Is she going to be Norwegian?
Is she going to be Japanese?
Is she going to be English?
Will she be French?
Yes, that's it. The girl is going to be French.
To learn French, a young French girl will be useful, okay?
The young girl is going to be French.
Why is the girl going to be French?
Because it will be useful for learning French.
To learn French, we are going to invent a story.
It's going to be the story of two young people.
A young man and a young woman.
The girl will be French and the young man will be American.
The two young people are going to make friends.
They are going to have a lot of friends.
We will choose friends for the two young people.
We are going to invent adventures, journeys.
We're going to discuss all of this together, you and I.
It's going to be a game, it's going to be fun.
But let's hope, let's hope it's going to be fun.
Yes, it's going to be fun, of course.
It's going to be fun and useful.
To learn French.
That's it. It's going to be fun and it's going to be useful for learning French.
Ladies, young ladies, gentlemen, listen up.
We are going to learn French.
Ladies.
Gentlemen.
Sir, ladies, madam, ladies, madam, ladies, madam, miss, miss,
Ladies
Mademoiselles
Sir
Gentlemen
Ladies
Listen
Look, he's listening
He listens.
Hello, how can I listen?
She listens.
Listen, Elsa.
Listen carefully, Patricia.
Okay, well, you listen too.
Listen, okay? You're going to listen.
So, I'm calm and I'm listening to you.
Listen.
I am the teacher. I am going to speak. Blah blah blah. I am going to speak French. I am going to speak because I am the teacher.
And you, you're going to listen because you're the students. The professor is going to speak and the students are going to listen. The students are listening, okay?
Oh no. The students will speak and the professor will listen.
Yes, of course. The students will also speak.
Okay. But now I'm going to speak and you're going to listen.
Go ahead, listen.
To learn French, we are going to invent a story.
A story like the story of Babar or the story of Winnie the Pooh.
Look at this little girl. What is she going to do?
I'm going to tell you a story. So, you see, this is...
A story. We are going to invent a story.
We're going to invent. It's going to be an invention.
Look at this prehistoric man. He's going to invent the wheel.
The Chinese invented gunpowder.
Edison invented the electric light bulb.
What are you going to invent next?
Marie-Laure also invents things.
Here's a phone, try it.
I see.
In the thread.
Hello ?
We are going to invent a story.
The story of two young people.
It's going to be the story of two young people.
A young girl and a young man.
A young man, a young man, a young girl, a young girl.
What is that? A young man or a young woman?
A young girl, yes. And what is this?
A young girl? No, she's not a young girl, she's a lady.
And that's a lady? No, that's not a lady, that's a priest.
That's a young girl. And what's that? A young girl?
No, not really, no.
That's a little girl.
That's a young man.
And this?
No, that's not a young man, that's a gentleman.
Yes, that's a young man.
And that's a young man?
No, not really, he's a little boy.
What is this?
A young girl, yes.
And this?
Those are young girls.
Young girls.
A young girl, young girls.
What is this?
A young man, yes.
And this?
Those are young people.
For the story, we're going to choose a young girl and...
and a young man.
We will choose.
A choice must be made.
She chooses some fruit.
He chooses a card.
We will choose the nationality of the young people.
Will the girl be American?
Italian?
Or will she be English?
Or will she be Japanese?
Or will she be French?
Will the young man be American?
Why not ?
Italy?
Norwegian?
Why not ?
Or will it be English?
Or will it be Japanese?
Why not ?
Or will he be French?
We can choose an American girl
or a young Italian, Norwegian, English, Japanese girl
or a young French girl.
We can also choose a young American man
or a young Italian man,
Norwegian, Japanese
or a young French man.
Look at this young man.
He is American.
And this young girl, she's American.
He is Italian, she is Italian.
He is American, she is American.
He is English, she is English.
He is French, she is French.
We will also choose some friends.
The young people in the story will have friends.
Friends.
Here are some friends, friends, friends, friends.
My friend Antoine Dutilleul.
Ousmane, a friend.
A friend.
Annick, a friend.
A male friend.
A female friend.
The young people will make friends.
Sophie, Philippe, friends.
A friend, friends. They're going to have friends, lots of friends. Friends, many friends. A student, students, many students. Balloons, lots of balloons.
One boat, many boats.
Money, lots of money.
The young people in the story will have many friends.
Italian friends?
Yes, why not?
If you wish.
Look at Marie-Laure, she's going to say why not.
That's enough, you're not going to eat them all.
And why not?
Because you're going to get sick.
Look at this gentleman, you'll see.
He's going to say, "Why not?"
Excuse me, sir, do you want to learn Japanese?
Non.
Ah.
And you, sir, do you want to learn Japanese?
Why not ?
Do you want to make a movie with me?
Ah yes, why not?
Why not ?
Do you want to come?
We are going to invent journeys.
Train journeys, car journeys, plane journeys, helicopter journeys, there you have it, people going on journeys.
We're going to invent trips, adventures, all kinds of adventures.
Romantic adventures
Yes, yes, but who's going to invent all this?
You, her, him, her, them, us
You and I, we
Me, you, us
We, you, him, them, her, she, we will invent the story together.
I will present the story and you will discuss it.
You are going to have a discussion.
Yes, no, okay, no, no, I don't agree, yes, no.
It's united.
So, there you have it, we're going to talk.
Look, they're talking.
"You seem to be saying it's up to us to do the work. I know what you're thinking, go on. Oh well, say it, I'll tell you."
"Just a small change. A small change, but you got the money?"
They discuss. I'm going to propose the story, and you're going to discuss the story with me. We're going to discuss, we're going to invent together.
Look, she and he are together. They are together.
Are you together? Yes. Yes, they are together. Are you together? No. They are not together. They are traveling together.
Are you happy that we're traveling together? Yes. We're going to invent the story together. Okay? Do you agree? Look, they agree.
"Okay. Okay, that's settled."
Do they agree? Oh no, they don't agree. They don't agree. And they, do they agree? Yes, they're together and they agree.
And here? Here, they are together, but they disagree.
We're going to invent the story together. Okay?
It's going to be fun. It's going to be a game. A game.
Belote and Rebelote.
A game like belote, for example. Belote is a card game.
Look at Marie-Laure and Mireille here. They're playing a game.
I've got you, you've got me by the chin. The first one to laugh will get a slap.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's playing a game. She's playing hopscotch. Hopscotch is a game.
Look at Mireille and Marie-Laure. They're playing a game. It's a fun game.
The puppet show is fun too.
That's a funny story. It's a Belgian story.
He's funny too.
And is Marie-Laure's game there any fun?
Does that amuse you?
Yes, it's fun.
We are going to invent a story, journeys, adventures.
We'll discuss all of this together.
It's going to be a game.
It's going to be fun.
Let's hope so.
Yes, let's hope it's going to be fun.
He hopes it will be fun.
We must hope.
We must always have hope.
Look, see Marie-Laure here.
I hope they're chocolates.
They're chocolates.
She hopes. She hopes it will be chocolates.
I hope these are chocolates.
Damn! These aren't chocolates.
Mireille hopes so too.
She hopes that Marie-Laure will give her chocolates.
I hope you'll give me some.
I don't know. We'll have to see.
Look here. Aunt Georgette is not well.
Mireille hopes she will get better.
I'm not doing well.
I'm tired.
I hope things will get better.
Are you going to be able to get up?
Well, I hope so.
We're trying it slowly.
Now you are going to speak French.
Listen to this dialogue between Mireille and her friend Jean-Michel.
You will repeat Jean-Michel's answers.
So, we're going to invent a story.
Shall we invent a story?
Yes, and I'm going to propose the story.
And what about us?
Well, you're going to invent the story with me.
We're going to invent adventures, journeys.
This is going to be fun, isn't it?
Let's hope so. Let's hope it's going to be fun.
Now it's your turn. You are Jean-Michel.
So, we're going to invent a story.
We are going to invent a story.
Yes, and I'm going to propose the story.
And what about us?
You will invent the story with me.
We're going to invent adventures, journeys.
This is going to be fun, isn't it?
Let's hope so. Let's hope it's going to be fun.
We are going to invent a story.
It's going to be fun and it's going to be useful.
This will be useful for learning French.
Funny, ha ha ha ha ha, and useful.
A pencil, a pencil, it's useful for writing.
Glasses, glasses, they're useful for reading.
A key, a key, it's useful for opening things.
A tie, a tie, no, a tie, it's nice, but it's not useful.
A handkerchief, yes. A handkerchief, a handkerchief. It's useful. And cigarettes. Cigarettes are useful. Cigarettes, no. Cigarettes aren't useful. Let's see if you've understood. A pencil, yes, it's useful. Cigarettes, no, they aren't useful.
Leeks? Yes, they're useful. Flowers? No, they're not useful. Observe. We're going to learn French. We're going to invent a story. You're going to discuss the story. Observe.
Hello, and where are you going? You see, I'm going to walk Fido.
Now, observe this
Hello, what are you doing?
You see, I'm walking Fido
Compared
You see, I'm going to walk Fido
You see, I'm walking Fido
Now, look at this young man.
He's going to call
He's going to eat
This is the immediate future
Now he eats
This is the present.
Now, look at Marie-Laure eating too much chocolate.
That's enough, you're not going to eat them all.
And why not?
Because you're going to get sick.
She's going to be sick.
This is the immediate future.
Now, look here.
What is it?
I'm sick.
Now she is sick.
This is the present.
Look at Ousmane.
He's going to work.
And now, he works. He is going to work, he is going to study; this is the immediate future. Now, he works, he studies; this is the present. He eats; present. He is going to eat; immediate future. He is going to study, he is going to discuss, he is going to speak, he is going to listen; immediate future.
Let's see if you've understood. I'm the professor, you're the students.
What are we going to do? We are going to learn French, and to learn the
French, what are we going to do? We're going to invent a story. Here we go.
I invented a story together. I'll suggest the story and you...
You're going to discuss the story; it's going to be the story of two young people, one
A young man and a young woman, of course, it's going to be fun and useful, useful for
Finally learning French, let's hope, let's hope it will be useful and fun, let's hope, let's hope, let's hope
Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
THANKS.