Subtitles ST' 501
and absorb it.
Very soon, you will see what happens
and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Beyond their third apartment, Robert and Mireille discuss education.
Robert argues that learning at school is useless.
Mireille is distancing herself from education and culture.
No one seems to notice that a man in black
took an interest in their conversation.
It is 11:45 on the observatory clock
Robert and Mireille are still on the terrace of Elila's garden.
They are drinking their third kirsch
So you think we teach a lot of useless things?
But what, for example?
Well, I don't know.
Almost everything.
Take mathematics, for example.
Geometry, trigonometry, integral calculus, differential calculus.
What's the point of all this?
Once you know how to do addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division, that's all you need.
And besides, now, with small electronic calculators and computers,
There's no point in even learning to count anymore.
Yes, but still, computers need to be programmed.
It's the same for chemistry.
All these formulas, what's the point, I ask you?
This might be good if you want to be a distiller or a pharmacist.
Or to refine heroin
But apart from that
It can also be used if you want to make explosives.
Unfortunately, I've always had bad grades in chemistry.
I've always hated chemistry
All these acids, it's smoking, it smells bad
Chemistry is the devil's cooking
And all the laws of physics are the same thing.
What good is it to know the law of falling bodies when you fall from a balcony?
It should be noted that when he was 10 years old, Robert fell from a balcony in New Orleans and spent three weeks in the hospital.
And Latin? You studied Latin, didn't you?
Yes, six years. From sixth grade to first grade.
Well then, do you speak Latin?
No, not really.
No, of course not. You studied Latin for six years, but you don't speak Latin.
Besides, even if you spoke Latin, who can you speak Latin with?
I ask you. Even at the Latin home, right in the Latin Quarter, they don't speak Latin.
Ave Janitor.
Okay, yes, nobody speaks Latin anymore. Even priests say Mass in French now. But people learn Latin for other reasons.
Oh really? And why is that, tell me?
Well, to learn French better and also for intellectual discipline.
Intellectual discipline? Intellectual discipline? You make me laugh with your intellectual discipline.
If you want my opinion, doing crosswords in Geobridge is more useful than a mental exercise.
But still, there is some beautiful Latin literature.
Oh dear, literature is fiction, lies, nothing but things that don't exist.
Does all this mythology actually exist?
Have you ever seen mermaids and centaurs?
And then, what has ever spoken towards, as in your classical tragedies?
La la la, la la la, la la la, la la la.
Come on, that's ridiculous.
It's artificial; there's nothing more artificial than a classical tragedy.
Even novels are not life, they are fiction.
So why don't you like history?
At least this is about real people, people who have lived.
people who influenced events.
Ah! If you believe that history tells you the truth, you are mistaken.
History has conspired to make you adopt the prejudices of your nation.
Your country is always right and others are always wrong.
But then, modern languages, at least that's useful, right?
Not the way they are taught, with all those conjugations, declensions, and vocabulary lists.
That's ridiculous, it's pointless.
We learn grammar rules for four years and we are not able to say two understandable sentences.
Well, I'm exaggerating. I had some very good German teachers.
But I don't know how to ask what time the train arrives.
It's true that you're exaggerating. You're funny, but you're exaggerating.
Besides, everyone has always been against the education they received.
Fortunately, culture is what remains when everything else is forgotten.
Oh, are you judgmental when you get going?
May I invite you to lunch?
Is it because I'm judgmental that you want to invite me to lunch?
No, it's because I'm hungry, because it's almost noon.
Because I believe you must be hungry, and so am I.
that the conversation interests me and that you want to continue it.
That's a lot of good reasons, but I can't accept it.
I go home for lunch every day.
It's a shame.
What time is it? Do you have the time?
It is five minutes to noon.
Oh dear, I'm going to be late.
Excuse me, I'm off.
Oh no, no, no, don't bother, see you soon. Goodbye.
Okay, now Mireille has just left
She has just left the Lilac Glossary
But in the beginning, where are Mireille and Robert?
They are still on the terrace of the glossary
They've been there for a long time, a long time.
They had time to drink two kirs.
And now they're drinking their third kir.
They are drinking their third kia.
Look at Marie-Laure over there. What is she doing?
She is learning her lesson.
And what is Mr. Bello doing here?
He is reading the newspaper.
And what do the Bellos do now?
They are eating.
Robert and Mireille are on the terrace of the Closerie des Lilas.
They are drinking their third kia.
And Robert is criticizing the teaching.
So, you think we teach a lot of useless things?
What for example?
Well, I don't know. Almost everything.
He criticizes everything. Well, almost everything.
Look at Marie-Laure. Has she finished her homework?
Not quite. Almost.
Have you finished your homework?
Almost.
That's it, I'm finished.
And here, she ate almost all the chocolates.
Did you eat all the chocolates?
No, not all
Yes, well, almost all of them
Robert criticizes mathematics
He says it's pointless
Geometry, trigonometry, integral calculus
Differential calculus, what's the point of all that?
It's pointless, it's not useful.
A pencil, yes. A pencil, now that's useful.
A pencil is for writing.
A corkscrew is useful.
It's used to uncork bottles.
A knife is useful.
It's used for cutting.
A watch is useful.
It's used to tell the time.
Glasses are useful.
Because it's used for reading.
But a tie is not useful.
It's pointless.
And mathematics is like a tie.
Finally, Robert says it's pointless.
But not everyone agrees.
I find mathematics very useful.
What do you think about math?
Is it useful?
Very useful.
Do you think math is useful?
Yes, I think so.
Of course, you need to know how to do addition.
Do you know how to do addition?
Yes, I do. I know how to do addition.
Here, look.
28 plus 14, for example, 8 and 4, 12, I write down 2 and carry over 1, 2 and 1, 3 and 1, 4, 42.
You also need to know how to do subtraction.
32 minus 16
6 subtracted from 12
That makes 6
and I retain 1
1 and 1, 2 subtracted from 3
There's 1 left, that makes 16
You also need to know how to do it.
a multiplication
43 multiplied by 12 for example
That makes 2 times 3.6
6, 2 times 4
1 times 3, 3
1 times 4, 4
4, 6, 8 and 3, 11, 4 and 1, 5.
You also need to know how to do division.
436 divided by 8, let's see, that makes 43, how many times 8?
5 times 8, 40.
5 times 8, 40, subtracted from 43, remainder 3.
It's 6, 36, in 36, how many times? 8, 4 times, 8 times 4, 32, top of 36, remainder 4.
That makes 54 and there are 4 left.
Me, my friend, I can do everything.
You need to know how to do addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division.
But that's all. That's all that's needed. That's enough.
And besides, now, with small electronic calculators and computers, there's no need to even learn to count anymore.
Besides, now, with small calculators and computers, there's no need to learn to count anymore.
It's not worth it. It's pointless. There's no need to learn to count. It's not worth it.
Thanks anyway.
There's no need to thank me.
According to Robert, chemistry is also useless.
What's the point of all these formulas? I ask you.
This might be good if you want to be a distiller or a pharmacist.
or to refine heroin.
But apart from that...
This might be useful if you want to be a distiller.
if we want to distill alcohol or perfumes,
or if we want to refine heroin.
Heroin is a drug like cocaine, hashish, opium, all that stuff.
Chemistry might be useful if we want to refine oil.
Or if we want to make explosives, Molotov cocktails, dynamite, atomic bombs, all that.
Chemistry is used for all sorts of things.
What is it for?
It is used to make pharmaceutical products, dyes, and many everyday objects.
Is it fun to watch?
Chemistry is used to manufacture plastics.
Here, they manufacture train cars.
At Citroën, they manufacture cars
And that's Mireille, the one who makes explosives.
Unfortunately, I've always had bad grades in chemistry.
I've always hated chemistry
Mireille doesn't like chemistry
She hates that
Listen Elsa, if there was anything, you know you'd be the first person I'd tell.
That's not right, is it? I hate breaking up. That's clever.
Mireille has always hated chemistry because it smells bad.
All these acids, they're smoking, they smell bad. Chemistry is the devil's cooking.
She hates chemistry because there are always fuming acids. It fumes, it smells bad.
That smells good. Perfumes smell good.
Fabric softener smells nice too.
And besides, at our house, everyone loves the smell of vanilla fabric softener.
Mustard has a strong smell.
It's the verb "to feel".
Listen, it smells funny.
That smells funny.
Is it you who smells like that?
"All these acids, they're smoking, they smell bad. Chemistry is the devil's cooking."
According to Robert, physics is also useless.
"What good is knowing the law of falling bodies if you fall from a balcony?"
In physics, we learn the law of falling bodies.
But if you fall from a balcony, knowing the law of falling bodies is useless.
When he was ten years old, Robert was with his parents in New Orleans and he fell from a balcony.
He stayed in the hospital for three weeks.
Look, he too fell from a balcony. He took a tumble.
That too is a fall. It's a waterfall. It's falling water.
In high school, we study Latin.
But, according to Robert, there's no point in studying Latin.
Because we study it for years, but we don't know it well enough to talk about it.
But we learn Latin for other reasons.
Oh really? And why is that, tell me?
Well, to learn French better.
Latin is useful for learning to speak French better, for example.
In the past, people spoke Latin.
But now it's over. We don't speak Latin anymore.
Even Latin men are not spoken to in Latin.
If you say hello to the receptionist in Latin, he won't understand you.
And yet, the Latin home is in the Latin Quarter, right in the heart of the Latin Quarter.
Here is Paris, here is the Latin Quarter, and here is the Latin Home right in the middle of the Latin Quarter, right in the heart of the Latin Quarter, right in the middle.
Spot on.
And look at the ball there, right in the glass, right in
The Latin home is right in the Latin Quarter
And yet, Latin is not spoken at the Latin home
In the past, parish priests, Catholic priests, said Mass in Latin
Our Father
But now they say Mass in French.
Today, we no longer learn Latin in order to speak Latin, no
But we learn Latin for intellectual discipline, because it is a good mental exercise.
It makes you work your head, it makes you use your brain.
Gymnastics is a physical exercise.
Learning Latin is a mental exercise.
Here is a gentleman who does a lot of physical exercise, but not much mental exercise.
You make me laugh with your intellectual discipline.
You make me laugh.
Look at Madame Hello.
She reads Asterix and it makes her laugh.
And here, Uncle Guillaume is jumping rope and it makes Marie-Laure laugh.
Whereas there is somewhere a surefire way to find a guy who would be delighted if you cooked him two fried eggs.
Ah, you're laughing.
Yes, that makes her laugh.
That makes them laugh.
Okay, now you're going to imitate Robert in his conversation with Mireille.
Listen carefully to what Robert says.
Okay, yes, nobody speaks Latin anymore.
Even priests say mass in French now.
But we learn Latin for other reasons.
Oh really? And why is that, tell me?
Well, to learn French better and also for intellectual discipline.
You make me laugh with your intellectual discipline.
Now, it's your turn.
Okay, yes, nobody speaks Latin anymore. Even priests say Mass in French now. But people learn Latin for other reasons.
Oh really? And why, tell me? Oh really? And why, tell me? Oh really? And why, tell me?
Well, to learn French better, and also for intellectual discipline.
You make me laugh with your intellectual discipline. You make me laugh with your intellectual discipline.
You make me laugh with your intellectual discipline.
According to Robert, doing crossword puzzles is more useful as a mental exercise than learning Latin.
Robert likes doing crossword puzzles.
In his opinion, it's a very good mental exercise.
That's his opinion. That's Robert's opinion. That's his view.
In his opinion, in my opinion, in your opinion.
Robert is very kind.
In my opinion, you should marry her.
I'm not asking for your opinion. Mind your own business.
Which do you think, this one or that one?
In my opinion, that one.
So, Manon, you don't like it?
Non.
Ah, well, I am indeed his friend.
Robert criticizes Latin literature.
In his opinion, it's all lies.
It's fiction.
Mythology, sirens, centaurs, they don't exist
These are lies, it's not true.
Mom, Marie-La ate all the cookies again
That's not true, that's a lie, it wasn't me
You're still eating chocolates.
No, I didn't eat chocolate, I worked.
Oh yes, is that a true lie?
Marie-Laure says she was working, but that's a lie, it's not true.
According to Robert, classical tragedies are ridiculous because everyone speaks in verse.
Tragedies are in verse.
Here are some verses, and here is some prose.
Literature, classical tragedies, novels, it's artificial, it's fiction.
So why don't you like history?
At least this is about real people, people who lived, people who influenced events.
The story is about real people.
Joan of Arc, Louis XIV, Napoleon, these are real people, people who lived.
Now they are dead, but they lived, from the verb "to live".
It's the past tense of "vivre" (to live).
They lived, they lived.
Pantagruel is not a real person, he is fictional.
He didn't really live
But Louis XIV is a real person, a historical figure
He actually lived
He had an influence on historical events.
If you believe that history tells you the truth, you are mistaken.
History has conspired to make you adopt the prejudices of your nation
History does not tell the truth
History has been manipulated, rewritten. History distorts the truth.
The truth, the truth, what is the truth?
There are several truths. There is a French truth, there is a German truth, an American truth, a Russian truth.
Finally, we can say that truth is the opposite of a lie.
"Lies, truth." But everyone sees truth differently. Do you know how the French represent truth? They represent truth as a naked young woman emerging from a well, holding a mirror. That's truth at the Palais de Justice in Paris.
Robert criticizes history, but he also criticizes modern languages ​​because they are taught poorly.
We teach conjugations, we teach declensions, we teach grammar rules,
but the students are not able to say two understandable sentences.
Robert is unable to ask what time the train arrives.
And you? Do you know how to ask what time the train arrives in French?
What time does the train arrive?
Very well, you know how to ask what time the train arrives
Robert is against everything, nothing pleases him
And you, are you against education or are you for it?
Do you enjoy studying?
Work: are you against it or for it?
And what about art and artists? Are you for or against them?
"Oh, you're an artist. I forgot."
"What do you have against artists? We need them."
Robert, on the other hand, is against everything.
He criticizes everything.
He puts on a little show to impress Mireille.
Robert exaggerates in his criticism of the education he received.
"Besides, everyone has always been against the education they received."
The education he received, received, is the verb to receive.
We receive an education, we receive a package.
Look, Mireille here, she's receiving a package.
We receive gifts, we receive letters.
Now listen to Mireille, she's going to be a bit pompous, a bit sententious.
Fortunately, culture is what remains when everything else is forgotten.
"Oh, are you judgmental when you put your foot down?"
Generally, Mireille is not judgmental.
She speaks normally, simply.
But when she gets going, when she starts to be sententious,
Then, she can be very judgmental.
Robert invites Mireille to lunch because he is hungry.
He is hungry.
Marie-Laure is hungry.
She eats because she is hungry.
But here, she is not hungry.
Well, eat.
I'm not hungry.
She's not hungry.
Here's another person who isn't hungry.
Aren't you hungry?
You really don't want a croissant?
I'm not hungry.
I'm hungry, I'm not hungry, that's the expression "to be hungry".
Robert has many good reasons to invite Mireille to lunch.
But she cannot accept because her parents are expecting her for lunch at noon.
It's already five to twelve, she's going to be late.
Then she gets up and leaves.
Oh dear, I'm going to be late.
Excuse me, I need to film.
Notice, Robert invited Mireille.
Robert invited her.
And now he's invited Mireille and Colette. He's invited Mireille and Colette, he's invited them. Interesting, isn't it? Okay, now watch, think, and talk.
What do we do at Citroën?
Are we refining oil or manufacturing cars?
We manufacture cars.
Look at this.
Does it smell good?
No, it smells bad.
It stinks.
Look, what happened to this man?
He fell from a balcony.
Is the Latin home far from the Latin Quarter?
No, it's right in the Latin Quarter.
Look at Robert here. What is he doing?
He does crossword puzzles.
In your opinion, is doing crossword puzzles a good form of physical exercise?
No, but it's a good mental exercise.
Are Joan of Arc and Napoleon fictional characters or real people?
These are people who have lived.
Do you know how to ask in French what time the train arrives?
What do you say if you want to know what time the train arrives?
You say...
What time does the train arrive?
That's it.
There you go. Look at Marie-Laure here. Is she hungry or does she have a toothache? She's hungry. Now, look. Why does the teacher always wear a tie? What's the point? I ask you.
Why is it pointless? Why do you always have a stick? What's it for?
It's useful, but it's very helpful, Mr. Robert.
No, but yes, why is there no point in arguing with these people?
I'm off, goodbye, see you soon.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada