Subtitles ST' 501
You have to look and fly away.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few words in French yourself.
It is night, and Mireille has let Robert return home for lunch.
After several unnecessary waits, Robert finally managed to send a phone call to Madame Courtois.
She's a big talker, and Robert isn't allowed to enter Edgewise.
But he has a lunch invitation.
It is noon in Paris.
Noon, who said that?
Where is the little mouse?
What does she do with the lace at the chapel?
For whom? For the ladies of Paris.
Marie-Laure, is that you? Go wash your hands.
Hurry up, you're late.
It is 12:05 PM. Robert is alone on the terrace of the Closerie des Lilas.
Mireille has left. She went home to have lunch with Dad, Mom and her little sister.
It is 6:05 AM in New York and 6:05 PM in Mumbai.
Robert set his watch to French time. He just finished his third kir.
He calls the boy.
Can I make a phone call?
Yes sir, in the basement, next to the toilets.
No, it's not for the toilet. It's for making a phone call.
Yes, sir. The phone booths are downstairs, in the basement.
Next to the toilets, at the back of the room on the right. Thank you.
Robert gets up.
He enters the room.
He goes down to the basement to make a phone call.
He is followed by a strange character dressed all in black.
Robert enters the booth. He tries to put a coin in the slot of the machine, without success.
He leaves the booth, goes back up into the room, and goes to the cashier.
Robert goes back down to the basement, enters the cabin, and this time it works again.
Hello, Mrs. Courtois?
No, the lady is not here.
The lady has gone out.
She went to take Minouche.
She didn't come back.
She'll be back in a little while for lunch.
Call back around noon, half past noon.
Ah good ?
Thank you, thank you very much.
I won't be able to see in half an hour.
Goodbye, madam.
Oh, madame,
What is she going to say to the lady?
Robert goes back into the room.
Always followed by the strange man in black
Robert returns to his table
How much is it?
30 and 30, 60 and 15, 75
75 francs
Is the service included?
Yes sir, 15%
Robert walks along Boulevard Montparnasse.
He is looking for a phone booth.
Ah, here's one.
But he doesn't seem to understand how it works.
Come on, Robert, a ticket?
Well, definitely not.
You need a card, a magnetic card.
Try the other one, it works with coins.
Do you have any change?
That's all I have.
Oh no, that won't do.
Is this for Paris?
Yes.
You need 50 centime, 1 franc or 5 franc coins.
You don't have any change?
No way.
Wait, let me see if I have any.
Here.
Thank you, goodbye.
MFP subtitles.
My dear little one. What a coincidence, we were just talking about you yesterday with my
Husband. How long have you been here? Since yesterday, no, I arrived the day before yesterday.
And how are you? Did you have a good trip? Not too tiring, no?
With the jet lag? My husband, who travels a lot, says that's the hardest part, the jet lag.
Schedule. I don't travel, I stay home. What do you want with Minou?
I can't travel. So your mother didn't come, she didn't accompany you.
Is she still in Argentina?
Salette gave us great pleasure.
Ah, we are looking forward to seeing you.
And I'm sure Minouche will be delighted to meet you.
Minouche is my cat.
She's a bit like our daughter, you know.
So, when are you coming to see us?
Unfortunately, that's not possible today.
Minouche is not doing very well.
No, I don't know what's wrong with her.
And I need to take him to the doctor this afternoon.
And besides, my husband is away. He's traveling.
He's never home, always traveling
Business, you know what that is?
I repeat it to him every day
You should be careful, you're tiring yourself out too much.
This is going to end badly, you're going to give me a heart attack.
He's not listening to me, he's laughing
Ah, men, they're all the same.
So when? Let's see when.
The day after tomorrow?
That's it, just come and have dinner with it the day after tomorrow, that's all.
We will be so happy to see you
So, is that settled?
The day after tomorrow, say 7:30 am, is that okay with you?
Do you have the address? It's next to the Nikko, the Japanese hotel. You'll find it. So we'll be waiting for you. Goodbye. And the day after tomorrow. Don't forget, especially.
It is 12:45. Robert is hungry. He spots a cafe-restaurant and sits down at an empty table.
The waitress serves a young man next to her.
And there you have it, a country ham and a glass of Beaujolais.
There you go. And good sir, what will it be?
Um... a country ham and a glass of Beaujolais, please.
Very good, Robert.
Then Robert continued his walk
It is 1:30 AM
Robert returns to the Luxembourg Gardens
So, where is that English homework?
Well, I don't have any English homework.
I am in primary school.
I don't do English.
Well, not really.
I'm doing English, but it's not serious.
I'm learning...
But then, why did I come here?
Mystery and bubblegum.
Would you like one?
Was the garden nice? What did you drink?
I drink Orangina.
You know, young people don't drink alcohol anymore.
Did you see that gentleman over there?
Well, how strange.
Do you know him?
No, but earlier, at the farmhouse, I went to make a phone call and he came down behind me.
He went into the next booth and stayed there while I was on the phone.
He left when I left and he got in behind me.
That's really weird.
Strange, strange.
Initially, Marie-Laure played in Luxembourg.
It is noon.
She sings a nursery rhyme.
Noon, noon, who said that?
Where is the pizzeria?
It's a nursery rhyme. Look, this too, that's a nursery rhyme.
Am, gram, tram, piqué, piqué, collé, gram.
Burré, bourré, rattam, astram, dam.
Astram, gram, piqué, piqué, collé, gram.
Drunk, drunk, ratatam, astram, gram.
You start.
Noon, who said that?
Where is the pizzeria?
What does she do with the lace at the chapel?
For whom? For the ladies of Paris.
Noon, it's lunchtime.
The Bélots have lunch at noon.
Robert is having lunch in a cafe.
At noon, it's lunchtime.
And in the morning, it's breakfast time.
Here, Robert is having breakfast at the hotel.
Marie-Laure has her breakfast around 7:30 in the morning.
And in the evening, it's dinner time.
The children eat dinner around 7 or 8 o'clock in the evening.
Even the courteous ones, they dine around 8 pm.
It is 12:05 PM.
Marie-Laure goes home for lunch.
She is late.
Hurry up, you're late.
Manuel, we're going to be late.
We're leaving in 5 minutes, quick.
Now go on, because you're going to be late for school.
Ah, you're late, aren't you?
We said two o'clock and it's two quarter past two.
She's hurrying because she's going to be late.
This lady is hurrying.
People are hurrying.
It's the verb "se dépêcher" (to hurry).
Okay then, are you going to hurry up?
I'm in a hurry.
Oh, there we go, there we go, I'm coming.
Hurry up.
Go wash your hands.
Hurry up, you're late.
Meanwhile, Robert set his watch to French time, because it was still on New York time.
There is a time difference between Paris and New York.
Do you know how many hours apart there are between Paris and New York?
Six hours less or more?
In New York, it is six hours earlier than in Paris.
This jet lag, when you travel, is very hard, it's tiring.
The scenes, the arguments too, it's hard, it's unpleasant.
Another scene last night.
Were you harsh?
When you travel, the hardest part is the jet lag.
My husband, who travels a lot, says that the hardest thing is the jet lag.
Robert set his watch to French time and he wants to telephone the courteous one.
Can I make a phone call?
If you want to make a phone call, you can make it from home, of course.
You can make a phone call from a phone booth.
You can make a phone call from a cafe.
In cafes, the telephone is almost always next to the toilets.
And the toilets are still at the end of the corridor.
The toilets are at the end of the corridor.
In cafes, the toilets and telephone are almost always in the basement, downstairs.
Down, up.
The phone is downstairs, in the basement.
Okay, now you're going to talk a little bit.
You will play the role of the boy
Listen
Can I make a phone call?
Yes sir, the phone booths are downstairs in the basement next to the toilets
Now you are going to try to answer Robert
Can I make a phone call?
Yes sir, the phone booths are downstairs in the basement next to the toilets
Yes sir, the phone booths are downstairs, in the basement, next to the toilets.
There, you see Robert going down to the basement to make a phone call, since he's in a café.
You can also make a phone call from a public phone booth, in the subway, or on the street.
There are booths that operate with coins.
Ah, not banknotes, no, no, no, we need coins.
That's money, coins.
You should always carry some cash with you.
Look, Robert wants to buy a croque-monsieur.
but he only has a large 500 franc note.
He has no change.
A croque-monsieur, please.
It's not a big deal, it's not a big deal.
There you go, 9 francs.
9 francs, there you go, a croque-monsieur.
Oh dear, you don't have any change?
No, I don't have any money at all.
Patrick, hey, do you have any change?
Yes, definitely.
This lady is giving change for 20 francs.
If it's 4.10, it's 10.20.
Oh, here we go, it's starting.
Cash.
As if I had nothing better to do, giving everyone their change.
Observe Robert, who wants to pay, how much does it cost?
30 and 30, 60 and 15, 75, 75, service is included, yes sir, 15% in general in cafes and
In restaurants, service is included in the bill; at the end of the bill, you add...
15% for the waiter's service charge; in hotels, service is generally included.
included in the room price. How much is the room? 250 francs. Breakfast is
Included? Yes, service and breakfast included. Robert gives the waiters a 100-franc note.
And the boy gives him his change. 15 francs, a 10-franc coin and a 5-franc coin. Okay,
Let's get back to phone booths. Some work with coins, and others...
Others that work with a magnetic card also allow you to make phone calls from an office.
A post office (post, telegraph, telephone) in France is the PTT administration which
He takes care of the phone; if you want to talk to someone, you can call them on the phone.
Who can call their father? Robert wants to speak to Madame Courtois, so he calls her.
When Robert calls Mrs. Courtois, it's the maid who answers.
Ms. Courtois is not here, she has left.
If the person you are calling is not there,
Well, it needs to be remembered.
Call back around noon, half past noon.
If you can't hear well, it's best to hang up and call back.
Hello? Hello? I can't hear you very well.
Listen, I'm hanging up and I'll call you back.
Robert calls back.
Wait, I'll put it on for you.
Don't hang up, I'll put it through to you.
Wait, don't hang up, the doorbell's ringing.
No, no, I'm not leaving.
They're going to put me through to the service.
Hello, yes?
Mireille ?
Ah, don't hang up.
I'll pass it on to you.
Please come by, Mom.
Can you put my little brother on the phone, please?
The good pass, Mrs. Courtois, to Robert.
Ms. Courtois exclaims.
Ah, Robert! How are you, my dear little one?
What a coincidence! My husband and I were just talking about you yesterday.
Mrs. Courtois and her husband were talking about Robert.
Observe. What is this book about?
What are you reading?
A book.
What is this about?
Well, it's about an elephant.
Ha ha ha! What a coincidence! My husband and I were just talking about you yesterday.
Coincidence, coincidence, she makes me laugh with her coincidence.
It's no coincidence that he was talking about Robert.
This is not a coincidence at all, since he has just received a letter from Robert's mother.
Is she still in Argentina?
You remember that Robert's mother lives in Argentina.
Yes, you were very pleased with his letter.
What else brings pleasure?
The gifts.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She has just received a beautiful gift, a beautiful boat.
That pleases him.
What still gives him pleasure?
Ah, chocolates.
It's the expression "to please".
Listen.
That's kind.
Dad told me that.
That makes me happy.
Robert's arrival pleases Madame Courtois and her husband; they hope to see
Robert, soon they are eager to see him, they are impatient, here is an impatient man
Look, Marie-Laure here, she's impatient! Ah, we're impatient to...
I'm sure Minouche will be delighted to meet you.
This is our cat Minouche, she will be delighted to meet Robert.
She will be very happy, I am delighted to see you. Look at Mireille here, she is delighted.
Madame Courtois' cat doesn't know Robert; she'll be delighted to meet him. Look!
Mrs. Bello here too, she is delighted to meet Robert.
I am delighted to meet you, Ms. Courtois, and I am eager to...
I know Robert, but not today because Minouche is sick, and then there's Monsieur.
Courtois is absent, and then my husband is absent. Mr. Courtois is absent; he is not here.
He's not in Paris, he's traveling. He travels a lot. He's traveling, he travels too much. Dirty
Tired, Madame Courtois keeps telling him to be careful, she says, "Be careful."
"Be careful," she repeats to him every day, "it's the..."
The verb to repeat: I repeat it every day, you should pay attention
Be careful, it's going to end badly, but he's not paying attention.
Marie-Laure doesn't pay attention either.
And it ends badly.
Be careful
But you can't be careful, can you?
This too will end badly.
Stop
Warning, this is going to end badly.
This too will end badly.
Do you see?
It ended badly
This too will end badly.
You see, it ends badly.
That too ends badly.
This will end badly. You'll give me a heart attack.
A heart attack, a stroke, a cardiac infarction.
There you have it, Mr. Courtois is having a heart attack.
He doesn't listen to her. He laughs.
He laughs. Look at Marie-Laure here.
She laughs. And here, she cries.
She laughs, he laughs too, they're all the same, men, don't even talk to me about them, they're all the same.
Women, don't talk to me about it, they're all the same, nor about a dinner the day after tomorrow, just you
Do you have the address? It's next to Nico's, the Japanese hotel, 59 Quai de Grenelle. That's the address.
Listen, can I ask for your address? The 7th arrondissement, the Courtois, they live in the 15th arrondissement.
on the banks of the Seine near the Eiffel Tower, opposite the Maison de la Radio and the statue
In the Liberty district, a rather modern neighborhood, Madame Courtois invites Robert to dinner the day after tomorrow.
The day after tomorrow? That's it! I don't have an audit or the day after tomorrow, quite simply.
We'll be so happy to see you. So, is that settled?
Okay, it's a deal.
So, it's afternoon at 2 o'clock.
Robert is going to have lunch on a terrace.
He orders a plate of country ham and a glass of Beaujolais.
Beaujolais is a red wine from a region near Burgundy.
Then Robert goes on a date with Marie-Laure; she gives him a ball of gum.
Do you want some? Then he sees the man in black. Marie-Laure asks Robert if he knows him. Do you know him?
No, but earlier at the farmhouse I went to make a phone call and he came down behind me.
He went to make a phone call, he went downstairs, he came in, he stayed, he went out, he went upstairs
Notice that all these verbs are conjugated with the auxiliary verb "être bon" (to be good). Now listen.
Look, think, and speak. Look at Mireille here; she takes her time, or she hurries.
She's hurrying, why is she hurrying? She's hurrying because she... because she's going
Being late, that's money or a bill, that's a bill, and that's money or a
A ticket is money, look at Marie-Laure, the chocolates, she hates them or it makes her
Pleasure, it pleases him, look at these people, they are traveling or at home, they are in
On a trip. Look at Marie-Laure. Is she laughing or crying? She's laughing. And here? She
He cries. What is this? Breakfast or lunch? It's breakfast.
Lunch. And is that breakfast or lunch? It's lunch. And
What time is it? Noon, who said so, the little mouse? The little mouse, the little
Mouse? Is there a mouse here? Where is it?
At the chapel.
At the chapel? Oh, okay.
No way! She's here!
Oulah! Oulah! Oulah! Oulah!
...
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada