Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on
and be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Robert has been invited to dinner at the Courtois
and he tries to convince Mireille to get herself invited too.
Mireille doesn't commit herself
and Robert spends the next 48 hours wondering if she'll be there.
He then becomes hopelessly lost trying to get to the Courtois apartment.
The Luxembourg Garden
Robert and Marie-Laure are sitting on a bench.
But what are you two doing here?
We're talking.
What's wrong with you? You look strange.
Do we look strange?
Strange, strange.
I called the courteous one earlier.
Oh yes ?
First, I came across a lady with a strange accent.
Which I didn't quite understand.
Ah, it must have been Conception, their maid.
She's Portuguese. She's a gem.
She's an excellent cook.
She's a remarkably good cook.
My queen too, by the way.
I called again a little later.
There, I met Mrs. Courtois.
I also had trouble understanding it.
However, she doesn't have a Portuguese accent, as far as I know.
No, but oh my, does she speak fast?
And how talkative she is!
Ah, that's true, she talks a lot.
But when her husband is there, he's the one who talks.
She said nothing.
So when he's not there, she takes advantage of it.
I couldn't get a word in edgewise.
Finally, it appears that Mr. Courtois is absent.
He is traveling.
Minouche is not doing well at all.
She has a migraine or something like that.
She needs to take him to the vet.
So they can't see me until the day after tomorrow.
But she invited me to dinner the day after tomorrow.
That's kind.
He's an excellent person.
She has a heart of gold, and so does he, for that matter.
He's a bon vivant.
Always happy, always optimistic, he never worries.
He always repeats, don't worry, everything will be alright.
Don't worry, there won't be a problem.
It won't be a problem.
You'll see, everything will work out, there's no need to worry.
For her, it's quite the opposite.
She is always a little tense, worried.
She keeps saying, this will all end badly.
No, Grandma, you'll see, it'll all work out.
She has a passion for cats. They never had children.
He's a gourmet. He travels a lot for business.
He knows all the great restaurants in France.
And since Conception is an excellent cook, and Madame Courtois too, you eat very well at their house.
Do you enjoy good food?
Oh yes!
Well then, since Madame Courtois is your godmother, you can't avoid being asked to dinner the day after tomorrow?
I don't know. I don't know if I will be free.
Ultimately, it doesn't depend entirely on me.
I'll see.
Oh dear, excuse me, I'm off.
I'm going to be late. Goodbye.
Where is she going?
It's a mystery.
Would you like one?
Thursday, May 31st.
Robert is walking around Paris.
He walks through the flower market.
He walks past the concierge's house, along the banks of the Seine, he looks at the animals
And all the while, he is nervous, tense, worried.
He wonders if Mireille will be at the Courtois' house the next day
Will she be at the Courtois'?
He enters the Louvre Museum
He sees a painting by a painter named Robert
How strange!
His name is Hubert Robert
Strange, strange
He passes by the victory of his motrasse
Dad, why doesn't she have a head?
It's the victory of his motrasse
He stops in front of the Venus de Milo.
Dad, why doesn't she have arms?
This is the Venus de Milo.
He goes to see the Mona Lisa, but he can only think about Mireille.
Will she be at the Courtois'?
I don't know.
In the evening, Robert takes a walk in Paris.
He's thinking about Mireille.
He wonders if she will be with the Courtois.
She will be there. She will not be there.
Robert slept badly.
He wonders if Mireille will be at the Courtois'.
He opens his window.
The weather is magnificent
She will be there
He shaves and cuts himself
She will not be there
It is 9 o'clock in the morning
Dinner at the Courtois' is at 7:30 in the evening.
Robert is going for a walk to pass the time
He goes around the island of Saint-Louis
He passes in front of the town hall.
He explores the Forum des Halles.
He visits Beaubourg, the Pompidou Centre.
And they wonder if Mireille will be at the Courtois' house tonight.
Three hours.
Robert returns to his hotel and changes his clothes.
and will take the subway to go to the Courtois' house.
He looks a little lost.
He gets off the subway.
He sees the Arc de Triomphe.
That's not it.
He takes the subway again.
Look at his plan.
Seems increasingly lost.
He gets off the subway.
Oh dear, poor Robert, that doesn't seem to be it.
Miss, please, the Totem Tower.
I don't know. You're in the defense area here. It's not this way, I don't think.
THANKS.
Excuse me, the Quai de Grenelle, please. The Totem Tower is this way.
The Quai de Grenelle, but that's in the 15th arrondissement. Here, you are in Montmartre.
you have to take the subway
Oh no, I don't have time.
THANKS
and Robert sets off on foot
he walks across all of Paris
Montmartre
the Sacré-Coeur, the Moulin Rouge
the Opera
Place Vendôme
La Madeleine, la rue royale, la place de la Concorde.
He arrives at the Eiffel Tower at this hour.
He catches sight of the Statue of Liberty.
Finally, here is the Quai de Grenelle.
Subtitles ST' 501
Let's go!
It's ringing.
Excuse me, sir.
Madame Courtois, is this the right place?
Ah, no, sir. No, Madame Courtois, it's not here.
No, you've come to the wrong door.
Madame Courtois is next door. The door next door.
Excuse me, sir. I'm sorry to have bothered you.
Excuse me.
It's not a problem, sir. There's no harm done.
Goodbye, sir.
It's 7:30. Phew!
Madame Courtois invited Robert because he called her.
He tried to call her several times.
The first time, he didn't get Madame Courtois.
It was not Mrs. Courtois who answered.
He had someone else.
He found the right one.
First, I came across a lady with a strange accent.
In New Orleans, you remember, Robert fell off a balcony.
Now he's found the right one.
Hello, Mrs. Courtois?
Oh no, that's the right one.
Here, Mireille runs into Hubert.
She is surprised to meet him at university.
Hi, Hubert!
What are you doing here? I didn't expect to run into you at the Sorbonne.
I go there sometimes.
Robert stumbled upon Conception, the maid of the courtly ones.
She's Portuguese. She's a gem. She's an excellent cook.
She's a remarkably good cook.
This maid is a gem. Gems. A gem.
The maid is a pearl. She is precious. She has many qualities.
First of all, she's an excellent cook.
A cook, a female cook.
That's a cook who cooks. She cooks well.
That's a man who cooks, but he's not very good at cooking.
Robert had difficulty understanding Madame Courtois.
He has trouble getting up.
She too has trouble getting up.
Oh, but what time is it?
Ten past twelve, miss.
Please come back in one hour.
And this gentleman is having trouble finding his way.
He has difficulty walking.
Jean-Claude is also having a hard time.
And he's having trouble starting his chainsaw.
When you have trouble sleeping, you can take pills.
Look, if she has trouble sleeping, you give her two in the evening.
Robert had difficulty understanding Madame Courtois.
However, she doesn't have a Portuguese accent.
Unfortunately, that's not possible today.
Minouche is not doing very well.
No, I don't know what's wrong with her.
And I need to take him to the doctor this afternoon.
However, she doesn't have a Portuguese accent, as far as I know.
As far as I know.
Listen to Marie-Laure here.
Is your sister married?
Mireille?
No, not that I know of.
Listen to Mr. Bello here.
Has Marie-Laure gone out?
No, not that I know of.
She must be in her room.
Not that I know of.
No, Mrs. Courtois does not have a foreign accent.
But Robert had trouble understanding her because she speaks quickly and a lot.
She is very talkative. She likes to talk. She likes to chat.
You like to chat too.
When Madame Courtois speaks, Robert cannot get a word in edgewise.
When you speak, we cannot get a word in edgewise.
I couldn't get a word in edgewise.
To place, a word. It's the verb to place.
Minouche is not well. She is sick. She has a migraine.
Minouche is not well at all. She has a migraine.
She has a migraine. She has a headache. He has a migraine too.
Are you okay? How's your head?
Oh, the head, a real bloodbath.
He has a migraine too. Look at Mr. Bello here. He has a migraine too.
Jean-Claude, the migraine, please.
Minouche is sick.
Mrs. Courtois needs to take him to the vet.
The veterinarian is the doctor for animals.
Mrs. Courtois loves cats very much.
She has a passion for cats.
She loves cats.
This gentleman also has a passion for cats.
Marie-Laure, on the other hand, has a passion for chocolates.
I have a passion for chocolates.
Ms. Courtois has a passion for cats
And she has a heart of gold.
That means she is very generous
She has a good heart
A heart, a heart, a heart, a hand
Heart on his sleeve
She has a heart of gold.
She is kind
Mr. Courtois also has a heart of gold.
But Mr. and Mrs. Courtois are very different
Mr. Courtois is a bon vivant
He's a bon vivant, like those people.
He likes to eat well, to drink well
He's always happy, he's an optimist
But don't worry
He's not worried, he's relaxed, at ease
Look at Marie-Laure here, she's relaxed too.
She's not worried about it
Well, you're not worried about it.
No, I'm not worried about it.
Why should I worry? Are you worried?
Yes, I have an exam tomorrow.
Don't worry, Henri will sort everything out.
Look at this gentleman, he's not worried.
And yet, he doesn't have a house.
He's worried about it, he's concerned
He's worried too, he's concerned
And he's right.
Jean-Claude, please don't worry about it.
Mrs. Courtois is worried
She is worried
This will all end badly.
My God, Julien, what's going on?
She too is worried. She's worried.
Mr. Courtois, however, is not worried.
Don't worry, there won't be a problem.
Don't worry.
Look, observe. Listen carefully.
Oh! I know you can't stay here!
But don't worry, I won't be long.
Ms. Courtois is still worried, tense.
Look, there's a tent. A pitched tent.
And there you have it, a relaxed tent.
And here's a relaxed bow. Here's a drawn bow. And here's a relaxed bow.
Well, Ms. Courtois is tense.
Here, Jean-Claude is worried, nervous, tense.
Mr. Courtois, on the other hand, is relaxed. He is not worried.
Don't worry, it'll all work out. It won't be a problem.
It won't make a fuss. Not a fuss.
That's it, it's a done deal.
Here, it's a no-brainer.
When it creases, it's not right.
Look at this lady.
She's not happy because it's creased.
That's not going well.
Here, it doesn't crease anymore.
She is happy.
How are you.
It's a done deal.
Mr. Courtois is optimistic.
He's not worried about it.
He thinks everything will be alright.
Everything can be fixed.
Look.
Marie-Laure has a small problem.
But Uncle Guillaume will sort that out.
There, it's sorted.
You'll see, everything will work out.
What else is there?
My ball fell into the lady's bag over there.
Well, go ask her.
I don't dare.
Wait, I'll fix that.
And there you go, it's sorted.
You see, everything works out in the end.
No, there's no problem anymore, everything's sorted out.
Mrs. Courtois invited Robert to dinner
Now, Robert suggests that Mireille get herself invited too.
Can't you get invited to dinner the day after tomorrow?
Mireille doesn't say no, but she doesn't say yes either.
It doesn't depend entirely on her
It depends first and foremost on Madame Courtois
And then it depends on his parents, on his job
It doesn't depend entirely on me.
We are always dependent on someone or something.
Take Marie-Laure, for example.
She is not free to go and play in Luxembourg as she pleases.
Do you come to play here every day?
It depends.
It depends on what?
It depends on the weather. If it's raining, I won't come.
It depends on the homework.
If I have any, you can't come.
Then it depends on mom. Sometimes she says no.
The next day, Robert goes for a walk in Paris.
He's thinking about Mireille. He's wondering if Mireille will be at the Courtois' house.
Will she be at the Courtois' tomorrow?
He wonders. He asks himself questions.
It's the verb "to wonder".
Here we have someone wondering how we got their phone number.
What I'm wondering is how he got my phone number.
Robert is wondering whether Mireille will be staying with the Courtois family.
So he goes to the Louvre Museum. He looks at the victory of his moth. A little boy wonders why it doesn't have a head.
Dad, why doesn't she have a head?
It's a victory for his motorcycle.
Robert, for his part, wonders if Mireille will be at the Courtois'.
Then he sees the Venus de Milo. The same little boy wonders why she doesn't have arms.
Dad, why doesn't she have arms?
This is the Venus de Milo.
It's obvious. Everyone knows that the Venus de Milo has no arms.
Are you familiar with the Venus de Milo?
Yes.
What is this ?
It is an ancient Greek statue.
What's special about her? Is she missing something?
He's missing his arms.
And what is missing from the victory at Samothrace?
The head.
You see, everyone knows about the Venus de Milo and the Winged Victory of Samothrace.
Then, Robert sees a very pretty painting by Boucher.
It reminds him of Mireille.
He wonders if she will be with the Courtois.
Then he sees Leonardo da Vinci's Mona Lisa.
He smiled at her and she smiled back.
It reminds him of Mireille.
And he wonders if she will be with the Courtois.
The following morning, Friday, June 1st, Robert slept poorly.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's asleep.
Look at Robert here. He's sleeping on a bench.
She sleeps. She sleeps. He sleeps.
Are you asleep now?
You can turn on the light, Jeanne, I'm not asleep.
He's sleeping. That's the verb "to sleep." Observe this little scene.
You will sleep there. You will be very comfortable. Good night.
Thank you. You too.
Good night.
Okay, sorry, I slept badly last night.
Robert slept poorly because he wondered if Mireille would be at the Courtois' house.
He gets up, opens the window, the weather is beautiful
The sky is blue, the birds are singing, there are flowers
Everything's fine, everything will be fine, Mireille will be at the Courtois'.
He cuts himself, everything goes wrong, Mireille won't be at the Courtois' house.
Robert is going to Beaubourg
He visits the Pompidou Centre
At three o'clock, he returns to his hotel.
He changes his clothes to go to the Courtois' house
He checks the Courtois' address
And he gets on the subway
He is mistaken, he is lost
He goes out to the star
He sees the triumphal arch
That's not it, he made a mistake.
He heads back into the subway
He goes out on defense
That's not it.
He made another mistake. He went back on the metro and got off at Montmartre.
He asks a young man for directions. Robert doesn't want to take the subway.
He is afraid of getting lost again and arriving late at the courtly house.
So he sets off on foot. He crosses all of Paris on foot.
Finally, he finds the Totem Tower.
He goes in, takes the elevator, rings the bell, and wonders if Mireille will be there.
Ah, but that's not Madame Courtois, he's gone to the wrong door
You've come to the wrong door, it's next door
Excuse me sir, I'm sorry to have bothered you.
It's alright sir, there's no harm done.
Goodbye, sir.
There's no harm in it.
Excuse me, excuse me, I hope I didn't hurt you.
No, there's no harm done.
Now it's your turn to speak.
Try to answer Robert
Excuse me sir, I'm sorry to have bothered you, excuse me
It's alright sir, there's no harm done.
Okay, now it's your turn, answer Robert.
Excuse me sir, I'm sorry to have bothered you, excuse me
It's alright sir, there's no harm done.
It's not a problem, sir. There's no harm done.
Okay, now listen, watch, think, and speak.
Let's see what you've learned.
Do you know what that is?
It's a gem.
And that's the good one, the good one of the courteous.
Look at Marie-Laure here. What is she doing?
Is she working or sleeping?
She is asleep.
Look at Mr. Courtois. Is he worried or is he relaxed?
He is relaxed.
And what about Mrs. Courtois?
This will all end badly.
Is she worried or is she relaxed?
She is worried.
Look at Rodin's Thinker, over there.
He looks worried, tense, nervous.
Do you know why?
He wonders if Mireille will be at the Courtois'.
And Robert, look at Robert.
Well, Mr. Robert, you seem quite nervous.
I am worried, Mr. Guignol.
What is it, Mr. Robert? What's wrong?
I wonder if Mireille will be at the Courtois'.
Yes, Mr. Robert, she will be there.
Ah, you'll see, everything will be fine, don't worry.
Subtitles ST' 501
the Florence J. Gould Foundation Incorporated, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs,
the Ministry of Culture and Communication, the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust, et le National Endowment for the Humanities.
For more information on this and other Annenberg Media programs,
Call 1-800-LEARNER and visit us at www.learner.org.
French subtitles?