Subtitles ST' 501
and absorb it.
Very soon, you will see what happens
and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
It's morning.
Robert woke up and ordered lunch
and began to explore Paris.
He visits an open-air market near his hotel,
then crosses paths with the same person at the right bank.
He goes to a restaurant
where he is distracted by a scene
between a crazy customer and a weightless waiter.
It is eight o'clock in the morning.
Robert wakes up.
It's Saturday, June 2nd.
Robert gets up.
He looks out the window.
He stretches.
He yawns, he takes a shower, he shaves, he cuts himself, he brushes his teeth, he brushes his hair, he cuts his nails and he orders his breakfast.
Hello, good morning, could I have some breakfast please?
Yes sir, tea, coffee or hot chocolate?
Oh no, no, excuse me, coffee. A latte, please.
Okay, sir, then a full latte, room 27.
Right away, sir, we'll bring it to you.
He finishes getting dressed, there's a knock.
Yes, right away.
Hello, sir. Enjoy your meal.
THANKS.
Robert is going to have lunch on the balcony.
He pours himself some coffee.
With milk.
Ah, where is the teaspoon? Ah, there it is.
There. A lump of sugar. He eats his croissant. Will he eat his bread too?
Well, it seems so. So, why not?
It looks good.
With butter and jam.
What? What is this? Mireille's jam?
Oh no, Mirabelle plum jam.
He takes his time. He's not in a hurry. He has nothing to do. He has leisure time. It's nice to have leisure time. He's going for a walk in Paris.
They pass by a bakery.
Ah, those croissants, those brioches, they look good.
But come on, Robert, you're not hungry, you just had lunch.
It's a series of errors, my dear.
A bastard.
Yes, it looks good, but come on Robert, you're not hungry, you just had lunch.
He continues his walk.
He passes by the Lutèce arenas
Then in front of the Paris Mosque
Saint-Louis Island
He walks, he walks, he begins to see
He buys a croque-monsieur
A croque-monsieur, please.
There you go, 9 francs.
Oh, yes, 500 francs.
You don't have any change?
No, I don't have any money at all.
Yes, absolutely.
Do you have 500 francs in change?
Yes, I think so.
50, 50-100, 200, 300, 400 and 500.
THANKS.
then he discovers the Place des Vosges
the old hotels of the Marais
the synagogue
and he eventually went into a small restaurant.
Is he still hungry?
Good morning, sir. Would you like an aperitif?
No, thank you.
Boy! Boy!
Go get me another glass.
This one is full of lipstick.
Boy! Boy!
Bring me a clean fork.
This one is full of egg yolk.
And change that plate, it's dirty.
But what on earth is this?
Do they no longer do the dishes in this house?
But that's incredible!
And look at this towel,
She is completely torn apart.
The tablecloth too.
You will bring me a calf's head.
I'm sorry, madam. There aren't any left.
What? There's no more calf's head.
And what does that gentleman eat?
This is not calf's head.
That was the last one. There aren't any more in the kitchen.
But we have a very good pig's foot.
I don't want pig's feet. I want calf's head.
I'm sorry, madam.
The rabbit with mustard sauce is very good.
The mustard, the mustard, it's making my nose ache.
Okay. You will bring me a lamb chop.
Yes, madam. A lamb chop.
A lamb chop, a mutton chop, it doesn't matter to me, it's all the same.
And just right. Good, madam.
Boy! Boy!
You will bring that chop back to the kitchen.
It's not cooked. I told you it was done.
Look at that.
It's completely raw inside.
That's incredible.
And then, you will bring me another knife.
This one doesn't cut.
Here is your cutlet, madam.
I hope that this time it will be cooked enough for you.
Your chop is cooked enough, but it's charred.
It's coal.
And bring me back those peas.
These are not fresh peas.
It's straight out of the can. It's canned.
That's all the cheese you have.
Your brie is too fresh.
Look at this. It looks like chalk.
Your brie is too fresh and your camembert is too ripe.
It stinks, it's an infection.
And then, bring me some fresh bread.
This one was fresh eight days ago.
Look. It's as hard as stone.
I'm not a hothead, but there are limits.
Today, we have four main scenes
Robert gets up, Robert has his breakfast
Robert is walking through a market
And Robert sees a somewhat eccentric lady in a restaurant.
Okay, first, Robert wakes up.
He wakes her up.
She wakes up.
Robert gets up.
He washes himself.
Attention.
He gets up.
He washes himself.
And he washes himself.
Look closely now.
Is he getting up or washing himself? He's getting up. And here? He's washing himself. Good. He's washing himself. He's taking a shower. He's taking a shower. A shower. He's shaving. He's shaving. While shaving, he cuts himself.
He cuts his nails
He knows how to cut off fingers
He brushes his teeth
Don't forget to brush your teeth.
He brushes his hair
She brushes her hair
He wakes up
He gets up
He washes himself
He shaves
He cuts himself
These are all reflexive verbs.
Now, observe this.
He cuts his nails.
He brushes his teeth.
He brushes his hair.
Note the definite article.
Now, Robert is having his breakfast.
He has a choice between tea.
Here, have your tea, Dad.
Oh, breakfast.
Chocolate.
Or coffee.
He chose coffee, coffee with milk
He eats a croissant
And then he eats a piece of bread
With butter
And jam
Mireille's jam, what is that?
Mireille ?
Oh no, it's Mirabelle, Mirabelle jam.
This is Robert's breakfast.
What do you usually have for breakfast?
Croissants, coffee.
Black coffee?
No, coffee with milk.
Coffee, lots of coffee, nothing but coffee.
Are you eating something?
That's very rare.
Right now, I would have a yogurt, a piece of fruit and a piece of bread.
Luxury is breakfast in bed.
Here, have your tea, Dad.
Oh, breakfast.
After breakfast, Robert goes for a walk on Rue Mouffetard.
a small street that is very lively at market time.
There are lots of fruits, grapes, apples, raspberries,
cherries, strawberries.
There are lots of vegetables, white beans, green beans,
Mushrooms
Mushrooms are also a vegetable.
Tomatoes
Potatoes
Because there are apples that are fruits
And potatoes, which are vegetables
There are also salads.
There are all kinds of meat.
Beef
Mutton or lamb meat
Chops
Veal
calf's head, calf's feet, pig's feet.
In France, we eat beef, veal,
mutton or lamb meat, pork meat,
and also chicken, rabbit, and lots of fish.
And cheeses, camembert, brie, goat cheese,
Roquefort and Cantal cheese. In the evening, Robert goes into a restaurant for dinner.
He notices a customer who's always complaining. Do you know her?
You recognize her, it's Aunt Georgette, but Robert doesn't know her.
He grumbles because his glass isn't clean; it's full of lipstick.
Boy! Boy!
Go get me another glass. This one is full of lipstick.
Do you remember the glasses?
A glass. There is lipstick on Aunt Georgette's glass.
Lipstick everywhere.
She grumbles because her fork isn't clean.
It is full of egg yolk.
Boy! Boy!
Bring me a clean fork.
This one is full of egg yolk.
Look, see Marie-Laure here.
Wow, you're beautiful.
You're covered in jam.
Oh dear, you can't go work anywhere else.
Look at this. The table is full of books.
Then Aunt Georgette grumbles because her plate is dirty.
And change that plate, it's dirty.
Pass me your plate, Aunt Georgette.
The glass is dirty, the fork is dirty, the plate is dirty, all the dishes are dirty.
Why are the dishes dirty?
They don't wash the dishes in this restaurant anymore?
But what on earth is this? Don't they do the dishes in this house anymore?
But that's incredible!
The dishes need to be washed.
Yes, you always have to wash the dishes.
Aunt Georgette is also grumbling because the tablecloth and her napkin are torn.
And look at this towel, it's all torn.
The tablecloth too, oh!
There is a tablecloth on the table.
And then there's also a towel to dry yourself with.
But the tablecloth and napkin are torn.
Here, look at this sheet of paper.
Now it is not torn, but now I am tearing it.
It is torn. That's the verb "to tear".
Torn apart. Torn apart in front of me. I want to see everything.
Tear it open now. Come on, yes. Come on, again, again, again. Come on, yes, yes, yes, again, again.
Just a tiny little piece, just a tiny, tiny, tiny piece. Again, again. Come on, again, again.
He tears up a magazine.
Then Aunt Georgette grumbles because she wants calf's head and there isn't any left.
She wants calf's head. Calf's head.
Calf's head?
Yes, calf's head is good.
But there aren't any left.
There aren't any left in the kitchen.
Aunt Georgette is starting to lose patience.
What? There's no more calf's head?
The boy offers a pig's foot.
Pig's feet are good.
Or perhaps rabbit.
Rabbit?
Yes, rabbit with mustard sauce.
Rabbit with a mustard sauce.
But Aunt Georgette doesn't want rabbit with mustard sauce.
She is losing patience
The mustard, the mustard, it's making my nose tingle.
She is not happy at all
It's going to explode
Look, Aunt Georgette here
He's really getting on his nerves.
Now look at Marie-Laure
He's going to get angry
Hey, give me back my gumballs!
What gumballs? I've never seen gumballs.
Come on, don't be silly, give me back my gumballs
Are there gumballs here?
Not possible
Come on, be serious
Now, look closely.
He's going to get angry
Ah, I'm getting really annoyed.
Give me back my gumballs
Do you hear? Give me back my gumballs!
Hey, what's wrong with you? Are you okay?
Give them back to me
Now it's your turn to speak.
You are Aunt Georgette
And you order calf's head
I'm sorry, madam, there aren't any left.
What? There's no more calf's head.
And what does that gentleman eat?
This is not calf's head.
That was the last one, madam. There aren't any more in the kitchen.
But we have a very good pig's foot.
I don't want pig's feet. I want calf's head.
I'm sorry, madam.
The rabbit with mustard sauce is very good.
The mustard, the mustard, it's making my nose ache, isn't it?
Now it's your turn.
I'm sorry, madam. There's no more calf's head.
What? There's no more calf's head?
No, madam, I'm sorry.
And what does that gentleman eat?
This is not calf's head.
Isn't that calf's head?
That was the last one. There aren't any more in the kitchen.
But we have a very good pig's foot.
I don't want pig's feet. I want calf's head.
I'm sorry, madam.
The rabbit with mustard sauce is very good.
The mustard, the mustard, it's making my nose tingle.
Aunt Georgette orders a mutton chop with points
She doesn't want a raw cutlet, of course.
She doesn't want a burnt chop either.
No, she wants a well-done chop
Not overcooked, but cooked through
Perfectly ripe, then.
Look at this chop
Is it ready?
No, it's charred.
It's coal
Coal
And then, Aunt Georgette grumbles
Because his knife doesn't cut
And then, you will bring me another knife
No, this one doesn't cut.
Aunt Georgette's knife doesn't cut.
But this one cuts well.
Then Aunt Georgette grumbles because the peas aren't fresh.
These are canned peas.
And then, bring me back those peas.
Those aren't fresh peas, they're canned.
It's straight out of the box.
There you go, fresh peas.
Those are canned peas.
A can of food.
And then, Aunt Georgette grumbles because the brie is too fresh and the camembert is too ripe.
Your brie is too fresh.
Look at this. It looks like chalk.
A good cheese should be slightly fresh.
When cheese is too fresh, it's not good.
It's hard. It's like chalk. Chalk. You know, chalk. Chalk is hard. It's hard. It's not good.
When cheese is overripe, it's not good either. It smells bad. It stinks.
Look. This Camembert is overripe. It's too old. It smells bad. It's overripe.
The Camembert is overripe and the bread isn't fresh.
It is as hard as stone
And then, bring me some fresh bread
This one was fresh eight days ago
Look, it's as hard as stone
It is hard, hard as stone
Stone is hard
Don Georgette is not a complainer, no, no, no
Normally, she doesn't complain
But now, now, she's forced to grumble.
There are too many reasons
When there are only one or two things wrong
Well, it's not a big deal.
But there are too many things that are wrong here.
That's too much, that's too much
This is beyond the limits
Look, see Marie-Laure here
She too is grumbling because she thinks she has too much work.
This is beyond the limits
I'm fed up, I'm sick and tired of homework and lessons
Hey, I think I'll go for a drive to Luxembourg
Just to change my perspective
Marie-Laure, you don't work?
That's a good one!
The mustard was making him go to his knees.
I had to complete a French assignment and a math assignment.
A history lesson, a geography lesson
And I don't work, there are limits
That's too much, there are limits.
Okay, now listen, watch, think, and speak.
Look at Robert. Is he getting up or washing himself? He's getting up. And here? He's washing himself. What does he have for breakfast? Tea, hot chocolate, or coffee with milk? Coffee with milk.
What is he eating here? A croissant or a piece of bread?
A piece of bread.
Where did he stop here? In front of a vegetable vendor or a fishmonger?
In front of a vegetable vendor.
And here, did he stop in front of a vegetable vendor or a fishmonger?
In front of a fishmonger.
And this? Is that a butcher or a fishmonger? A fishmonger. And this? Is that a delicatessen owner or a cheesemonger? A cheesemonger.
Look at this glass
Is it full of lipstick or egg yolk?
It's covered in lipstick
Now, be careful, this is getting very difficult.
Look closely
Is it rabbit with mustard sauce or calf's head?
You have to guess
What are you betting on?
Calf's head?
Yes, you're right, it's calf's head.
And in your opinion, is this cutlet raw, medium, or charred?
It's ready.
And is this cheese too fresh or too ripe?
It's overdone.
And is this bread stale or fresh?
It is as hard as stone.
That's all for today.
Give me a chicken, Mireille.
There's no more chicken Mireille, Mr. Guignol, it's over.
So, a calf's head.
There's none left in the kitchen, it's over.
A pig's foot.
There aren't any left.
A lamb chop.
No, I'm telling you, it's over.
Rabbit with mustard sauce.
Non.
Ah, the mustard, it's making me angry.
Here, the mustard.
Calm down, it's over.
Subtitles ST' 501
...
Subtitling by Radio-Canada