Subtitles ST' 501
You have to look and fly away.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few words in French yourself.
In a nice restaurant, Robert sees a young couple at a table.
She is blonde and Robert thinks she might be Mireille, but he can't say for sure.
The chef named several kitchens after a former girlfriend of his.
Another Mireille, who suffered from indigestion.
Touching.
It's Sunday. Robert has nothing to do.
He is taking a walk.
There are people who go to church
my temple friends.
And everyone buys cakes from the pastry shops.
Robert stops in front of a pastry shop, admires the window display and decides to go in.
Hello Mrs.
Sir, what would you like?
What is this?
Cream-filled owls.
And this?
Coffee or chocolate éclairs?
Lemon tarts, sir.
Nuns, also with coffee or chocolate?
I'll have a nun.
Yes. With coffee, with chocolate?
At the café.
Is this for takeout?
No, it's to eat right away.
There you go, sir, that will be 10 francs.
Thank you. Goodbye, sir.
Robert continued his walk.
He enters a restaurant.
Hello Sir.
A place setting, please.
This way, please.
Please.
THANKS.
You are welcome.
Wine.
Thank you, sir.
Please, sir.
Robert consults the menu.
The martini is for the lady, and the Pernaut is for the gentleman.
When he looks up, he sees at a neighboring table
A young blonde woman having lunch with a young man
Robert wonders if it might be Mireille
Please bring us the wine list.
Yes, sir, right away
So, darling, what are you tempted by?
Well, I don't know.
Something light, I'm not very hungry
What is their daily special?
Toulouse cassoulet must be good.
Oh dear, no, that's too heavy.
What do you want to learn?
Sauerkraut with garnish tempts me, but I don't digest it very well.
Oh really? Dad says sauerkraut is very easy to digest.
Sauerkraut, perhaps, but goose fat, smoked bacon,
Sausages and ham are a different story.
No, but look at the ducks they have.
So, duck with olives, duck with orange,
Duck breast with cherries, duck breast.
without mentioning duck foie gras in the hors d'oeuvres.
Well, we really need to make a decision.
So, what are you having?
Well, I don't know.
I think I'll just have a small herb omelet.
I know you.
You're going to eat an omelet and in two hours you'll die of hunger.
That's how it was last year, when you were on your diet.
Hey, did you see? Mireille-style eggs.
Where?
There, in the hors d'oeuvres.
Have you made your choice?
What are Mireille's eggs?
These are stuffed hard-boiled eggs.
The egg yolks are mixed with a tuna and tomato puree
Topped with an anchovy fillet, a black olive, and capers
Oh, anchovies are too salty.
Oh, there's also a stir-fried chicken, Mireille!
And Mireille, apricots in the desserts.
Why do you have all these dishes called Mireille?
Ah, sir, that's quite a story.
A very sad story
Our boss had a girlfriend in his youth named Mireille.
and who died from indigestion caused by pink shrimp.
He is inconsolable and dedicates all his most brilliant culinary creations to her memory.
It's very touching.
And how is this chicken, Mireille?
Sautéed with eggplant and tomatoes.
The chicken pieces are sautéed in very hot oil,
Then garnish with slices of fried eggplant and sautéed tomatoes.
Well, I think I'll have a small grilled steak, a ribeye.
And for me, it will be a pepper steak.
And what about cooking methods for grilling?
For me, medium-rare, please.
And for me, blue
And where to begin?
For me, a plate of raw salmon
You don't have a snail?
Oh no, sir, I'm sorry
Damage
Well, I'll take a dozen oysters and you'll bring us a bottle of Muscadet and half a Moulin à Vent and half a bottle of Badoit mineral water.
THANKS.
The salmon is for the lady, and the oysters are good, thank you.
There you go, enjoy your meal.
No, come on, Robert, it's not Mireille.
In fact, she speaks through her nose as if she had a cold.
Enjoy your food.
THANKS.
Mireille doesn't talk like that.
Enjoy your food.
The ribeye steak, madam.
Pepper steak.
THANKS.
Is your ribeye steak okay? Is it cooked to your liking?
Yes, very good. And you? Is your steak blue?
Ah yes. For once, it's really blue.
You take some cheese.
What's wrong?
Camembert, Roquefort, Pont-l'Evêque, Cantal, Saint-André, Brie, Chavignol.
That's a goat too.
Okay then, I'll have some Brie.
And for the gentleman.
THANKS.
And for me, a little goat, please.
That one, yes.
Would you like a dessert?
Oh no, no dessert for me. I'm not hungry anymore.
Let's see what you have.
Bavarian cream, raspberry tart,
floating islands,
pear charlotte, chocolate mousse,
and the sorbets and the private sundae.
What is your private cut?
These are candied chestnuts with cognac.
vanilla ice cream
and fresh cream on top.
Okay, I'll take that.
And we have calories before that.
It's a good thing you weren't hungry.
For me, it will be a sorbet.
Pear, raspberry, passion fruit?
raspberry
and you will bring us two express
and the addition
You see, Robert, you can see that clearly.
that it's not Mireille
It's Sunday
On Sundays, Catholics go to church
and the Protestants go to the temple
And everyone goes to the pastry shop to buy cakes.
All kinds of cakes.
Come on, cream puffs are cakes.
Eclairs are cakes.
The nuns.
And then there are the pies.
Apricot tarts, cornflower tarts, apple tarts, lemon tarts.
There are lots of different cakes.
And do you like cakes?
Oh yes, I really like cakes.
Can you give some names of cakes that can be found in pastry shops?
mille-feuilles, religieuses, rum babas.
Here is a nun.
But it's also a cake.
Robert buys a nun's pastry because it's Sunday, no doubt.
Here, Mireille buys a newspaper.
You remember, I bought you this for your birthday.
Ah yes, yes, I remember.
Here, Robert buys a restaurant guide.
And here, Robert buys a croque-monsieur.
Look, here we're going to buy something to taste because the little boy is hungry.
It's the verb "to buy".
Yeah, it's 4:30.
Why does he keep repeating that it's 4:30?
He says that because he's hungry and we haven't had a taste yet.
What if we bought something?
Good idea!
You can give this to Eric for his birthday, so he can buy whatever he wants.
Robert enters a restaurant.
He notices a couple with a young blonde woman and he thinks of Mireille.
But it's not Mireille. In fact, it's Mireille's sister, Cécile, and her husband Jean-Denis.
They are having aperitifs. The lady has a martini and the gentleman a Pernod.
Then they look at the map. Let's see, what's there?
First, appetizers.
What kind of appetizers are there?
Cured meats, grey or pink shrimp, foie gras, duck foie gras, goose foie gras.
Oh, and then there are also Mireille eggs.
Are you familiar with Mireille eggs? No?
There you go, you take some eggs, one egg, some eggs.
But you use hard-boiled eggs.
You take the yolks, you take tuna, canned tuna.
There you go, tuna, fresh tuna, but you're using canned tuna.
So, you mix the tuna with the tomato puree.
You take the egg whites and stuff them with the tuna and egg yolk puree.
You take a can of anchovies, some black olives
You put a fillet of anchovy on the stuffed egg and there you go.
Does that sound good to you? That's fine.
Let's see, what else is there?
Perhaps there are snails?
Snails, there you go, a snail, snails
You don't have any snails?
Oh no sir, I'm sorry
There are no snails, but there are oysters.
There you go, oysters.
And then there's raw salmon
Salmon is a fish
After that, what's next?
Fish, poultry, meat
Ah, there's duck
All kinds of ducks
Duck with olives
Duck à l'orange
duck with prunes and peaches, duck aiguillettes, duck breast.
What else is there? Let's see.
There is cassoulet, Toulouse cassoulet, a specialty of the Toulouse region.
It's a dish of beans, white beans, with sausage and confit goose.
Is cassoulet light?
Actually, it's not very light, I don't like cassoulet.
What else is there? Ah, there's sauerkraut, garnished sauerkraut.
It's made with sauerkraut garnished with bacon, ham, hams, sausages, sausage.
That's fresh sausage.
And these are dried hams and sausages.
Do you remember those dried sausages?
Let's see, what else is there?
Hey, there's some chicken, Mireille.
Yes, yes, yes, Mireille's chicken.
Yes, it does exist, the Mireille chicken.
You don't know it? No?
You'll see.
You take chicken, chicken cut into pieces.
You take some oil and you stir-fry the pieces of chicken in very hot oil.
You take some eggplants, you cut the eggplants into slices
and you fry the eggplant slices in very hot oil.
Then you take some tomatoes and you sauté the tomatoes in very hot oil.
And there you have it.
Cécile doesn't want any chicken, Mireille.
She doesn't want sauerkraut, nor does she want cassoulet because it's too heavy.
It's not easy to digest.
It's heavy.
Look, it's heavy.
That's not heavy, it's light.
Light, heavy.
It's heavy.
Look, it's heavy.
Oh, you're so heavy.
Cécile doesn't want sauerkraut because it's heavy.
She wants something light
Like a small omelet
A small herb omelet
There you go, some herbs to flavor the omelet
Last year, Cécile was on a diet
She ate very little
She drank mineral water to stay thin
Monitor your diet
Finally, Cécile and Jean-Denis have some grilled food.
That's grilled fish, grilled red mullet, grilled sardines, a grilled sausage.
That's a barbecue, grilled meat.
Barbecues are very diet-friendly.
I think I'll have a small barbecue.
A ribeye steak.
A ribeye steak is beef.
And what about cooking methods for grilling?
You have the choice between medium, medium-rare or blue.
Right on the mark, please.
And for me, blue.
Is your steak blue?
Ah yes. For once, it's really blue.
For once, it's actually blue. That's exceptional.
Because generally, when you order a rare steak, it's always overcooked.
For once, as an exception, as an extraordinary event.
Generally, Mireille is right.
But for once, it's Mary-Laure.
And 8 x 8?
8 x 8, 64.
Non, 72.
Seventy-two.
No, how silly of me. Sixty-four. You're right.
For once, I'm right.
That doesn't happen often.
Now you are going to speak French.
You are at the restaurant, you are Cécile, you are going to order a grilled dish and to start, a plate of raw salmon.
Have you made your choice?
I think I'll have a small barbecue.
A ribeye steak.
I think I'll have a small grilled steak, a ribeye steak.
And how is it cooked?
Right on point, please. Right on point, please.
Right on the mark, please.
And where to begin?
The plate of raw salmon, the plate of raw salmon, the plate of raw salmon.
The boy brings the cheese platter.
There is camembert, cantal, saint-andré, brie.
All of this is about cows, cow's cheese.
There are also goats, goat cheeses, all sorts of goats,
Manure, from Valençay.
All of these are goat cheeses.
And then there's also Roquefort cheese.
That's sheep's cheese.
There you go, sheep.
After the cheese, dessert.
Would you like a dessert?
Oh no, no dessert for me, I'm not hungry anymore.
Let's see what you have.
There's a Bavarian cream, a raspberry tart,
Floating islands, pear charlotte, chocolate mousse, sorbets, raspberry sorbets, raspberries, pear sorbets, there you go, pears, a pear, passion fruit sorbets, there you go, passion fruit.
And then there's the privale coupe. Do you know the privale coupe? Look. You take chestnuts, candied chestnuts, you put them in a coupe, you take cognac, you pour it over the candied chestnuts, you take ice cream, vanilla ice cream, and you put the ice cream on top of the chestnuts.
Then you take some fresh cream, fresh cream, there you go, and you pour it over.
It's not bad, but it's not very light. It's full of calories.
Okay, I'll take that.
And so the calories start piling up. It's a good thing you weren't hungry.
And onward with the calories. Onward. Onward. Onward.
Thank goodness, thank goodness you weren't hungry.
Jean-Denis is making fun of Cécile.
She said she wasn't hungry, but she looks very hungry.
Donnie, look at Marie-Laure here.
She says she doesn't like chocolate mousse, but she eats it all.
So, is my chocolate mousse any good?
Yeah, but anyway, you know, I don't really like chocolate mousse that much.
Ah good?
Well, tell me, is that all that's left?
It's a good thing you don't really like chocolate mousse.
In this restaurant, there are Mireille eggs, Mireille chicken, etc.
And there's also a dessert called Mireille.
Mireille's apricots.
It's a dessert that is made with apricots.
There are eggs à la Mireille, sautéed chicken Mireille, apricots Mireille.
Jean-Denis wonders why.
So he asks the boy.
Why do you have all these dishes called Mireille?
Ah, sir, that's quite a story.
A very sad story.
It's not a cheerful story.
It's a sad story.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She is sad.
She is not sad here.
She is cheerful.
And Charlotte, here, she was sad.
Listen, Charlotte, we don't want to see you sad.
Look at Jean-Claude here.
He is cheerful.
But here, he is sad.
Well, the story of all these dishes
Her name is Mireille, it's a sad story.
The chef, the cook, had a girlfriend named Mireille.
And that girlfriend died.
She died from indigestion caused by pink shrimp.
She loved pink shrimp.
So she ate too many pink shrimp and she died.
The chief was very sad and he never got over it.
He remained inconsolable.
Look at Jean-Claude here, he is inconsolable.
And look at Marie-Laure, she's sad
But here, she is no longer sad, she is comforted.
She consoled herself.
But the chief himself never got over it.
He was always thinking about his dead girlfriend
And every time he invented a new dish, he called it Mireille.
To honor the memory of his deceased girlfriend
Isn't that sad?
That's very touching, isn't it?
It's very touching.
Okay, now, observe this.
Marie-Laure is carrying her boat.
She carries it, that's the verb to carry.
Now, observe.
She is going to bring her boat to her father.
Bring me your boat, I'll fix it for you.
It's the verb "to bring".
Now, look.
She's going to take her boat with her.
Take your boat with you, you're not going to leave it there.
It's the verb "to carry away".
Carry, bring, take away.
Look at Marie-Laure, she's wearing something.
Here, the boy brings a fork to Aunt Georgette.
Bring me a clean fork.
You will bring me another knife.
Here, the boy takes the glass.
Listen carefully to what the saleswoman says
Is this for takeout?
No, it's to eat right away.
Here, the boy brings the wine to Cécile and Jean-Denis
Here, he brings the cheese platter
Now, observe Robert
He takes the cheese
And now he's having some cheese
Cheese, cheese
Now, observe what Jean-Denis is going to say
I know you
You're going to eat an omelet and in two hours you'll die of hunger
Jean-Denis is making fun of Cécile a little.
I know you
Observe what Marie-Laure is going to say here
Here, pass me the box of candy
These candies are mine.
Go ahead and give it to me, I'll only take one, I promise.
Yeah, I know you
You say you'll only take one, and then you'll eat them all.
At the end of the meal, Jean-Denis asked for two espressos and the bill.
And you will bring us two express coffees and the bill.
Two express drinks, one express drink, and the bill.
And that's it, it's finished.
Oh no, we forgot to talk about the wines.
Oh dear, that's not good at all.
We need to talk about wines.
Okay, so Jean-Denis consulted the wine list
and he orders a bottle of Muscadet.
He also orders a half-bottle of Moulin à Vent.
A bottle, half a bottle.
He also orders a half-bottle of mineral water.
The French drink a lot of mineral water to eliminate waste.
I need to eliminate it!
Drink, eliminate, drink, eliminate, drink, eliminate!
Monitor your diet and trust Contrex.
Now listen, observe, think, and respond.
What do you buy in a pastry shop? Bread or cakes?
Cakes
Look closely, are those shrimp or foie gras?
These are shrimp
Be careful, this is quite difficult
Is it a duck or a goose?
A duck
Are these oysters or snails?
Oysters.
Is that heavy or is that light?
It's heavy.
What is she following?
A course or a diet?
A diet.
Is this an appetizer or a dessert?
A dessert.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
Is she sad or is she happy?
She's sad, look at Robert, what's he having, cheese or cheese, cheese and here
What does he take cheese for? What do we ask for at the end of the meal? And would he bring us two?
Express and the bill, what will you have, Mr. Guignol? Well, to start, shrimp.
Mireille's eggs, a dozen snails, a plate of raw salmon, and then a chicken.
A rare steak with fries, a soucroute, and a cassoulet—well done, Mr. Guignol!
It's good, it's good, it's good.
It's very good.
I can't take it anymore.
So, Mr. Guignol,
I'll give you a little cheese, a dessert.
No, no, no, nothing. I'm finished.
No cheese, no dessert, no coffee, no bill.
Applause
Subtitles ST' 501
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.