Subtitles ST' 501
We need to watch and get involved.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few words in French yourself.
Mireille goes for a walk and Robert invites himself along.
Robert is almost lost on the subway
on his way to meet Mireille at the station.
But they travel by train in time.
On the road, Mireille suggests
that they use familiarity, progress.
At 9:01 a.m. on Monday morning, the phone rang at the Bélots' house.
Mireille, who happens to be near the telephone, picks up the phone.
Hello ?
Hello? The Salvation Army?
Oh no, madam, it's not the Salvation Army.
You have the wrong number.
This is the fire station.
You have a wrong number.
Oh, did I dial the wrong number?
Yes, you have the wrong number, madam.
Oh, excuse me, miss, excuse me.
No harm done, madam, it's not serious.
Do you want the Salvation Army?
Yes, the Salvation Army.
Wait, I'll check the number. Don't hang up.
Hello, ma'am?
It's 43 87 41 19.
Ah, you are very kind, miss.
Thank you very much, miss.
You're welcome, it's nothing. You're very welcome.
It's the least we can do.
Goodbye, madam.
Mireille hangs up.
At 9:03, the phone rings again.
Mireille answers immediately.
Hello, this is the Salvation Army, Major Barbara speaking.
Hello ?
Could I speak to Miss Mireille Bello, please?
Is that you, Robert? How are you?
I'm fine, thank you. Are you too?
I... I'm calling you because the other night, Friday,
You told me to call you this morning.
Is...
I wanted to ask you when I could see you again.
Finally, if you wanted...
That's nice, but not today.
Yes, today I have to go to Chartres.
I thought you had gone to Chartres the other day
THURSDAY ?
No, I couldn't go on Thursday.
But I absolutely have to go today.
I should go to Chartres too.
The cathedral
Couldn't I go with you?
Oh, if you insist
But you know, I don't go to Chartres to see the cathedral
I'm going there to visit the museum and to speak to the curator.
Oh, well, that's not a problem.
I could visit the cathedral while you see this gentleman.
First of all, the curator is not a gentleman, it's a lady.
And I think you're fixing things too easily.
Oh, well, you know, if there were only difficulties like that, life would be easy, wouldn't it?
And how do you plan to get to Chartres? By car? By road?
No, I don't have a car.
I could rent one, if you wanted.
Oh no, it's too expensive.
And besides, with a rental car, I'd be too afraid of breaking down.
If you don't want to rent a car, let's take the coach.
That shouldn't be very expensive.
Oh no, the coach isn't expensive. But it's not convenient. It's not fast.
So, let's go by plane. That, at least, is fast.
No, come on. You can't fly to Chartres. It's too close. Chartres is too close to Paris.
Well then, if it's so close, let's walk. I enjoy walking.
But still, it's not far, but it's not that close either.
Well then, let's go by bicycle or on horseback.
On horseback would be nice. But I don't have the time.
So, if you're in a hurry, let's go by motorcycle.
I love motorcycles, don't you?
I don't know. It's a bit dangerous.
And besides, I don't have a helmet anyway.
And helmets are mandatory on motorcycles.
So, I suppose we can't go there by boat.
So, what's left?
The helicopter? The hovercraft?
There is indeed a hovercraft service between Boulogne and Dover,
but not between Paris and Chartres.
And there is no helicopter service either.
There are indeed the gendarmerie helicopters,
but they do not take passengers, except to transport them to the hospital.
So, are you going to go by train?
Of course, you guessed it.
The train, you know, is still the best option.
Great, I'll be able to take the TGV.
But no, come on, there is no TGV between Paris and Chartres.
The TGV is going too fast, it's too close.
With the TGV, we will have arrived before we have left.
TGV or not TGV, if you would be so kind, I would gladly go with you.
Okay, and of course.
Meet at 11am at Montparnasse station, suburban side.
How do we get to Montparnasse station?
It's easy, you just have to take the subway.
Do you believe that?
Yes, of course, why not.
The other day, I wanted to take the subway.
I got completely lost.
No kidding, that's impossible.
You can't get lost on the subway.
Me too.
Well, listen, it's not difficult.
You take the metro at the Odéon or Saint-Michel station.
You take the Porte de Clignancourt, Porte d'Orléans line,
direction Porte d'Orléans.
And be careful, you don't take the metro that goes to Porte de Clignancourt.
You take the one that comes from there and goes to the Porte d'Orléans.
And you get off at Montparnasse-Bienvenue.
It's simple, it's direct, there's no change.
You can't go wrong.
And you'll buy a booklet of tickets. It's cheaper.
A notebook, please.
THANKS.
On the subway, Robert, the man who gets lost everywhere.
Facing him were four gates and two corridors.
hundred kilometers of tunnels,
the world's largest underground network.
Once again, Robert will prove it
of its exceptional ease in getting lost.
Robert, the man who gets lost everywhere.
Finally, almost everywhere.
When Robert arrives at Montparnasse station,
Mireille is already here.
She waits for him while reading a newspaper.
Hello.
Excuse me, I'm a little late.
I almost got lost.
Where is the ticket window ?
La-bas.
I'm taking two first-class round trips, right?
No, just one ticket.
I've already bought my ticket.
And me, I travel in second class.
So, if you were planning, by any chance,
to travel in the same carriage as me,
You'd be better off buying a second-class ticket.
All right.
We have the second-year returns for Chartres, please.
Which way is it?
It's this way.
This way?
You need to validate your ticket.
...
Ah Versailles, the castle, the Grand Trianon, the gates, the Hall of Mirrors, the park, the flowerbeds designed by ours, the fountains, Mother Antoinette's hamlet.
I should go to Versailles one of these days.
It would be great if I could visit this with an art history specialist like yourself.
I wanted to tell you, we shouldn't see you like that.
Can we see you?
Yes, we see you, we call you.
You know, young people use the informal "tu" form very quickly.
I didn't want to use the informal "tu" with you in front of the courteous people the other day because they are a bit old-fashioned.
But I'm used to addressing all my friends informally.
So, can we use the informal "tu" form?
Oh, by the way, my parents would love to meet you.
They would like to have you over for dinner one of these evenings.
The Courtois have spoken to them a lot about you.
Would Thursday evening work for you?
We could perhaps go to the cinema afterwards, if you like.
Yes, if you want.
I think we could use the informal "tu" form.
Listen.
The phone rings and nobody rushes to answer.
It's the telephone. The telephone rings. It's the verb "to ring".
Here, Robert rings at the door of the courteous ones.
Listen.
I think someone rang the bell.
Is it the phone or the door?
This is the door.
Now, pay attention.
Wait, don't hang up, the doorbell's ringing.
So, is that the phone or the door?
This is the door.
Listen.
The doorbell rang, is it the phone or the door? It's the door. The phone is ringing. Mireille is there.
She happened to be near the phone; she wasn't expecting any calls, no, she was there by chance.
It's a coincidence, a chance occurrence. It's like Robert here; they're not looking for Mireille, no.
No, no, he's just passing by. Hey Robert, are you looking for me? No, I was just passing by.
By chance, and indeed, chance works things out well.
Hey, you wouldn't happen to have a light, would you? I don't know why I chose the bank.
Besides, I didn't really choose it; it was chance that chose it for me.
Life has always been more or less a matter of chance; the phone rings, who is it?
Robert, no, it's a lady who dialed the wrong number; she wanted the army of
Hi, but she did the bicycle number.
She dialed the wrong number
Oh, did I dial the wrong number?
Yes, you have the wrong number, madam.
Look at Robert here
He wants to ring the Courtois' doorbell, but he rings the wrong doorbell.
Excuse me, sir.
Madame Courtois, is this the right place?
Oh no, sir, no, Mrs. Courtois, this isn't it.
No, you've come to the wrong door.
And look at Joan of Arc here
She's fighting the wrong war
It's a lady who would like to see a gentleman named Tasson
I think she's in the wrong house
The lady dialed the wrong number
She wanted the Salvation Army
A Protestant charitable organization
Here's Mireille
As an officer in the Salvation Army
Mireille replies, just for fun.
That it is not the Salvation Army
But the fire station
Oh no madam, it's not the Salvation Army
You have the wrong number
This is the fire station.
Here's the fire station. A firefighter, several firefighters, very friendly. Mireille is looking for the Salvation Army number for the lady. The lady thanks her.
Oh, you're very kind, miss. Thank you very much, miss. You're welcome, it's nothing.
And taste it. Thank you, thank you Julienne for taking my turn. You're welcome, Dad.
The phone rings, Mireille answers it
Hello, this is the Salvation Army, Major Barbara speaking.
The device
Robert would like to go to Chartres with Mireille
I should go to Chartres too.
Ah, the cathedral
Couldn't I go with you?
Oh, if you insist
If you insist, if you absolutely want to come, you can
It's the expression "to hold"
Ah. There you go.
a young woman who doesn't want to
to stay. She doesn't want to
To stay. Sit down.
I don't want to stay.
Observe Marie-Laure here.
She insists on wearing her pink dress.
I want to wear my pink dress.
Can I? Okay.
If you insist.
Okay,
I'm going to play. Robert
can go to Chartres with Mireille
If he insists. But
And Mireille is not going to Chartres to see the cathedral.
She knows the cathedral.
No, she's going to Chartres to visit the museum.
a small museum located next to the cathedral,
and speak to the museum curator.
That's not going to stop Robert.
It's not serious.
Oh, well, that's not a problem.
I could visit the cathedral while you see this gentleman.
And I think you're fixing things too easily.
You know, if there were only difficulties like that,
Life would be easy, wouldn't it? If there were only difficulties like this, life would be easy, wouldn't it?
Life is easy, no, life isn't easy. In reality, life is complicated and difficult because...
that there are many problems, big problems, but if there were only problems like that
Minor problems. Life would be easy. Life would be easy, that's not reality.
That's what would happen if all these problems didn't exist. That's the conditional tense.
How does Mireille plan to get to Chartres? How does she intend to go there?
Let's see, how can we get to Chartres? We can get there by road.
There you go, a road. A road, yes. You can go to Chartres by road. By car. By car. By car.
But Mireille doesn't have a car. Robert doesn't have a car either. But he could rent one.
I could rent one, if you want.
Oh no, it's too expensive. And besides, with a rental car, I'd be too afraid of breaking down.
Mireille doesn't want a rental car because she's afraid of breaking down.
She would be afraid, that's the conditional of the expression to be afraid.
Look at Mireille here, she's going to be scared.
Idiot!
You were scared, weren't you?
Look at this young girl, she's scared.
Don't be afraid, miss.
Now look at this lady, she was scared while sleeping.
What's going on?
I was scared, Hervé.
With a rental car, Mireille would be afraid of breaking down.
Look. There's Mireille, who's broken down.
It broke down there too.
And here too, it broke down.
Are you experiencing a breakdown?
You can get to Chartres by coach or plane.
Or on foot. On foot.
Look at Robert and Mireille here. They are walking to Chartres.
You can also go to Chartres by bicycle.
Or by motorcycle.
But for motorcycling, you need a helmet.
When working on a construction site, a helmet is also mandatory.
When you're a firefighter, a helmet is mandatory too.
When you ride a motorcycle, you have to wear a helmet.
Asterix has a helmet, but Mireille doesn't.
So, she can't go to Chartres by motorcycle.
Is it possible to go to Chartres by boat?
No, it's not possible. You can't go there by boat.
So what? What's left?
The helicopter?
No, there is no helicopter service between Paris and Chartres.
There are indeed the gendarmerie helicopters.
The gendarmerie, which is responsible for traffic enforcement, has helicopters.
But the gendarmerie helicopters do not take passengers
Look at this small plane, it can take passengers
How many passengers can it carry?
Two or three probably
The pilot has two or three passengers
But this plane can take 200 or 300 passengers
"The gendarmerie's helicopters do not carry passengers, except to transport them to the hospital."
So, what's left? The hovercraft?
There you have it, a hovercraft.
There is indeed a hovercraft service between France and England, between Boulogne and Dover.
but there is no hovercraft service between Paris and Chartres.
But then, but then, what's left?
How will Mireille get to Chartres? By train?
Yes, of course, but you know, you guessed it. The train, you know, is still the best option.
What is the best way to get to Chartres?
It's about taking the train.
Yes, by train. I don't know if you can go by plane.
By hovercraft, certainly not, no.
The train, you know, is still the best option.
This is the best. It's excellent. You can't find better.
This is what we do best. You won't find better.
The train is the best option. It's fast, convenient, comfortable, and always on time.
Ah, that's very good. And then, you meet people on the train. You make acquaintances.
I like the train. You meet people.
There are extremely fast trains, like the TGV, the fastest train in the world.
Mireille arranges to meet Robert at Montparnasse station.
This is a large train station in Paris. A train station. A train station. There's a train station. There's the train station in Montreal, Canada.
This is Chartres station. Chartres station. Saint-Lazare station in Paris.
Montparnasse station has two sides. One side for suburban trains and one side for long-distance trains.
The suburbs of Paris are the area around Paris, near Paris.
Suburban trains don't go very far
And long-distance trains go far
Mireille arranges to meet Robert at Montparnasse station
But Robert doesn't know how to get to Montparnasse station
Robert is a bit dim-witted.
Because it's not difficult
There is no problem
All you have to do is take the subway
It's easy, you just have to take the subway
Yes, Robert, you can just take the subway. It's an easy solution. There's always an easy solution. Look.
I'm bored.
Well, you just have to read it.
Oh, I think I'm going to be sick.
You just have to stop.
I'm sleepy
As for me, you just have to go to bed.
How to get to Montparnasse station?
But it's very easy, you just have to take the subway
Now listen, then imitate Mireille
How do we get to Montparnasse station?
It's easy, you just have to take the subway
Okay, your turn now.
How do we get to Montparnasse station?
It's easy, you just have to take the subway
Well, that's easy, you just have to take the subway.
Mireille explains to Robert how to get to Montparnasse station by metro.
First, you have to go to the station, to Déon, to Saint-Michel.
This is Saint-Michel station.
This is the station at Déon.
A subway station.
Then you have to buy tickets
A book of tickets is cheaper
A notebook, please.
How much is it?
Then you need to look for the line Porte de Clignancourt, Porte d'Orléans
Montparnasse, welcome, is on the Porte de Clignancourt, Porte d'Orléans line
Saint-Michel and Odeon too
So it's direct, there's no change
But if you want to go from Strasbourg-Saint-Denis
at Louis-Blanc, well, that's not direct.
There has been a change.
You need to change trains at Gare de l'Est.
First, you have to go through the gates.
You have to put the ticket in the slot.
You need to take the ticket back.
And we need to find the line
Porte de Clignancourt-Porte d'Orléans.
We must not take the direction
Clignancourt Gate. No, no, no, no.
You need to take the train that comes from there.
and which goes to Porte d'Orléans, that is to say the direction of Porte d'Orléans.
There are corridors, tunnels, a whole network of tunnels, a network, the road network, the rail network, the air network.
Robert will get lost in this network of corridors.
He will demonstrate how easily he gets lost.
He will prove that he can get lost anywhere.
Look at Robert on the subway
Robert, the man who gets lost everywhere
Facing him were four gates, two corridors, and one hundred kilometers of tunnels.
The world's largest underground network
Once again, Robert will demonstrate his exceptional knack for getting lost.
Robert, the man who gets lost everywhere, almost everywhere
And now, to relax, watch this advertisement for a watch.
"On the rails, a Kelton, the watch that can withstand anything. Facing it, four locomotives, 200 wagons weighing 100 tons each, a 2.6 km train, the longest train in the world. Once again, Kelton will prove its exceptional robustness. Kelton, watches that can withstand anything. Well, almost anything."
A ticket window at Montreal station, a metro ticket window, a ticket window, a station ticket window.
Robert buys a ticket, a train ticket, a subway ticket, a banknote, a plane ticket, a train ticket.
He buys a round-trip ticket.
Paris-Chartres, that's the outbound journey.
Chartres-Paris, it's the return journey.
Paris-Chartres-Paris, it's a round trip.
I would like a ticket to Toronto.
Toronto.
A round trip?
No, go ahead.
Robert buys a second-class return ticket,
because there are two classes.
The second and the first,
which is more comfortable and more expensive.
They validate their tickets.
He boards the train, which departs immediately.
When the train passes through Versailles, Robert says he would like to visit the castle with Mireille.
But Mireille said nothing. She remained lost in her thoughts.
Robert gets lost on the subway and Mireille gets lost in her thoughts.
She's thinking. Or she's dreaming.
"Annick, what's wrong with you? Are you dreaming?"
"Oh, by the way, my parents would love to meet you."
"By the way, she's thinking about something else."
"By the way, observe."
"Oh, by the way, I almost forgot."
" It's good. "
Now listen, watch, think, and respond.
Look at Robert here.
Ah, no, sir. No, Mrs. Courtois, it's not here.
What did Robert do?
He went through the wrong door.
Now, how can we get to Chartres?
We can go there...
by car?
By plane?
By coach?
By train?
By boat?
Oh no, no, not by boat.
By helicopter?
No, not really.
By bicycle, by motorcycle, on foot, on skis, when there is snow.
Where do I need to go to catch the train?
We need to go to... the train station.
What happened to Mireille?
It broke down.
Mr. Guignol, I've broken down.
Oh, it's not a problem, I'd already fixed it, there you go, it's sorted.
Oh, thank you, Mr. Guignol
You're welcome, it's nothing, it's the least I could do.
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501
by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, the Florence J. Gould Foundation Incorporated, le Ministère
Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of Culture and Communication, the Commissariat
general to the French language, the Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust and the National Endowment
for the Humanities.
For information about this and other Annenberg Media programs, call 1-800-LEARNER and visit
us at www.learner.org.
French subtitles?