Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on
and be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Returning to Paris, Robert and Mireille get seats on a crowded train,
unaware that they are sharing the compartment with a mysterious man in black.
Tonight, Mireille must visit a friend in Saint-Germain.
Tomorrow, one in Provence.
Robert, ever jealous, spends hours trying to find her.
Subtitles ST' 501
On the train back from Chartres, Robert is not in a very good mood.
There are a lot of people on your train. Look at that.
All the compartments are crowded.
No, that's not true.
All the seats are taken, look at that.
People are packed in like sardines.
If I had known, I would have stayed home.
Or I would have rented a car.
Yeah, or you would have come on foot.
Don't worry.
We're not going to stand in the corridor.
Let's look further.
We'll find a place.
Hey, what did I tell you?
This compartment is empty.
Finally, almost empty.
In one corner, there is a passenger hiding behind a newspaper.
The man in black. Strange.
I really don't understand how you can prefer the train to the car.
I appreciate the SNCF.
What?
SNCF, the French National Railway Company.
Note, I have nothing against the car.
On the contrary, I would love to have a small, convertible car.
Or at least with a sunroof.
And a large trunk to put my suitcases in with all my dresses inside.
And a mini-bike.
A small Peugeot 205.
You wouldn't have preferred a little Alpine Renault, by any chance?
Yes, that's true, of course.
Now that's a car.
The real sports car.
Nervous, fast.
Lightning-fast comebacks.
And as for road handling, it's fantastic.
It's driven with the little finger.
And it works, you can do 140 km/h all day without overheating.
And the braking was impeccable.
4 power-assisted disc brakes.
And it uses almost no energy.
6.5 litres per 100 km.
Hey, you seem to know your stuff.
Not necessarily, it's something you're born with.
My father works at Renault.
But anyway, all of that is not for me.
Note that in a way, I just as much like hitchhiking.
All the advantages of a car without the disadvantages.
Are you hitchhiking?
It happened to me.
Once, I hitchhiked from Paris to Geneva.
It took me 8 hours.
That's not bad.
But isn't that dangerous?
Aren't you afraid?
Non.
And that's the charm.
That's it, we've arrived.
Mireille and Robert get off the train
and exit Montparnasse station.
If we were to have dinner on a riverboat,
That would be great, I'll invite you.
That could be good, right?
With all the monuments illuminated.
Oh, do you think so?
That's something for American tourists.
You're not an American tourist, are you?
Anyway, I'm not free tonight.
I have to go to a friend's house to see Saint-Germain.
And the bus is this way.
What? Your driver isn't waiting for you with the Alpine?
My driver? Oh no, not tonight. I gave him the night off.
Look, here comes my bus. Well, on a Thursday evening.
Don't forget that you should be home around 7:30 or 8:00.
Won't I be able to see you tomorrow?
No, impossible. Tomorrow I'm going to Provence. Goodbye.
Hello.
And the bus starts.
A friend?
It wouldn't surprise me if this friend had a slight Swedish look about her.
and beautiful, muscular legs in a pair of sky-blue shorts.
Is Robert jealous?
Taxi !
He hails a taxi.
Boulevard Saint-Germain, please. Where can I stop you? I don't know.
Not mine either, at Flore's café, yes, that's it.
No Mireille, nor any Swedes, at the Flore.
Neither at Demago's, nor at his home, nor at the drugstore, nor at the Martinican romance shop.
Not at Vagenand, nor at Proca, nor at Tabou, nor at Riverside, nor at Whisky à Gogo.
Where could she be?
I don't know about that.
Robert and Mireille leave Chartres and its cathedral.
They went to the train station to take the train to Paris.
They just boarded the train. They're looking for seats. They look in all the compartments, but there are no seats available. There are lots of empty seats. All the compartments are packed. The train is crowded. There are no seats available. All the seats are taken.
Here too, the train is crowded.
All places are taken.
But not here.
There are some free seats here.
There are also free seats here.
There are two free seats there, but the third one is taken.
This carriage has a corridor and compartments.
A compartment.
The corridor.
The corridor. A corridor at university. A corridor on the subway.
Here, Robert and Mireille are standing in the corridor.
Here, they are sitting in a compartment.
Where are the gentleman and lady? In the corridor or in the compartment?
In the compartment.
And the conductor, is he in the compartment or in the corridor?
In the corridor.
Robert is not happy because there are too many people
No, that's not true, all the seats are taken
No, that's not true, he's not happy
Look at Mireille here, she's not happy either.
Oh no, that's not true.
No, that's not true, all the seats are taken
Look at this, people are packed in like sardines!
The train is crowded, people are packed in tightly.
They are packed in like sardines.
Robert is not happy.
He grumbles.
He regrets coming.
If I had known, I would have stayed home.
If I had known...
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She's not happy either.
She is outraged.
She regrets having worked so hard.
If she had known, she would have watched television instead of working.
There is no justice.
If I had known, I would have watched TV.
It took me an hour to do this assignment. It's outrageous.
Mireille is optimistic.
We'll find a place.
Hey, what did I tell you?
Mireille is always right.
This compartment is empty.
Look, Marie-Laure never makes a mistake either.
That's a ten of diamonds.
What was I saying? I'm never wrong.
This compartment is almost never empty, well, almost never, this compartment is alive
The room is empty, well, almost empty. This glass is full, this one is...
The box of chocolates is empty, well, almost empty, the plate is empty.
The carriage is empty.
Mireille appreciates the SNCF, the French National Railway Company.
Everyone appreciates the SNCF.
Because trains are
dressers
comfortable
We are pleased
to inform you that a bar
Relaxation is available to you throughout the entire course. You will find an assortment there.
cold plates, croque-monsieur, sandwiches, coffee and drinks.
And most importantly, the trains are punctual. And besides, the trains are fast.
MFP subtitles.
Subtitles ST' 501
She takes the train. But she would love to have a car. If she were rich, she would like
It's good to have a car. But is Mireille rich? No, she isn't. If
She was rich, that's an assumption. An assumption contrary to reality.
If she were rich, let's say, she would like to have a car. "If she were rich" is the imperfect tense. "She would like to have a car," she would like, is the conditional tense.
She would like to have a convertible car
Or a car with a sunroof
The 2CV, for example, has a sunroof.
A sunroof
She would like a large trunk to put her luggage in.
The trunk is full
You can put a lot of things in a chest
Mireille would like a large trunk to put her suitcases in.
There you go, suitcases.
A suitcase, a suitcase
Look at this gentleman and this lady.
They have two children and a suitcase
Suitcases are interesting.
Mireille would love to have an Alpine.
Because that's a car.
Now that's a car!
It's a fast, responsive car with lightning-fast acceleration.
It accelerates quickly.
Lightning-fast comebacks, like a bolt from the blue.
That's a stunning look.
And as for road handling, it's fantastic.
It's a car that handles well on the road.
A car that handles well.
The car handles surprisingly well.
This is a small car that handles the road very well.
That one also holds up well.
It's holding up well.
It's an easy car to drive.
It's driven with the little finger.
And we can do 140.
140 km/h, all day long, without heating.
That's a car that's overheating.
But the Alpine doesn't overheat.
And the braking was impeccable.
It brakes well.
It's a car with good brakes.
Here's the brake pedal.
And there's the handbrake.
Bob has the opportunity to test the brakes thoroughly during a fast drive through a city.
These are mixed brakes, disc at the front, drum at the rear.
For the brakes, this is the real test.
A brake, to brake, braking.
And it doesn't use that much fuel.
It doesn't use much gas.
Look, a motorized bicycle.
Does it consume a lot? No!
It uses very little fuel.
And Robert and Mireille are drinking kir.
The Alpine doesn't consume much fuel.
Approximately 7 litres per 100 km.
7 litres to travel 100 km
The R5 consumes even less
And as for braking, impeccable.
4 power-assisted disc brakes
Mireille seems to know a lot about cars
She seems to know what she's talking about.
Hey, you seem to know your stuff.
He knows his wine.
In our family, everyone loves the smell of lavender soup.
And we know a thing or two about lavender here.
Mireille is a car expert, she knows her stuff, not necessarily, it's from birth, it's from birth, since her father is an engineer at Renault.
She was born that way, Mireille doesn't have a car, it's a shame, she would like to, but in a way, she likes hitchhiking just as much.
Here are Robert and Mireille hitchhiking
Here's someone hitchhiking
Here's the cartoonist Serre hitchhiking.
He also hitchhikes
And what are they doing? Are they hitchhiking?
No, they're hitchhiking by boat
Hitchhiking is great.
It has all the advantages of a car, without the disadvantages
The car has advantages
It's fast, that's an advantage.
It's convenient. That's an advantage too. But it uses gas. That's a disadvantage. It breaks down. That's a disadvantage too.
Do you hitchhike? Yes, I have. It happens to her. She has hitchhiked. She has hitchhiked a few times. Not often, but it has happened to her.
Observe what Marie-Laure says
Are you doing well in school?
Did you get 10 out of 10 on your homework?
It happened to me once
And you sometimes get zero?
It happened to me
Once, Mireille hitchhiked from Paris to Geneva
It took her 8 hours
She left at 1 a.m. and arrived at 9 a.m.
So it took her 8 hours
Now listen carefully to this exchange between Mireille and Robert about hitchhiking.
Then you will answer Robert as if you were Mireille.
Are you hitchhiking?
It happened to me
Now answer Robert as if you were Mireille.
Are you hitchhiking?
It happened to me
Now we're going to ask someone if they hitchhike.
Do you hitchhike?
Very rarely.
Has that never happened to you?
Yes, it has happened to me, but rarely.
Is it dangerous to hitchhike?
Yes, we still need to take certain precautions.
Robert suggests to Mireille that they go to dinner on a riverboat.
If we went to dinner on a riverboat, that would be nice, I'll treat you.
That could be good, right?
The Bateaux Mouches are boats that go up and down the Seine.
There are small ones and there are big ones.
On the larger ones, you can have dinner in the evening.
Of course, it's a tourist thing, but it's not bad.
It's one way of seeing a part of Paris.
And in the evening, you can see the illuminated monuments.
That would be great, I'll invite you.
That could be good, right?
With all the monuments illuminated.
That would be good.
Listen to what Marie-Laure says.
If I didn't have this dissertation to finish for tomorrow, we could go to the movies.
Yes, that would be good.
Mireille cannot accept Robert's invitation.
She is not free tonight.
She has to go to a friend's house who lives on Boulevard Saint-Germain.
She's going to take the bus from here to get there.
Anyway, I'm not free tonight.
I have to go to a friend's house on Boulevard Saint-Germain.
She checks the bus number and route. Robert thinks of the Alpine and
to the young man with a Swedish look who saw him in Chartres and he said very
(Sarcastic) You're going to take the bus? What do you mean your driver isn't waiting for you?
Not with the Alpine, he really seems jealous, this Robert, a driver, a taxi driver, mind you.
Mireille doesn't understand this sarcastic allusion to the fact that the driver is a woman.
Robert, my driver, oh no, not tonight, I gave him the night off. Tonight I gave my
I told the driver, James, I don't need you tonight, you can take the evening off.
Mireille leaves and Robert, left alone on the sidewalk, becomes increasingly suspicious.
A friend? I wouldn't be surprised if this friend had a slightly Swedish look and nice muscular legs in a little sky-blue shorts.
That wouldn't surprise me.
Observe what Marie-Laure says here.
I wouldn't be surprised if they were chocolates.
Exactly, chocolates.
I had guessed it.
This little girl is really very intelligent, very perceptive.
A friend?
It wouldn't surprise me if this friend had a bit of a Swedish look and nice muscular legs in a little sky-blue shorts.
What is Robert imagining?
Is Mireille having a meeting with the young man from Chartres on Boulevard Saint-Germain?
In any case, he stops a taxi to go to Boulevard Saint-Germain.
Taxi !
Boulevard Saint-Germain, please.
On Boulevard Saint-Germain, yes, very good, but where?
Where do I stop you?
I don't know.
Me neither.
Boulevard Saint-Germain is vague, it's vast.
Boulevard Saint-Germain is long.
The taxi driver, who is a woman, suggests stopping Robert at the Café de Flore.
At the Café de Flore?
Because it's one of the most famous places in Saint-Germain-des-Prés.
A literary café where Jean-Paul Sartre used to be seen, very close to the Saint-Germain-des-Prés church.
Robert is looking for Mireille at the Café de Flore, but she's not there.
He is looking for De Mago, another well-known cafe, just opposite the church.
He goes across the street to Brasserie Lippe, another very well-known cafe and restaurant.
He goes next door, to the Drugstore, to the Martinique Romerie.
where they mainly serve punches and rum-based drinks,
Chez Vagenande, a restaurant in the style of 1900
At Le Procope, the oldest café in Paris, dating back to the 17th century
At Tabou, a cellar, a very well-known nightclub
Everywhere, that is, but no Mireille, nowhere.
Where could she be?
I don't know
Nobody knows
Let's see what you know
Listen, watch, think, and speak.
Look.
Are all the seats taken or are there any seats available?
There are some free seats.
And here, are there any free seats or are all the seats taken?
All places are taken.
Look at Robert and Mireille.
Are they in the compartment or in the corridor?
In the corridor.
And this gentleman, is he in the compartment or in the corridor?
In the compartment.
Based on this image, can you say that this car has lightning-fast acceleration or that it brakes well?
Make sure it brakes properly.
Look at Robert and Mireille here.
What are they doing?
Are they hitchhiking or taking the train?
They are hitchhiking.
In your opinion, is that a hovercraft or a riverboat?
A riverboat.
You have a car that consumes very little fuel.
Is this a disadvantage or an advantage?
That's an advantage.
You receive a gift and you're almost certain it's chocolates.
What are you saying? You're saying...
I wouldn't be surprised if they were chocolates.
Again.
You are not happy. You regret coming.
What are you saying? You're saying...
If I had known, I would have stayed home.
Again.
Now, your daughter or your little sister is doing something wrong.
She drops the snack tray, for example.
What are you saying?
That's not true!
Once again
That's not true
Once again, you are right.
What are you saying?
What was I saying? I'm never wrong
Once again
I think there's a mouse around here
Haven't you seen a mouse?
What was I saying? Here she is!
What is it, Mr. Guignol?
There's a mouse
But come on, Mr. Guignol, that's not true. Are you afraid of mice?
Yes, then!
But come on, at your age...
Yes, I'm afraid of mice. It's gasoline.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
THANKS.