Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Good morning, ladies, good morning, young ladies, good morning, gentlemen.
We are going to learn French.
And to learn French...
We are going to invent a story.
That's it. Very good.
We are going to invent a story about a young French girl,
A young American man, friends, French friends, Japanese, English, Italian friends, lots of friends.
Adventures, journeys, it's going to be a real novel.
A collaborative novel, a collective novel.
Because we're going to invent this together, you and I.
Do you like novels?
Yes. Well, it depends.
Do you like romance novels?
Oh no, I don't like romance novels. I hate them.
Oh really, you don't like romance novels.
What do you like? Do you like adventure novels, fantasy novels, or science fiction novels?
Oh no, I don't like that.
Do you prefer detective novels?
Yes.
And you, miss, do you like detective novels?
Non.
No. Do you like romance novels? No. No. You don't like romance novels either. Do you like adventure novels? No. No. But then, do you like science fiction novels? No. No. But then, but then, you don't like novels at all? No.
Oh really, you don't like novels. You prefer movies?
Yes.
I also prefer the cinema.
What do you prefer? Swedish films? Japanese films?
English comedies? Italian comedies?
American musicals?
You don't like comedies. Neither do I. I don't like comedies.
I prefer tragedies, dramas.
I love crime stories with lots of victims.
I also love crime stories.
Are we going to see a crime in the story?
A crime? I don't know.
Maybe. We'll see.
Let's see. Let's continue inventing the story.
Let's start with the young man, he's American, he's arriving in France.
He is at the airport
The police pass.
We can't get through.
Go ahead, you can pass.
You may pass.
Now he is at customs with two other young men.
Are all three of you French?
No, miss and I are American.
Ah, you speak English?
Of course, since we are Americans.
And you, are you American too?
No, they are American, but I am Brazilian.
You have nothing to declare?
Non.
Okay, you can go through.
Go ahead! Go through!
Is it true that you're Brazilian?
Of course, why not?
Where are you?
The university residence, at the Brazilian house.
Is there a Brazilian house in the city?
Of course, there is a Brazilian house for Brazilian students.
Brazilian. And an American house for Americans. Obviously, that's where you go.
Yes. And you, are you going to the American house? No, I'm not going to the projects. I'm in the neighborhood.
Latin. Are you taking a taxi? No, the shell or the train. And you? I'm taking a taxi. Goodbye.
...
So let's see, what kind of story are we going to choose?
A romance novel or an adventure novel?
That's a romance novel.
And that, that's an adventure novel.
And that, that too, is an adventure novel.
And that, that, that's a love story.
Look at this lady.
She is reading a romance novel.
And what is she reading here?
An adventure novel.
And you, what do you prefer?
Romance novels, detective novels, or science fiction?
Look, this is a detective novel.
That too is a detective novel.
But that's a science fiction novel, a speculative fiction novel.
That too is a science fiction novel.
And what is this?
A detective novel or a science fiction novel?
It's a detective novel.
Is this a detective novel or a science fiction novel?
That's a science fiction novel.
And that's a detective novel.
That's a detective novel.
And that's a crime film.
That too is a crime film.
That's a comedy.
That's an English comedy. It's an English film.
An English comedy, an English film.
And that's an Italian comedy. It's an Italian film.
An Italian comedy, an Italian film.
That's an American film. It's an American musical.
An American film, a musical, an American musical.
That's a Swedish film.
A comedy? No, more like a tragedy.
That's a Canadian film.
Is it a comedy? No, more like a tragedy.
Okay, now let's see what you like.
Do you like Italian comedies? Chocolate candies?
Look at Marie-Laure. She really likes chocolate candies.
She loves it.
Do you like it?
Yes, a lot.
I love chocolates.
She loves chocolates and she loves Uncle Guillaume.
I love Uncle Guillaume.
Let's recap.
Let's see what Marie-Laure likes.
and what she doesn't like.
Chocolates? Yes, she likes them.
Cream puffs? Yes, she likes them.
She likes it.
She likes cream puffs,
But she prefers lightning.
She loves éclairs.
She loves stories.
But she doesn't like learning her lessons.
Uncle Guillaume? Oh yes, she likes Uncle Guillaume.
She adores Uncle Guillaume.
Mireille loves detective novels
But she hates being tickled.
Stop, I hate it!
We're going to ask a few people what they like
Which do you prefer, romance novels or adventure novels?
Adventure novels
And science fiction, do you like it?
Not many
Do you like romance novels?
No not at all
Adventure novels?
Yes, adventure novels or detective novels.
Speculative fiction novels, science fiction?
No, not really.
Do you like adventure novels?
Ah yes, a lot.
Do you like detective novels?
Yes, detective novels, yes.
Which do you prefer, romance novels or detective novels?
In between, there are detective novels.
Now you are going to speak French.
Listen to this dialogue between Robert and Mireille
You will repeat Mireille's answers
Do you like novels?
Oh yes, well, it depends
Do you like romance novels?
Oh no, I don't like romance novels, I hate them.
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille
Do you like novels?
Oh yes, well, it depends
Do you like romance novels?
Oh no, I don't like romance novels, I hate them.
I love Japanese films
And you, do you like Japanese films?
Oh yes !
But Japanese films are not very useful for learning French.
So we're going to invent a French story,
with young French people, French adventures, trips to France.
Are we going to have a crime?
In crime movies, there's always a crime.
If you want, we can have a crime in the story, a crime with a criminal and a
victim, if you want to commit a crime, we can, it's easy, we can, it's possible, we can
Yes, thank you, I can, and you can do that too, of course. Why not?
No, you can't. No, he can't. I can. You can. She can. We can. You can.
They can, they can, if you want, you can have a crime in the story, we'll see.
A crime in history, yes or no, maybe, maybe, we'll see about that.
It depends, we'll see. You give me a ball of gum, maybe? We'll see about that.
depends on whether you are nice
Maybe, I don't know, we'll see.
Look, you'll see.
I'll go see.
What is this ?
I don't know, we'll see.
Oh, candy! Are they good?
I'll go see.
Yes, they're good, and as for me, I don't know, we'll have to see, it depends, we'll see, we'll
Start the story. Start. Come on, start, start. Okay, I'll start, then. Let's see.
Well, go ahead, start. Let's see, where do I start?
astramus, gram, piqué, piqué, collé, gram, bourré, bourré, ratatam, astramus, gram.
You start.
Okay, let's begin. Let's start the story.
At the beginning of the story, a young man arrives in France.
A young man. A young man. A young man.
And that's the young man in the story.
A young man, the young man in the story. A young man, undefined. The young man, defined. A young girl, the young girl in the story. A young girl, undefined. The young girl, defined.
"Young people," "The young people of history." "Young people," indefinite article. "The young people," definite article.
Okay, so the young man in the story arrives here, the plane arrives here, it's the
The train is arriving, it's arriving here. The train is leaving, it's leaving, it's arriving, it's leaving, it's arriving.
When a celebrity arrives for a visit, it always starts with music.
Now, look closely. Is he arriving or leaving? He's arriving. Is she arriving or leaving? She's arriving. Look at Marie-Laure here. Is she leaving or arriving? She's leaving.
And Robert here, is he arriving or leaving? He's arriving.
And this young girl, is she arriving or leaving? She's arriving.
And the bus here, is it leaving or arriving? It's leaving.
And here he arrives.
Miss, it's for you. Yes, I'm coming. I'm leaving.
He arrives, he leaves. To arrive, to leave.
The young man arrives in France. He is at the airport. It's Charles de Gaulle Airport in Roissy. It's one of the airports in Paris. It's an international airport.
at an airport, the police are passing by, a police officer, a police officer, a police officer
a police station a police car the traffic police the police a police officer a
A police dog.
A detective novel.
The police officer looks at his passport.
Here is a French passport.
But Robert has an American passport, obviously, since he is American.
Then he goes through customs.
Customs.
That's Swiss customs.
Swiss customs officers.
Robert has nothing to declare.
He can pass, since he has nothing to declare.
Okay, you can go through. Go ahead, go through.
Look at this gentleman, this lady. They are going through customs.
Please come along.
Please, go ahead.
But come on, let me through.
First movement of the concerto.
Can I come through?
But go ahead, miss, go ahead.
Let's sit down to eat.
Let's move on to the living room.
They go into the living room.
The young people are at the airport.
They are going to Paris.
The Brazilian is going to the university residence.
The university residence at the University of Paris is for students, both foreign and French students.
At the university residence, there are rooms, a library and a house for each foreign country.
A house.
That's a house in the Pyrenees.
That's a house in Brittany.
That's another house in Brittany.
That's Aunt Amélie's house.
The Brazilian is going to the Brazilian home.
But there is also a Japanese house for Japanese students.
A Dutch house for Dutch students.
A Lebanese house for Lebanese students.
A Swedish house for Swedish students.
A Danish house for the Danes.
An American home for Americans.
A Mexican house for Mexicans.
A Cuban home for Cubans.
A Tunisian home for Tunisians.
A Norwegian home for Norwegians.
A Canadian home for Canadians.
A Cambodian home for Cambodians.
An Indian house for Indians.
An Armenian house for Armenians.
A Swiss house.
A Belgian house and an English house.
The girl goes to the American house because she is American.
And this young man goes to the Brazilian house because he is...
Brazilian.
No, no, no, no, no. He's Brazilian.
Listen, a young Brazilian girl, a young Brazilian man.
She is American. He is American.
She is French. He is French.
She is Swedish. He is Swedish.
Look. A young girl. Male or female?
Female.
A young man.
Male.
A lady.
Female.
A gentleman.
Male.
A man.
A woman.
Female.
A student.
Male.
Now, pay attention. Listen carefully.
A house. Masculine or feminine?
Female.
A library.
Male or female?
Female.
A university.
A professor.
Male.
A passport.
A cinema
Male
A story
Femina
A novel
Male
A film
A comedy
Femina
A tragedy
A trip
Male
An adventure
Femina
A game
Male
An elephant
A dog
Male
A crime
A victim. Ah, watch out. A female victim. Look. There's a victim. The victim is a man, but victim is feminine. A victim is feminine. A victim. A victim.
Now look. Is a teacher masculine or feminine? A teacher is masculine.
A professor, a professor, professor, it's masculine.
A victim, a victim, a victim, victim, it's feminine.
A masculine, a feminine, the masculine, the feminine.
To get to Paris, young people can take a train, a bus, or a taxi.
The young American is going to the Latin Quarter.
The student quarter, the university quarter.
Let's recap. We are going to learn French.
To learn French, we are going to invent a story.
For the sake of the story, we will choose two young people.
The young people will make friends.
To learn, to invent, to choose, to have, that's the infinitive.
Learn, understand, take in, be, do
To invent, to love, to adore, to hate, to begin, to go
And choosing, leaving, coming, having, seeing, being able to, knowing, all of these are infinitives.
Okay, let's see what you've learned.
I am the professor and you are the students.
We are going to learn French.
To learn French, we are going to invent a story.
It's going to be the story of two young people.
A young girl and a young man.
The young man in the story is going to be...
American.
At the beginning of the story, the young man arrives in...
In France.
He is at...
The airport.
At the airport.
He is with two others...
Young people.
He goes through the police, he goes through the net, then he takes a taxi to go to Paris.
That's all for today.
Goodbye ladies, goodbye young ladies, goodbye gentlemen.
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada