Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on
and be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Robert is determined to find Mireille.
He rents a car and gets directions to Provence.
But he turns to follow a sports car
driven by a young woman who might be Mireille.
By the time he realizes his mistake,
he is 300 kilometers off course,
lost in the wine country of Burgundy.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Towards the east, or rather the south, yes that's it, that's the southeast of Paris, it's not very far.
Is this near Chartres?
Oh no, Chartres is towards the southwest, the province is above Fontainebleau, you know.
THANKS.
Do you know where I could rent a car?
Oh yes ?
Avis, Hertz, Europecar, Matéi.
Why do you want to rent a car?
Yes.
Go to the Shell garage, at the bottom of Aspaille Boulevard.
If you like, he's a friend.
Tell him you're coming from me.
THANKS.
Hello Sir.
Good morning.
I am here on behalf of the owner of Home Latin.
I would like to rent a car for the day.
Yes, what do you want?
A big car, a small car,
Automatic or manual gear shifting?
Look, I have a brand new Renault 11 here,
with five synchronized floor-mounted speeds.
I also have a CX, with hydraulic suspension.
It's very comfortable.
Oh, I don't care about that.
Give me the cheapest one.
That R5 over there, for example.
Apparently, the R5s are the cheapest.
It's true ?
I'm sorry, but it's not allocated.
I can't give it to you.
But if you want, I can give you a Peugeot 205.
Is that the cheapest option you have?
Yes.
Good.
How much is it for the day?
450 francs.
Okay, I'll take it.
If you would be so kind as to give me your driver's license.
Ah, an American driver's license.
A few minutes later, Robert is behind the wheel of the Peugeot.
We're going to Fontainebleau, it's this way.
Yes, go back up the boulevard in Spa, it's right there in front of you.
Are you familiar with Paris?
No, not really.
Here.
Okay, I'll show you. You're here. Go up Boulevard Raspail to Denfert-Rochereau. You'll see, it's a square with a lion. Turn right onto Avenue du Général Leclerc. Follow it to Porte d'Orléans. And there, take the ring road on the left. Just follow the signs for the A6 motorway towards Lyon.
There are signs everywhere, there's no way to get lost.
You cannot get lost
Alright
Thank you, goodbye
Goodbye, have a good trip
Meanwhile, Mireille calls her uncle Guillaume
To borrow a car from him
Uncle? That's me, Mireille.
Tell me, I have to go to Provins to see my friend Colette
You know, Colette Besson, could you lend me a car?
Yes, my dear Mireille, of course.
Take whichever one you want, it won't matter.
At CX?
Understood. Take it to the garage whenever you want.
I'm going to call them to let them know.
Thank you, goodbye.
Meanwhile, Robert is walking up Boulevard Raspail.
He arrives at Hell-of-Horses Square.
The square with the lion,
veer to the right,
Take Avenue du Général Leclerc, follow it, follow it all the way to Porte d'Orléans, it should
To be here now, take the ring road on the left, the A6 motorway towards
In Lyon, there are signs everywhere, there's no way to get lost.
Three hours later, Robert is completely lost
300 kilometers from Easter, in the heart of Burgundy.
He asks for directions.
Excuse me, sir, is the road to Paris this way?
You're mistaken, young man. The road to Paris is to the right, over there.
There, over there, that's Marcon. There, you're lost.
This is what happened.
In Fontainebleau, he wanted to get off the highway
to go back up towards Provins.
Just as he was exiting the interchange, he saw an Alpine with a blonde woman inside who
Robert was heading onto the motorway towards Lyon when he immediately turned around and started
In pursuit, Robert accelerates at full throttle, but the Alpine refuses to let him pass.
Just before Beaune, the Alpine stops for Andolescence.
Fill up with premium gasoline, please.
The blonde woman gets out of the car and heads towards the toilets.
That's not good.
Disgusted, Robert exits the highway
and will get lost in the Burgundy vineyards.
Alox, Corton.
Night, Saint-Georges.
Vaux-le-Romalais.
Rougeau.
Chambol-Musigny.
Gevrey-Chambertin.
Fixed.
Last time, Robert wanted to go to dinner with Mireille on a riverboat.
But she said she wasn't free, that she was going to a friend's house on Boulevard Saint-Germain.
Robert took a taxi and went to Saint-Germain to try and find Mireille.
He didn't find it.
He slept badly.
He's not in good shape.
Look at Jean-Claude here, he's not in good shape.
Yes, he's in good shape here. He's in top form.
In shape, not in shape.
Not in good shape.
In shape, in shape, not in shape.
They look to be in good shape.
But they don't look to be in good shape.
I have a crushed one.
Oh, you don't look well.
Robert asks where Provins is.
This is the southeast of Paris.
North, west, south, east, southeast.
It's near Chartres.
Oh no, Chartres is towards the southwest.
Provins is near Fontainebleau.
Are you familiar with Fontainebleau?
There is a beautiful forest and a beautiful castle.
Provins is not far away.
Let's ask someone where Provins is.
Is it far from Paris?
I would say about a hundred kilometers east of Paris.
It is 90 kilometers east of Paris on the road to Troyes.
Is this near Chartres?
No, not really, no.
Oh no, not at all, it's in the opposite direction.
According to the hotel owner, it's a little above Fontainebleau.
It's above Fontainebleau.
Above, below.
Look.
Mireille lives on this floor.
That's the floor above.
And that's the floor below.
Robert wants to rent a car.
To go to Provins, obviously.
The hotel owner recommended a garage on Boulevard Raspail.
Because the garage owner is a friend.
Go to the Shell garage, it's at the bottom of Boulevard Raspail.
Down, up.
Up, down.
Where is Raymond?
He is at the top.
Down, up.
Up, down.
At the very top of the Pyrenees mountain range, at the foot of the Vignomal massif, lies Lake Gaube.
Go to the Shell garage. It's at the bottom of Boulevard Raspail. You can go there on my behalf.
That's what Robert does. He says he's there on behalf of the hotel owner.
Hello Sir.
Good morning.
I am here on behalf of the owner of the Latin home.
From. Observe.
Hello? Yes, you've reached Mr. Bello's?
Yes, I can see if he's there. Who's calling?
Mr. Charpentier. Very well. Don't hang up.
Dad, this is for you! Mr. Carpenter speaking!
Robert is here on behalf of his hotel owner.
The owner is the boss. You can own a hotel,
One can own a house and a garden.
One can own a car.
Observe this scene.
You are going to see a worried car owner.
This is your car, number 11 027 SK 94.
11 027 SK 94.
Do you know the owner?
Robert can choose between a big car or a small car.
A big car, a small car.
And a very small car.
Robert can choose between automatic or manual gear shifting.
That's a manual, floor-mounted gear shift.
The mechanic recommended a CX, a Citroën car that has hydraulic suspension.
It's very comfortable.
Comfortable, look, the floor, it's not very comfortable, it's hard
A sofa is more comfortable
A bench is less comfortable than a sofa
An iron chair isn't very comfortable.
But two chairs are more comfortable
And a deckchair is even more comfortable
But comfort is not what interests Robert.
Comfort is irrelevant to him.
He doesn't care.
Robert wants the cheapest car.
A 2CV, for example, or an R5.
These are the cheapest cars.
The mechanic does have an R5, but it is not allocated.
I'm sorry, it's not allocated.
Listen to what Marie-Laure says, who doesn't want to sell her last chocolate.
Give me a chocolate.
I only have one left.
I'll buy it from you.
How much?
50 cents.
I'm sorry. This chocolate is not for sale. I'm keeping it.
The mechanic is offering a Peugeot 205.
It's more expensive than a 2CV or an R5, but it's the cheapest one he has.
Is that the cheapest option you have?
Yes.
The Citroën is the most comfortable car he has.
The Alpine is the fastest car he has.
The R5 is the cheapest option.
How much is it for the day?
450 francs.
Okay, I'll take it.
Alright.
If you would be so kind as to give me your driver's license.
Ah, an American driver's license.
That's a French driving licence.
Listen carefully to this conversation between the garage owner and Robert.
Then, you will answer the mechanic as if you were Robert.
I'm sorry, but it's not allocated. I can't give it to you.
If you want, I can give you a Peugeot 205.
That's the cheapest option you have.
Yes.
Okay, that's fine. How much is it for the day?
450 francs.
Okay, I'll take it.
Now, answer as if you were Robert.
I'm sorry, but it's not allocated. I can't give it to you.
If you want, I can give you a Peugeot 205.
That's the cheapest option you have.
Yes.
Okay, that's fine.
How much is it for the day?
450 francs.
Okay, I'll take it.
Okay, so, in the end, Robert takes the 205.
It's a small Peugeot car.
In France, there are many small cars.
What kind of car do you have?
I have a Peugeot 304, a French car.
Is it a big car?
No, small car.
Is it a car with an automatic transmission?
No, manual gear shifting.
I have a 104 that is 12 years old, like a good whisky.
Is it a big car?
It's a small car that serves me very well in Paris, and it runs very well.
Let's get back to Robert. He is now driving the 205.
The steering wheel.
A young woman driving a bus
Robert asks the garage owner for directions
He asks how to get to Fontainebleau
Fontainebleau, yes, because he knows that Provins is next to Fontainebleau
To get to Fontainebleau, it's this way.
Okay, to understand the mechanic's explanations, we need to review a few terms.
First, a boulevard, this is Boulevard Raspail
Boulevard Saint-Michel, Boulevard Saint-Germain. There's also a ring road. It's a boulevard that goes around Paris. And then there are the avenues that resemble boulevards.
This, for example, is General Leclerc Avenue. The Champs-Élysées is also an avenue, a very grand, very wide avenue. Here's another avenue. And then there are the streets. A street, a small street, an old street.
And then there are the seats
Place Saint-Michel, Place de la Sorbonne
Place de la Concorde, Place Vendôme
Place de la Bastille, Place de l'Étoile
Place Saint-Sulpice, a square in the provinces
Another place in the provinces, another place
And outside the cities, there are the roads and highways.
To get on or off a motorway, there are interchanges.
Here's an interchange, a motorway exit to go to Fontainebleau. Robert needs to take
To get to motorway 6, he has to go up Boulevard Raspail.
Here are some cars driving up the Champs-Elysées.
You need to follow Boulevard Aspaille to Place d'Enfer-Rochereau
Here, you need to turn right, turn slightly to the right.
There's a car veering to the right.
At Porte d'Orléans, you need to take the ring road to the left, that is to say, towards the east.
towards the A6 motorway which goes to Lyon.
Fortunately, there are signs everywhere.
You can't get lost.
It is impossible to get lost.
There's no way to get lost.
There are signs everywhere.
There's no way to go wrong.
You can't get lost.
It's impossible. There's no way.
Observe this scene where Mireille doesn't arrive
to open a jar of jam.
I'm sorry, there's no way to open it.
There must be a way.
I'm telling you there's no way.
I've tried everything.
You see, there was a way.
Where there's a will, there's always a way.
Of course, where there's a will, there's always a way.
Robert always manages to get lost.
Look at him. He's completely lost in the middle of Burgundy.
This is what happened.
He was exiting the motorway at Fontainebleau
when he saw a red Alpine with a young blonde girl inside.
He turned around.
One turn, one half turn.
The car turns around.
They turn around
Robert turned around and set off in pursuit of the Alpine.
He's following the Alpine; it's a chase.
He rushes forward, he goes as fast as he can
He hurries, he rushes
He rushes forward
Go for it, go for it!
Robert is speeding along at full throttle.
He presses the accelerator all the way down, to the maximum.
Robert tries to overtake the Alpine.
Look, we're not going fast, all the cars are passing us.
Watch the taxi, it's going to overtake the small car.
Near Beaune, in Burgundy, the Alpine stops at a service station to get gas.
Fill up with premium gasoline, please.
You can ask for 10 litres, 20 litres or, generally, a full tank.
The dish, please
Right away, miss
At gas stations, there are two types of gasoline
Regular and premium gasoline
Super petrol is more expensive than regular petrol
When Robert sees that the blonde girl is not Mireille
He is disgusted, he is sickened.
and he will get lost in the vineyards of Burgundy,
in Lox-Corton, Nuit-Saint-Georges, etc.
Meanwhile, Mireille borrows a car from Uncle Guillaume.
Could you lend me a car?
Mireille borrows the car, and her uncle lends his car.
Observe.
Hey, you're rich, can you lend me 50 francs?
Will you give them back to me?
Ten, twenty, thirty, forty and fifty.
THANKS.
Here, the fifty francs I borrowed from you yesterday.
In this scene, Mireille borrows fifty francs and Marie-Laure lends fifty francs.
Mireille borrows her car from Uncle Guillaume.
And Uncle Guillaume lends him his car.
Uncle Guillaume is going to phone the garage to let them know that Mireille is going to take her car.
He's going to warn the garage.
You should always call to let us know.
Look.
I'll let you know so that someone can be sent here to keep an eye on your house.
Warning, this is more serious.
It was the police who needed to be notified.
And so in fact, your friend Bailly died on June 25, 1973.
Do you know what time?
At 8:17 a.m.
I know, I was there.
I looked at my watch at that moment, instinctively.
And it was me who alerted the police to this stupid accident.
In serious cases, the police should always be notified.
If you don't hear from me in a half-war, you notify the police.
Let's see what you have to say.
Listen, think, and speak.
Look at Robert. Is he in good shape or not?
He's not in good shape.
In your opinion, is Provins more southeast or northwest of Paris?
To the southeast.
On the map, is Provins above or below Fontainebleau?
Above.
You are Mireille. You answer the phone.
This is someone who wants to speak to Mr. Bello.
What are you asking?
What did you say?
Who is this from?
Again.
What is that? The gear shift or the steering wheel?
The steering wheel.
And is that the gear shift or the brake?
The gear change.
In your opinion, is this a highway or a road?
A highway.
In your opinion, are these cars going down the Champs-Élysées or up it?
They pull them up.
According to the mechanic, why is it impossible to make a mistake?
Because there are signs everywhere.
What is Robert doing?
He turns around.
Do you need petrol or premium?
What are you saying?
Fill up with premium gasoline, please.
Mireille wants to go to Provins.
She doesn't have a car.
What is she asking Uncle Guillaume?
She asks him to lend her a car.
You have an appointment with Mireille.
You can't go there.
What needs to be done?
We need to warn her.
Hello, Mr. Guignol. I'm here on behalf of Mr. Dupont.
Mr. Dupont doesn't know.
It's for renting a car.
Do you want to rent a car?
Yes, Mr. Guignol, I want to rent a car.
I'm trying to melt your heart. That's a very beautiful car.
Comfortable, fast, sunroof, four wheels.
Roux, it holds up very well.
You steer a steering wheel with your little finger.
Hood, engine, brrrr, brrrr.
Front chew, back chew, everything.
How much is it?
1000 francs per day.
Okay, I'll take it.
Subtitles ST' 501
...
For more information on this and other Annenberg media programs,
Call 1-800-LEARNER and visit us at www.learner.org.