Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Indeed, shortly afterwards, Robert emerges onto the rue de Vosgirard.
52.
It must be this way.
54 ?
No, then it's not here.
46, 28, 12
But where is the 18th?
There is no 18, it doesn't exist.
Well, well, could Mireille have given me a fake number?
No, there it is, 18 is here
It is a fairly old building, with five floors, and a sixth floor under the roof.
Near the front door, there is a button and a small sign that says "Ring and enter".
Robert presses the button, pushes the door open and enters.
The light went out immediately.
The vestibule is dark and smells like cat pee.
Robert is looking for a list of tenants
There aren't any.
He thought to himself that he should have asked Mireille which floor she lived on.
That would have been simpler
On the glass door of the concierge's lodge
There's a sign that says hit hard
Robert hits
No effect
He hits harder
Yes, what is it?
Bello, please.
Georgette Bello, on the fifth floor at the back of the courtyard.
No, Mr. and Mrs. Bello.
Ah, they live on the fourth floor, right.
Take the stairs opposite, the elevator isn't working.
The elevator is small and looks fragile
Even if he had walked, Robert would probably have preferred to go up on foot.
At the foot of the stairs, on the ground floor, a small sign orders
"Wipe your feet"
Robert obeyed, he wiped his feet
Having reached the fourth-floor landing, he notices near the right-hand door
A small business card that says
Mr. François Bello, engineer and captain
He gives a discreet ring to the doorbell
A smiling young girl opens
This is not Mireille
Ah, excuse me, I must have made a mistake
I... I was looking for the Bello
This is the right place, you haven't made a mistake.
You must be Mr. Taylor, no doubt. I'm Colette Besson, a friend of Mireille's. Come in.
In the entrance hall, Robert notices a large vase with half a dozen roses reflected in a mirror, happily completing the dozen.
It's the American!
Come on Marie-Laure, you need to be polite, what's with these manners?
That's my beloved cowboy. Hi, cowboy. Where did you leave your horse?
I tied him up in the garden downstairs.
You did the right thing, because we don't have any space here.
And you know, we're not really used to receiving cowboys with horses.
If you would be so kind as to sit down for a moment in the living room, I will inform Mrs. Bello.
The room Robert is in is a fairly large living room
which connects to the dining room, where the table is already set for this meal.
A sofa, a few chairs, Louis XVI and Second Empire armchairs, a piano, and on the wall, two or three modern paintings.
Madame Bellou enters
I am delighted to meet you
Madame
The Courtois have told us a lot about you
Mr. Bellou's follow-up
Marie-Laure, very happy to meet you
Sir
Hello Robert, how are you? I see you've already met my parents
Marie-Laure, please turn off the TV.
It's the weather report. And Robert, quite astonished, recognizes the presenter.
But I know this gentleman.
Really ?
Not possible.
No kidding.
Do you know Alain Gilopétré? Since when?
Just now. I met him in the street. I was a little lost. He pointed me towards Rue de Vaugirard.
And how long ago did you last see it?
No, just now. Maybe half an hour ago.
Well, he made it to the studio in a hurry.
Oh yeah?
He seemed to be in a hurry.
And did you talk to him?
Yes.
He might talk about you, an American cowboy lost in the streets of Paris.
Marie-Laure, you are unbearable.
Titoudon, it's very hot in here.
Let's go out onto the balcony for a moment, I'll show you the view.
An unobstructed view, as you can see, with the Luxembourg Gardens right in front.
There, the Senate, naturally.
Over there on the left is the Pantheon.
And on the right, over there, alas, the Montparnasse tower.
58 floors. A horror, a catastrophe.
It can be seen from all over Paris.
And the Eiffel Tower, we can't see it?
No, not from here. It's further to the right.
It can be seen from the rooms that overlook the courtyard.
Come, Mr. Taylor.
So, this is our bedroom, there's the bathroom, but we can't see the Eiffel Tower from here, we can't see the tops of the rooms that are on this side overlooking the courtyard.
Mr. Bello and Robert return to the living room
You have a really beautiful apartment.
Passing by the kitchen
Well, it looks like everyone's in the kitchen
We really like this apartment.
We were already living here when Mireille was born
It is very well situated in full sun, and there is plenty of sunshine.
Excuse me for a minute, I'm going to prepare the appetizers.
Robert and Mireille are alone on the balcony for a moment.
It's true that you have a magnificent view.
Yes.
Hey, I wanted to tell you, my parents have invited a friend of mine, Hubert de Pinochambra.
He is a childhood friend, and he comes from a very aristocratic family.
And he's always talking about his family, his ancestors, their hunting, their horses, their castle.
The family owns a large construction company.
But you shouldn't take him too seriously because, in fact, he's just playing.
And he plays his role as a great aristocrat remarkably well.
He's a funny guy, you'll see.
It's very funny.
Personally, I find it amusing.
He amuses me greatly.
Hey, that must be him.
You may have noticed that Robert often gets lost
So he is forced to ask for directions
For example, when he went to the Courtois' place, he ended up at the Defense
Miss, please, the Totem Tower
I don't know, you're in La Défense here, it's not this way, I don't think so.
He takes the metro again and a quarter of an hour later, he finds himself in Montmartre.
"Excuse me, the Quai de Grenelle, please. The Totem Tower is this way."
"The Quai de Grenelle, but that's in the 15th arrondissement. Here, you're in Montmartre."
Here, he wants to go to Provins and he asks where Fontainebleau is.
"To get to Fontainebleau, it's this way."
"Yes, go back up Boulevard Raspail, right there in front of you."
And three hours later, he finds himself in the heart of Burgundy.
"Excuse me, sir, Paris is that way."
Today, he has to go to the Bélots' house. He got lost again.
Don't follow him, he's lost.
He meets a man and asks him for directions.
Excuse me sir, excuse me, I'm a little lost.
Vougira Street, please.
It's this way, that was the side. Is it that way?
No, it's this way, it's not far, you're almost there.
A few minutes later, at the Bélots' house, he sees this gentleman on television.
So 17 degrees in Perpignan, we are 4, 5 degrees above huge seasonal averages, we don't understand anything anymore.
But I know him, sir.
Really ?
Alain-Gillot Pétret is the one who gives the weather report.
What a coincidence!
Robert eventually made it to the Bélots' place, but it was a difficult journey.
He eventually found the rue de Vaugirard, but he couldn't find number 18.
Finally, he found it.
It is a late 19th-century building with five or six floors.
It's that building at number 2. Second floor, door on the left.
In the center of Paris, most buildings have five or six floors, except for the Montparnasse tower which has 58 floors.
The ground floor, the first floor, the second floor, the third floor
The fourth floor, the fifth floor, under the roof
Roofs, roofs
The rooftops of Paris
So Robert finally found the Bélots' house.
There is a large door, he rings the bell, presses the button and pushes the door open.
The moment he enters, the light goes out.
She turns it off, she turns it on.
The lights turn on, the lights turn off.
Here the headlights are on and here they are off.
You can also light or extinguish a fire, a cigarette, the TV.
Put out your cigarette, old man.
Marie-Laure, please turn off the TV.
Turn off.
Turn it off!
Turn off everything.
And here, we turn it on.
You can turn it on.
No, stop, it's bothering me.
He turns it off.
It turns on.
Stop, I'm telling you it bothers me.
He turns it off.
He turns it back on.
Robert doesn't know which floor Mireille lives on.
So he looks for the concierge to ask her.
He strikes.
No effect.
No one comes, no one answers.
He hits harder.
Yes, what is it?
Enter.
Bello, please.
Georgette Bello, on the fifth floor at the back of the courtyard.
On the fifth floor at the back of the courtyard.
At the fifth, she means on the fifth floor.
Are the rooms on the first floor, sir?
Well...
Can you go, Dad?
Yes !
"Au premier" means on the first floor.
So, which floor is it on?
At the top, last.
Bello, please.
Georgette Bello, on the fifth floor, at the back of the courtyard.
She lives on the fifth floor, at the back of the courtyard.
Isn't your office at the back of the courtyard?
The courtyard? Now that's a courtyard.
An old courtyard.
A farmyard.
A schoolyard.
A courtyard.
Very often in Paris, buildings have an interior courtyard.
There are apartments facing the street and there are apartments facing the courtyard
An apartment facing the street, an apartment facing the courtyard
The Bélots' apartment is not on the courtyard, it's on the street
On the fourth floor, you need to take the stairs
The staircase, do you remember?
There is an elevator, but it is out of order.
There is an elevator there and it is not out of order.
Here's an elevator, a modern elevator.
The elevator in the bicycle section is older.
And on that day, it didn't work. It broke down.
The elevator breaks down here.
But what is it, sir?
I don't know. It's a breakdown.
Ladies and gentlemen, don't panic.
It's nothing, just a minor incident. We'll get you off the train.
But that's outrageous!
Above a certain room price, the elevators must not break down.
Listen to the short exchange between Robert and the concierge.
Then, you will answer Robert as if you were the concierge.
Bello, please.
Georgette Bello ?
On the fifth floor at the back of the courtyard.
No, Mr. and Mrs. Bello.
Ah, they live on the fourth floor, right.
Is there an elevator?
No, take the stairs opposite, the elevator is not working.
Now it's your turn. You're the concierge.
Bello, please.
Georgette Bello ?
On the fifth floor at the back of the courtyard.
No, Mr. and Mrs. Bello.
Ah, they live on the fourth floor, right.
Ah, they live on the fourth right-hand side.
Is there an elevator?
No, take the stairs opposite, the elevator is not working.
Robert will go up the stairs.
Wipe your feet.
Robert, obediently, wipes his feet.
He wipes his feet. He wipes his forehead. She wipes her hands. And he wipes a hat. That's the verb "to wipe".
Now, Robert is in the entrance
This lady is in the entrance
In the entryway, there is a vase with half a dozen roses
That is to say, six roses
Behind the vase, there is a mirror.
A mirror
The six roses are reflected in the mirror
That makes a dozen roses
Six roses in the vase and six roses in the mirror, twelve roses.
The roses are reflected in the mirror; that's the verb "to reflect."
Here, the houses opposite are reflected in the windows.
These are people whose reflections are in shop windows.
The trees are reflected in the water.
Here, pink flamingos are reflected in the water.
Here, a castle is reflected in the water.
Here, the towers are reflected in the water.
Here, the boats and houses are reflected in the water.
Here, the abbey of Brantôme is reflected in the water.
These are just reflections.
He's my beloved cowboy.
The French love cowboys.
Kiluk, the man who shoots faster than his shadow, is a very likeable hero.
Note that the French also like Indians very much.
Okay, now let's tour the apartment. We've already seen the entrance. Here's the living room. It's more of a living room than a lounge. Here's a lounge.
In the Bélots' living room, there is a sofa and armchairs.
A sofa, a couch, and armchairs.
Second Empire armchairs, a Louis XVI armchair, an armchair at Marcel Proust's aunt's house.
A chair, garden chairs, cafe chairs, church chairs.
Here's someone who repairs chairs.
He repairs chairs too.
There's a piano, a piano, a piano, on the floor, a carpet.
On the wall, a few paintings.
A painting.
The living room connects to the dining room.
There is no door between the two rooms.
It's almost the same room.
The living room opens directly onto the dining room.
In the dining room, the table is set for seven place settings.
A place setting.
Good morning, sir. A place setting, please.
Please.
Here, the table is set for seven place settings.
There will be seven of them.
Come on, Mr. and Mrs. Belleau, that makes two.
Mireille makes three. Colette makes four.
Marie-Laure makes five. And Robert makes six.
Who is the seventh?
Mystery and bubblegum
There are three bedrooms in the bicycle apartment
The parents' room, Mireille's room, and Marie-Laure's room
There is also a bathroom
There is also a kitchen
This is the cuisine of the courteous
Aunt Georgette's Kitchen
The kitchen of the holiday home
And here is the kitchen of Marcel Proust's aunt in Illiers
A living room, a dining room, three bedrooms, a bathroom and a kitchen
In total, that makes seven pieces
Seven rooms including the kitchen and bathroom
But that's not counting the entrance and the hallway, which aren't really rooms.
And on which floor do you live?
At the fifth
What kind of rooms are there in your apartment?
It's a studio apartment. There's a main room and two small bedrooms.
Is there a kitchen?
Yes, very small.
Anything else?
A small bathroom.
How many coins do you have?
There are four rooms.
What are these parts?
The living room, two bedrooms, and then the storage room, the bathroom, the toilet and everything.
You don't have a kitchen?
Yes, yes, the kitchen too, yes, a large kitchen, the living room and the dining room.
bicycles overlook the street there is a balcony balconies a balcony a balcony from this balcony we
It has a very pretty view; we have a view of the Luxembourg Gardens. Let's go out onto the balcony for a moment.
I'll show you the view; it's very important, everyone wants a view.
The view!
A view of the Pyrenees, a view of the valley and the lake, a view of the valley, a view of the Calanques.
From the Courtois' house, there is a view of Paris.
From the Belleaux balcony, you can see the Senate and the Luxembourg Palace, the Pantheon and the Montparnasse Tower.
But we can't see the Eiffel Tower because it's on the other side.
But you can see the top of the Eiffel Tower, from windows overlooking the courtyard.
From these windows, you can also see the towers of Saint-Sulpice.
Let's see, let's take a look around at the towers.
The towers of Notre-Dame, the towers of Chartres Cathedral,
the towers of Carcassonne, a tower of the castle of Chinon,
the towers of a late medieval castle.
The towers of Aigues-Mortes, the Eiffel Tower,
the towers of La Défense, the Montparnasse tower.
A horror, a catastrophe.
Mr. Belleau does not like the Montparnasse Tower.
He doesn't like her.
He says something horrible because he doesn't like it.
Listen.
I'll serve the tea, madam.
Tea, how awful.
It's the scotch today.
Apart from the Montparnasse Tower, which is a disaster, a horror,
Mr. Belleau is very proud of his eyesight.
We really like this apartment because of the view.
An unobstructed view thanks to the Luxembourg Gardens.
It belongs to the state.
No one will ever be able to build in front of our house and take away our view.
A breathtaking view.
Mireille explains to Robert who will be the seventh person at dinner.
This is Hubert.
Hey, I wanted to tell you, my parents have invited a friend of mine, Hubert de Pinot-Chambrin.
He is a childhood friend and comes from a very aristocratic family.
And you'll see, he's always talking about his family, his ancestors.
His family owns a whole bunch of castles, hunting grounds, with dogs, horses, all that stuff.
The family owns a large construction company.
He's a funny guy, you'll see.
He's not like everyone else, and he's fun.
He's a strange guy.
Look, you're going to see a funny rabbit.
What is this ?
It's a rabbit.
That's a funny rabbit.
What's so funny about my rabbit?
Now let's see what you have to say.
Look, listen, think, and speak.
You want to go to rue de Vaugirard.
You're a little lost.
You stop a passerby. What do you say to him?
Excuse me, sir. I'm a little lost.
Rue de Vaugirard, please.
In your opinion, is this the ground floor or the sixth floor?
The sixth floor.
Look at it. Are the headlights on or off?
Turned off.
And here, is the light on or off?
Turned on.
Look closely. Is that a street or a courtyard?
A courtyard.
Is that a staircase or an elevator?
A staircase.
What is that? Is it a chair or an armchair?
An armchair.
Is this a dining room or a bedroom?
A dining room.
You have a very nice apartment.
Yes, we love it. It's very well located, and there's plenty of sunshine.
It's very well located, it has its rooms,
We count in the kitchen and the bathroom,
There is plenty of sunshine, the toilets are in the Louis XVI style.
Go go
Oh, those two annoy me.
I've had enough, I'm going to sleep.
I've had enough, I'm going to bed.
But what is this, Mr. Guignol?
What are you doing?
I'm going to bed.
But it's not a bedroom, it's a dining room.
Never mind, Miss Mireille, I'm tired, I'm going to bed.
Oh, that Mr. Guignol is unbearable.
Oh, to lie down in my dining room, no, no, really, listen, oh no.
Here, come out onto the balcony, I'll show you the view.
A breathtaking view.
Subtitles ST' 501
...
Annenberg Media
Subtitling by Radio-Canada