Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Thursday evening, Bélots' apartment.
That's Hubert. I recognize his ring of the doorbell.
Madame Bélot will open.
My respects, madam.
Hubert, what a pleasure to see you.
Thank you for your beautiful bouquet.
Please, madam, it's the least I can do.
I know you like roses.
You really shouldn't have.
Sir.
Good evening, Hubert.
Good evening.
Hello, you.
Good evening, Colette.
Good evening.
How are you ?
It's fine. You look as fresh as a daisy.
Mireille introduces Robert to Hubert.
Robert, Hubert.
Good evening.
Everyone to the table
And everyone heads towards the dining room
Let's see, Mr. Taylor is on my right.
Hubert is on my left.
Colette and Mireille next to Hubert
You, Marie-Laure, next to Dad
Everyone settles in.
Thank you Hubert
This deer.
A little more foie gras, Mr. Taylor.
I'd love that, it's delicious.
It was Mrs. Courtois' mother who did it herself.
Marie-Laure, please sit down, or you'll have to go to your room?
During the meal, Robert is a little surprised by Hubert's way of speaking.
Rest assured that I fully share your opinion, sir.
You have the kindness to believe me, dear lady.
Please pass me the salt.
Dear sir, please be aware that good wine can only be found in France.
Is there any good wine around Provins?
For great wines, you have to go a little further, all the way to Burgundy.
Yes, Beaune, Alex Corton, Nuit-Saint-Georges,
Bonne Romanée, Vougeot, Chambault-le-Musigny,
Geoffrey-Chambertin, Fixin.
Yes, yes, I know it very well.
Excellent, excellent.
If I understand correctly, miss, you live in Provence?
Yes, but I come to Paris often.
Almost every day, in fact.
I understand.
The provinces must be a bit boring.
Oh no, not at all.
You know, between Paris and the provinces,
Personally, I think I prefer the provinces.
I like Provence.
Provinces aside, I prefer Provence to Provins.
That's stupid
Marie-Laure, please be quiet, behave yourself
Oh, if we can't even laugh anymore now
Our villa is not very big
But we have a small garden with a few apple trees at the end
It's pleasant, you feel at home, behind the wings, the walls, the gate
It's the countryside, and yet I'm in Paris in an hour or more
So, how's the construction going? Is business good?
Oh, don't even mention it to me.
My uncles are in charge of it, but they're not doing anything particularly fascinating.
We did quite a few interesting things.
Look at La Défense, Beaubourg, La Villette, the Palais Omnisport de Bercy, the Opéra de la Bastille, the Grand Louvre, the Forum des Halles.
But they, my uncles, they only build rabbit hutches, council flats, workers' housing.
You know the type.
What do you want?
Nowadays, it's only for the working class.
The workers want to have mains drainage, running water, central heating, gas, electricity, all modern comforts.
They need dishwashers, refrigerators, vacuum cleaners, televisions, lives of garbage.
But only 100 years ago, all these people lived 10 to a room without lighting, with water from a pump and the toilets at the bottom of the yard.
He managed very, very well without a bathtub or bidet.
He wasn't any more unhappy because of it
Robert couldn't help but intervene
He wasn't any more unhappy because of it?
That's what you say, sir.
I'm not so sure about that
I'd like to see you, ten to a room in a filthy hovel.
Without your daily bath or shower
Without your phone, your elevator, or your servants
I'm not sure you'd be that happy about that.
Know that the working class has the same rights to comfort
than the descendants of the oppressors of the Middle Ages.
Regarding the Middle Ages,
Did you go see the exhibition?
Carolingian manuscripts at the Petit Palais?
Today, we are getting to know Hubert.
Here he comes.
That's Hubert.
I recognize his ringing of the doorbell.
Marie-Laure recognizes him immediately, even without seeing him, just from his ringing of the doorbell, which is unlike any other.
Hubert is not like everyone else. First of all, he is very polite, excessively polite even.
My respects, madam.
My compliments, oh, that sounds very nice, very distinguished. My compliments go with the kiss.
Look.
Are we leaving already?
Yes, it's sorted, it's sorted.
Allow me, I will now pay my respects to the lady.
My respects, madam.
Hubert, what a pleasure to see you.
Thank you for your beautiful bouquet.
But please, madam, it's the least I can do.
I know you like roses.
But really, you shouldn't have.
But please, madam, it's the least I can do.
I know you like roses.
Ah, Hubert has very good manners.
Good manners are very important.
Madame Belleau is very particular about good manners.
Marie-Laure doesn't always have very good manners.
Here, do you remember?
It's American!
Come on, Marie-Laure, will you be polite? What's with these manners?
She doesn't always have very good table manners.
Marie-Laure, please sit down, or you'll have to go to your room?
Look, she's not standing properly, she's standing badly.
Marie-Laure, hold on tight
She is not polite.
How stupid he is!
Marie-Laure, please be quiet. Sit down.
Shut up.
Be quiet.
Stop talking.
There are circumstances in which one should not speak.
We must remain silent.
In the cinema, for example.
Because it bothers others. Observe.
I'll draw you a little picture.
But be quiet now.
Chut!
Those two aren't going to shut up anytime soon.
Because there are some ill-mannered people out there, after all.
Chut!
Be quiet. Listen.
Hush, hush, be quiet. Listen.
Be quiet for a bit.
Marie-Laure is sometimes ill-mannered, but Hubert, on the other hand, is very well-mannered, very polite, very distinguished.
He speaks well, very well, in a somewhat pretentious, mannered, affected way.
For example, he doesn't say "okay" or "I agree".
No, he said, rest assured that I completely share your opinion.
Rest assured that I fully share your opinion, sir.
Be sure, be, that's the imperative of the verb to be.
Or, he doesn't simply say, believe me, but please be kind enough to believe me, dear lady.
Please be kind enough to believe me.
Please believe me
Would you be so kind as to believe me, dear lady?
"Ayez" is the imperative form of the verb "avoir" (to have).
Don't be afraid, miss
He didn't say either
Can you pass me the salt?
But please be so kind as to pass me the salt, miss.
Please be so kind
Please be so kind as to pass me the salt
Please pass me the salt, miss.
Please, this is the imperative form of the verb "to want".
He also said, "Know that there is no good wine except in France."
Remember that good wine can only be found in France.
"Sachez" is the imperative form of the verb "savoir".
You should know that good wine only comes from France.
Hubert is a bit of a chauvinist.
They think everything is better in France, especially the wines.
In France, there are good wines. In other countries, there are no good wines.
Are there good wines in Spain?
Yes !
Hubert said no. There are only good wines in France.
Are there good wines in Norway? No.
Are there good wines in Germany? No.
Are there good wines in England? No.
No, no, no, no, there are only good wines in France.
In France only, nowhere else but in France.
Robert tries to make conversation with Colette.
If I understand correctly, miss, you live in Provence?
Yes, but I come to Paris often. Almost every day, in fact.
I understand. Life in the provinces must be a bit boring.
Oh no, not at all. You know, between Paris and the provinces, I think I prefer the provinces.
It is important to know that France is divided into two parts.
Paris and the provinces.
Toulouse is in the provinces. Lyon is in the provinces. Bordeaux is in the provinces. Brest is in the provinces. Marseille is in the provinces. Paris is Paris. But the provinces are the provinces.
It is sometimes said that Paris is more lively, more interesting, and that the provinces are a bit boring, a bit dead.
But there are many people who prefer the provinces, because it is calmer, more peaceful, more picturesque.
Colette, for example, prefers the provinces.
You know, between Paris and the provinces, I think I prefer the provinces. I like the provinces.
Province for province, I prefer Provence to Provins.
That's stupid.
Marie-Laure laughed because she understood.
She understood Hubert's wordplay.
She's not stupid, that little girl.
Come on, Colette likes Provins and the provinces.
Provins is in the provinces.
Okay, but there are a lot of provinces.
Alsace is a province.
Burgundy is a province. Normandy is a province. Aquitaine is a province. And Provence is also a province.
If he had to choose between Provins and Provence, Hubert would choose Provence.
Note that Provins isn't bad. It's quite a pretty little town, rather picturesque.
There are very old monuments like this tower which dates back to Roman times
It's a rather pretty provincial town
So, it's a province, but it's a rather pleasant province.
But obviously the provinces aren't bad either.
There is sunshine, olive trees, and fountains.
There are small picturesque villages, hilltop villages with old houses, the beautiful ones of Provence, there are old churches, bell towers, squares with plane trees, people playing boules, flowers, the sea.
Hubert prefers Provence, but Colette prefers Provins.
It's very close to Paris, but it's the countryside.
The city, the countryside.
In Provins, Colette lives in a villa, a house with a garden around it. Here's a small villa. Here are some villas. There's a garden with flowers, vegetables, and apple trees.
Apple trees at the end of the garden, at the back of the garden.
We feel at home because the garden is enclosed by hedges, gates, and walls.
A grid, a grid, a grid, a wall, a wall, a wall and a grid.
A hedge, hedges
It's the countryside, and yet I can be in Paris in an hour at most.
It takes her one hour to get to Paris.
Look at Marie-Laure here
She made this drawing in five minutes.
It took her five minutes to make this drawing.
Oh, that's very good.
Did it take you a long time to do that?
Oh, I can do that in five minutes.
Now, listen carefully to the conversation between Robert and Colette.
Then, you will answer Robert as if you were Colette.
If I understand correctly, miss, you live in Provence?
Yes, but I come to Paris often, almost every day in fact
I understand, the provinces must be a bit boring
Oh no, not at all
You know, between Paris and the provinces, I think I prefer the provinces.
Now, try to answer as if you were Colette.
If I understand correctly, miss, you live in Provence?
Yes, but I come to Paris often.
Almost every day, in fact
I understand
The provinces must be a bit boring
Oh no, not at all
Oh no, not at all.
You know, between Paris and the provinces, I think I prefer the provinces.
Mr. Belleau brings the conversation to the topic of construction.
So, how's the construction going?
We're doing some interesting things in the field of construction.
Beaubourg, the Forum des Halles, La Défense, Marne-la-Vallée.
Beaubourg, the Opéra de la Bastille, that's very good.
The Forum is less aesthetically pleasing in terms of architecture.
And what about the Bercy Omnisport Arena?
It's very pretty.
I don't dislike the architecture.
But the Pinochambre construction company isn't doing anything interesting.
Nothing interesting, look at Marie Laure, she turns off the TV because there's nothing interesting on.
What's this? Meh, nothing interesting, the Pinot Chambrun construction company
only builds social housing, low-rent housing, cheap housing
For the workers. The workers, the people who work with their hands. The social housing, these apartments
Workers, it's not interesting from an architectural point of view. They're rabbit hutches. That
They look like rabbit hutches, chicken coops. They're not very attractive. But they are comfortable.
There is electricity, mains drainage, running water, central heating.
In the past, workers had no comforts.
They lived in slums without lighting or electricity.
He used kerosene lamps for light. He didn't have running water. He had to fetch water from the pump. He didn't have a toilet in the house. He had to go outside. The outhouses were in the courtyard, at the back of the courtyard.
At the very bottom, at the end. Do you remember?
The miners work at the bottom of the mine.
Submarines travel along the seabed.
There's a little wine at the bottom of the glass.
There are villages at the bottom of the valley.
Here is a village at the bottom of the valley.
The boy is at the back of the room.
The staircase is at the back of the courtyard. Listen.
Edward, the small door at the back on the left. Hurry up.
In the past, workers had no comforts.
But today, they need washing machines, dishwashers,
refrigerators, vacuum cleaners, televisions, garbage chutes, garbage disposal systems, sinks, bidets, showers, bathtubs for taking baths.
They need all of that
They need all modern comforts
They want all the modern comforts
He demands it, they need it
Observe Myriam here
She is very demanding.
He needs a whole bunch of things
He needs a book
He needs a sheet of paper
He needs a pencil
Hey, can you pass me that book?
Give me that sheet of paper.
I need a pencil. Won't you get me one?
What else do you need? Do you need anything else?
Hubert isn't really serious.
He is playing a role. He is playing the role of the reactionary aristocrat.
In the past, workers had no comforts, but they lived very well without them.
They weren't any more unhappy because of it.
They managed very, very well without a bathtub or bidet.
They didn't have all the modern comforts, but they weren't unhappy.
Observe what Mr. Bellou says here.
We are not rich, we only have one car, but we are not any less unhappy for it.
I wish we were as rich as Uncle William.
Meh, but why is that?
Because he has two cars and we only have one.
But I'm not any more unhappy about it, am I?
Robert is outraged.
He wants to intervene, to stop Hubert.
And he finally intervened.
He can't help but intervene.
Look at the girl here.
She wants to prevent the young man from intervening.
Robert can't help but intervene
Look at Marie-Laure, she wants to scratch herself.
She can't stop scratching herself.
Stop scratching
I can't help it
Robert can't help but intervene
Then, he intervenes
He wasn't any more unhappy because of it?
That's what you say, sir.
I'm not so sure about that
I would like to see you, living ten to a room in a filthy hovel, without your daily bath or shower, without your telephone, your elevator or your servants.
I'm not sure you'd be that happy.
Know that the working class has the same rights to comfort as the descendants of the oppressors of the Middle Ages.
Robert accuses Hubert of being a descendant of the oppressors of the Middle Ages.
The oppressors of the Middle Ages were the great lords who had all the rights and who oppressed the poor people.
In a modern democracy, everyone has the same rights.
The workers have the same rights as Hubert from our bedrooms.
Madame Bello skillfully diverts the conversation.
Speaking of the Middle Ages, did you go see the exhibition of Carolingian manuscripts at the Petit Palais?
This is the Petit Palais where exhibitions are held.
And here are Carolingian manuscripts, that is to say from the time of Charlemagne, around the 8th century.
Okay, now let's see what we can say.
Listen, watch, think, and speak.
Well, first of all, you are a man, a very distinguished gentleman, very polite.
You meet a lady, you kiss her hand, and what do you say?
You say...
My respects, madam.
There you go, that's very good.
Now, Hubert, that charming boy, has given you a magnificent bouquet of roses.
You thank him. What do you say?
You say...
Thank you for your beautiful bouquet.
Again.
Now, you are Hubert. What is your answer?
Please, madam, it's the least I can do.
Again.
"Now, your daughter is very nice, but she is a little ill-mannered."
So, your daughter leaves the table and she's not sitting properly. What do you say? What do you say?
"Please be quiet, behave yourself."
"Again."
"According to Hubert, who's a bit of a chauvinist, you know, is there good wine everywhere?"
No, good wine is only found in France.
Mr. Courtois is absent today.
He is not in Paris and he is not abroad.
Where is he?
He is in the provinces.
Is this the city or the countryside?
This is the countryside.
Where does Colette live?
In an apartment or in a villa?
In a villa.
In your opinion, is this a worker or an oppressor from the Middle Ages?
A worker.
Is that a sink or a garbage chute?
A sink.
Do you think that in the villages of Bélots you have to fetch water from a pump or that they have running water?
They have running water.
But of course we have running water, we have running water, we have gas, electricity, we have central heating, a bathroom with a bathtub, a shower, a refrigerator, a television, a vacuum cleaner, a dishwasher, a garbage chute, and there you go, we can be a little bit more at ease.
MFP subtitles.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
culture and communication, the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust and the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Pour information about this and other Annenberg Media programs,
call 1-800-LEARNER and visit us at www.learner.org.