Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Thursday evening, we're still at the table at the Bélots' house.
Colette, would you like some more foie gras? You do enjoy it.
Colette has run out of bread. Marie-Laure, please go and get some bread.
Rents must be expensive in this area.
Yes, quite a lot. But we don't rent. We own a condominium.
We bought the apartment about twenty years ago.
Each owner pays their share for heating, caretaker salaries, maintenance, repairs, and periodic facade cleaning.
But overall, even with all the expenses, it's more economical than renting.
Yes, of course, property ownership has its advantages.
But it's becoming hellish.
So, my family once owned an estate in Vendée, a small castle in Touraine, another in Burgundy with some vines, a manor house in Brittany, a hunting lodge in Sologne, a farmhouse in Provence, a chalet in the Alps, a nice little almshouse in Périgord and a cottage in Normandy.
But now it has become impossible
With taxes
And above all, the lack of servants
Because, let's face it, we're no longer being served.
How right you are, my dear friend!
Would you please pass me the salt?
We don't have any problems with domestic staff.
It must be said that we do not have a large estate
But we still have a small house in the countryside.
which serves as our second home, near Dreux.
It was a small peasant's house.
which was in very poor condition when we bought it.
The doors wouldn't close, and there were no more panes of glass in the windows.
We did all the repairs ourselves.
Almost all the roof tiles had to be replaced.
Everything had to be repainted, everything had to be reupholstered.
We trained the masons, the mold makers, the carpenters,
plumbers, painters.
The whole family worked.
It took us two years to make it habitable.
We had the water brought in and the electricity installed.
The barn was converted into a garage.
That wasn't the hardest part.
All you had to do was drop an N and add an A.
Oh, stop. Stop with your absurd wordplay.
What is an absurd pun?
Grange, garage.
You have barn, the word barn, and you want to make a garage.
You remove an N and add an A. You see?
Non.
Go get your Scrabble, I'll show you.
Marie-Laure gets up.
Madame Belleau reprimands her.
Marie-Laure, what are you doing? Would you mind sitting down?
Dad told me.
Ah good.
So, you aggregate, you remove an N, you add an A, and you make a garage.
So.
Is that it?
It wasn't difficult, was it?
Meanwhile, Ms. Belleau continues her conversation with Robert.
This has become very common lately.
City people are buying old peasant houses,
They modernize them and use them as second homes.
They come here for the weekend.
I find it sad to see farmers being driven out of their old houses.
But we're not chasing anyone away.
These are old, abandoned houses that are mostly falling into ruin.
In any case, we earned our house.
We worked really hard on it and it's definitely ours.
At that moment, a doorbell rings.
I think someone rang the bell.
Marie-Laure, would you please go and see?
Marie-Laure gets up and leaves the room.
Hello, little one.
Would you like some tickets from your handsome friend?
Ah, no, no.
Ah yes, that's what I want.
Very nicely.
Non !
A moment later, she returns.
What was it?
A nun.
What did she want?
She wanted to sell me lottery tickets to win an old 16th-century priory.
What's this all about? And what did you do?
I told him that we weren't interested, that we already had a second home
and that with the taxes and the lack of domestic staff, that was enough as it was.
Marie-Laure
What? That's not true?
But you should have called me, come on, that poor nun
Well, it wasn't a real one.
How so ?
No, she was a fake nun.
How do you know?
She had a mustache
That's not a reason
They must be nuns with moustaches.
Maybe, yes
Aunt Amélie has a moustache
But she had a mustache like that
Bizarre
Bizarre.
Today, the main topic of discussion is the Bélots' apartment.
and their second home.
The Bélots live at 18 rue de Vaugirard, in an apartment.
They are not tenants.
If you don't have a car, you can rent one.
You remember that Robert rented a car to go to Provins.
When you don't have a house, you can rent a house or an apartment.
You remember that the Bélots rented a holiday home in Brittany.
When you rent a house or an apartment, you are a tenant.
When you are a tenant, you have to pay the rent every month.
You need to send a check to the landlord for the rent.
The Bélots do not pay rent because they are not tenants, they are owners.
The apartment belongs to them. They don't pay rent, but they do pay building fees. They pay for the building's heating, for repairs, for the periodic cleaning of the facade, and for the caretakers' salaries. The caretakers are the concierge or concierge.
Every month, the owners, or rather the co-owners of the building, have to pay the caretaker, the concierge.
According to Mr. Bello, even with these expenses that must be paid, it is more advantageous to be an owner than a tenant.
But overall, even with all the expenses, it's more economical than renting.
Yes, of course, property ownership has its advantages.
But it's becoming hellish.
My family once owned an estate in Vendée, a small castle in Touraine, another in Burgundy with some vineyards, a manor house in Brittany, a hunting lodge in Sologne, a farmhouse in Provence, a chalet in the Alps, a charming cottage in Périgord and a cottage in Normandy.
Hubert lists a whole bunch of properties and estates that his family supposedly owned all over France.
In Normandy, Brittany, Vendée, Touraine, Burgundy, and Sologne
In Provence
In the Alps
In the Périgord
Obviously, when Hubert lists all his properties, all his beautiful estates, he's having a little fun.
He plays a role, the role of a descendant of a great aristocratic family.
Marie-Laure takes him seriously, but he's not entirely serious; he might be exaggerating a little.
This small castle in Touraine, for example, is the Château de Chambord, built in the 16th century by King Francis I.
It now belongs to the State and has never, to my knowledge, belonged to the Pinot-Chambre family.
A manor house, a country house, these are small castles, the home of a gentleman.
The mask is the typical house of Provence.
And the chalet is the typical wooden house of the Alps.
These are chalets in the Alps.
Old peasant chalets.
And modern chalets for second homes.
So, in the past, the Dubert family owned a whole bunch of properties.
But now, that's no longer possible.
Yes, of course, property ownership has its advantages.
But it's becoming hellish.
It is no longer possible to own properties.
It's too difficult. It's horrible, awful.
It's hell. It's becoming infernal.
This has become impossible for two reasons.
First, because of taxes, property taxes.
We need to give money to the state every year.
It's very expensive.
And then, the other reason is the lack of servants.
In the past, people had servants.
We had servants who waited on you.
Today, there are no more servants to serve you.
We are no longer being served.
Courteous people have a good servant, yes, but it's rare.
And besides, today's maids don't work like they used to.
Because, let's face it, we're no longer being served.
Here, look.
Aline ! Aline ! Aline !
It's incredible how badly they can serve you.
Excuse me, madam.
The Belleaus, however, have no servants at all. They don't have a maid.
Fortunately, they have Marie-Laure.
Marie-Laure, please go and get some bread.
Yes.
I think someone rang the doorbell. Marie-Laure, would you please go and see?
Hey, would you mind passing the book over there?
THANKS.
Are you going to get me a pencil?
Oh dear, hey, I'm not your maid, am I?
If you want a pencil, you go get it yourself.
Oh dear, it has to be said, we're no longer being served.
Hey, no, we're not being served anymore.
You have to do everything yourself.
When you only have a small apartment, like Aunt Georgette,
It's still okay, we can manage.
But when you have a rather large house,
When you have multiple properties, this is no longer possible.
We can't do it.
We don't have any problems with domestic staff.
It must be said that we do not have a large estate.
But we still have a small house in the countryside.
which serves as our second home.
The Bélots have this apartment in Paris. It is their main residence.
And then, they also have a small house in the countryside.
That's their second home.
They use it as a second home for holidays and weekends.
It was a small peasant's house that was in very poor condition that we bought.
Peasants.
A peasant's house in Vendée.
A peasant's house in the Pyrenees.
A peasant's house in Burgundy.
A house in poor condition.
Another house in poor condition.
A house in very poor condition.
A house in very, very bad condition, in ruins.
And there you have it, a ruined castle.
And here's a car in very bad condition.
When the Bélots bought this house, it was in very bad condition.
The doors wouldn't close.
Doors are made to close, aren't they?
I close the door.
That's a door that closes properly.
But the doors of the Bélots' house did not close, or closed poorly.
They needed to be repaired.
There were no panes of glass in the windows.
Normally, there are panes of glass in the windows.
There are windows here.
You can see the reflection in the windows.
But in the Bélots' house, there were no panes of glass in the windows, or they were broken.
They had to be replaced.
The roof tiles also had to be replaced.
Many tiles were broken. They had to be replaced.
Everything had to be repainted.
These are some painters.
The walls needed to be wallpapered again and again.
The Bélots did everything themselves.
They repainted it themselves.
They became painters.
That gentleman is a painter.
He's a painter, a real painter.
But is Mr. Bélot a painter?
No, he is not a painter.
He is an engineer at Renault.
But he's a painter.
He's not a bricklayer, but he does the bricklaying. He does all kinds of trades. Bicycles created painters, bricklayers, and carpenters. There's a carpenter. And there are the joiners. Carpenters build the frameworks.
Bicycles made the plumbers
A plumber
Bicycles are not carpenters or plumbers.
But they did the plumbing.
Look at Marie-Laure there
She's playing airplane
Is Marie-Laure an airplane?
No, but she's doing the airplane thing.
Be quiet for a bit, there's no way to work
Stop acting like an idiot
I'm not acting like an idiot, I'm acting like an airplane
The locals had the water brought in and they had the electricity installed.
They had the water turned on.
There was no water in that house, so the people had water brought in.
They didn't do it themselves.
They called in workers, specialists who brought in the water.
The locals had the water brought in, the workers brought the water.
There was no electricity either, so the locals had electricity installed.
They didn't install the electricity themselves; it's too dangerous.
They brought in specialists, electricians.
They worked hard to make the house habitable.
When they bought it, it was not habitable, it was uninhabitable.
Now it is habitable.
They made it habitable.
It was a lot of work.
It took them two years to make it habitable.
It took them two years.
It took us two years to make it habitable.
We had the water brought in and the electricity installed.
The barn was converted into a garage.
There was a barn, because it was a peasant's house.
A barn for storing hay.
The Bélots didn't need a barn, but they did need a garage for their car.
So, they converted the barn into a garage.
Easy, said Mireille.
That wasn't the hardest part. All you had to do was drop Anne and add an A.
Look.
You have barn, the word barn, and you want to make a garage.
You remove an N and add an A. You see?
Non.
Marie-Laure can't see. She doesn't understand.
You agranges, you remove an N, you add an A, you agarrages. There you go.
You remove an N. You remove. It's the verb to remove.
Look, I put on my glasses, I take off my glasses.
Look, he's taking off his glasses.
He takes off his cap.
She takes off her sweater.
There is redness on the cheek.
Wait, I'll take it off for you.
Yes, wait.
Okay, so the Bélots live in Paris, on rue de Vaugirard, in an apartment.
They are the owners.
This is their main residence.
They also have a house in the countryside.
They own this house too.
It belongs to them. They bought it.
This house in the countryside serves as their holiday home.
This has become very common lately.
City people are buying old peasant houses,
They modernize them and use them as second homes.
They come here for the weekend.
Robert, imagine poor peasants being driven from their homes by city people.
But Mireille reassures him.
But we're not chasing anyone away.
But him, yes, we'll chase him away.
But we don't drive out the peasants.
These are old, abandoned houses that are mostly falling into ruin.
Okay, let's see, we'll ask this lady where she lives and if she has a second home.
Which neighborhood do you live in?
I live in the fifth arrondissement, not far from this garden.
Do you live in a villa?
I live in a building, in an apartment.
Are you a homeowner?
No, I am renting the apartment.
Which neighborhood do you live in? In the 4th arrondissement, near, in the Marais. Do you own your home? Yes. Is it a house? It's an apartment. So you're a co-owner? Yes, exactly. Are the maintenance fees high?
Yes, quite a lot, because there is construction work.
Which neighborhood do you live in?
In the 15th arrondissement.
Are you a homeowner?
Yes.
Is the rent expensive?
I don't pay rent because I own my home.
So you pay taxes?
Yes.
Are you in a condominium?
What do the charges include?
The concierge's salary, garbage collection, and maintenance work.
And do you own a second home?
Non.
Where are you going on vacation?
In the south of France, near Aix-en-Provence.
Since you don't have a second home, how do you manage?
I rent a house.
While the Bélots are talking about their second home, there's a knock at the door.
Marie-Laure will open.
What was it?
A nun.
What did she want?
She wanted to sell me lottery tickets to win an old 16th-century priory.
A priority.
Did Marie-Laure buy lottery tickets?
Non.
She said she wasn't interested.
I told him that we weren't interested.
Marie-Laure doesn't want to win an old 16th-century prayer book.
He's not interested.
She already has a second home.
A second home is enough.
With taxes, the lack of domestic staff, all that.
What's this all about? And what did you do?
I told him that we weren't interested.
That we already had a second home.
And that with the taxes and the lack of domestic staff, that was enough as it was.
Marie-Laure!
What? That's not true?
But you should have called me, come on, the poor nun.
Well, it wasn't a real one.
How so ?
No, she was a fake nun.
How do you know?
She had a mustache.
She wasn't a real nun.
Now that, yes, is a real good nun.
But no, that's not a real nun.
Do you see the mustache?
Okay, now listen carefully to the dialogue between Marie-Laure and her mother about the nun.
Next, you will answer Mrs. Belleau as if you were Marie-Laure.
But you should have called me, come on, the poor nun.
Well, it wasn't a real one.
How so ?
No, she was a fake nun.
How do you know?
She had a mustache.
Now, answer as if you were Marie-Laure.
But you should have called me, come on, the poor nun.
Well, it wasn't a real one.
How so ?
No, she was a fake nun.
And how do you know that?
She had a mustache.
Now let's see what you have retained.
Listen, watch, think, and speak.
The Belleaux have a very nice apartment on rue de Vaugirard, but they don't pay rent.
Why don't they pay rent?
Because they own the property.
The caretaker, who is she? Do you know who she is?
She's the concierge.
In your opinion, is this a chalet in the Alps or a house in Provence?
A chalet in the Alps.
Is that a Norman cottage or a Provençal mass?
It's more of a Provençal mass.
In your opinion, is Mr. Bello working as a bricklayer or a carpenter here?
He's a bricklayer.
And here, is he playing the painter or the plumber?
The painter.
Look closely. Are the Bellos having water brought in or electricity installed?
They are having the water brought in.
And is that a barn or a garage?
A barn.
Warning, this is going to be very difficult.
To convert a barn into a garage, do you need to add an N or remove an N?
We need to remove an N.
Look at this house.
In summary, is it habitable or is it in poor condition?
It's in bad condition. It's in very bad condition.
Everything needs to be repaired. Everything needs to be done.
Mr. Guignol, it's cold.
Would you like to turn on the heating, please?
Mr. Guignol, the windows are dirty.
You can't even see the Moparnasse tower anymore.
Would you please wash the windows, Mr. Guignol?
Mr. Guignol, the living room walls are dirty.
Would you like to repaint them, please?
In pink, please, Mr. Guignol.
Mr. Guignol, it's raining in my room.
The roof tiles will need to be replaced, please.
Oh dear, this is becoming hellish.
We're not even being served anymore
Hey, Mr. Guignol, wake up!
Oh, hey, gently, gently
You can see that I'm asleep, can't you?
Subtitles ST' 501
and other Annenberg Media programs,
call 1-800-LEARNER
and visit us at www.learner.org.