Subtitles ST' 501
and fly away.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few things
In French, yourself.
Yes.
The door of the door, once again.
Marie-Laure reports that there was a man dressed in black
who asked if she had a sister
who resembled an actress.
She sent it, and Mireille is angry.
Perhaps that was his big chance.
At the same time, Robert tries, in vain,
to arrange the workroom at Belle-Ôse.
Thursday evening, we're still at the table at the Bélots' house.
In that respect, we can say that we worked on this street house.
Oh la la!
That's probably why I became so attached to it.
The bell rings again. Everyone stops eating and talking.
Marie-Laure will open.
I wonder what it could be.
So, what was it?
The brother of the nun from earlier.
What is this all about?
Yes, he had the same moustache as her.
And what did he want?
He asked me if I had an older sister who looked like a movie actress.
And what did you say?
Well, that question. I said no, of course.
What nerve! It might have been the chance of a lifetime to make films.
Now, it's a failure.
Finally
That's really weird
It's true, I wanted to be an actress for a long time.
I dreamed of going to Hollywood
Playing the unknown woman on the Orient Express
Traveling, staying in luxury hotels
Now I don't know
It's crazy how attached I've become to our country house.
When I was little
I found this desire of many French people ridiculous.
To have a small house of their own
The kind of thing that's my dream, my rest
And now, as I get older
I'm starting to understand
Having your own little house
Even if it is very modest
I see
A cottage and a heart
Our house isn't really a cottage.
First, the roof is not thatched, but tiled
Oh, de la tuile ?
Wouldn't you prefer slate?
Personally, I find it so much more distinguished.
Ah, slate is very pretty, but it's more expensive.
And besides, it must be nice and heavy.
It's lighter than the tile
But obviously, that would be too heavy for your wooden houses
Why do you say our houses are made of wood?
You don't have a wooden house in France?
No, very few. A few chalets in the mountains.
But apart from that, we're building with solid materials.
Made of stone, bricks, or cement blocks.
In France, we like things that last.
Is your country house made of solid materials?
Of course, it's beautiful local stone.
And the walls are at least two or three hundred years old.
And I fully expect them to still be standing for my great-grandchildren.
You cannot have great-grandchildren.
And why is that?
You're too young, you're not even married.
I read in Le Monde that there are more than 300,000 students in Paris.
Where do they live?
Well, it depends.
Those who are lucky enough to have their parents in Paris, like Mireille
They generally live in their own homes, of course.
And what about foreigners?
Some live in the university residence.
Most foreign countries have a house in the city.
Others stay in hotels or rent rooms from private individuals.
Some of them live with families.
They have their own room, a bathroom.
They eat their meal with the family.
A single meal or full board.
I thought French families were very closed off.
That's quite true in a way.
But there are people who take in foreign students.
Because they have an apartment that is too big for them,
that they need money, widowed ladies, pensioners.
There are also people who want to give their children foreign friends.
The Belleau family would not, by chance, intend to receive strangers.
You know, we don't have a big apartment, we only have this one room.
Including the kitchen and bathroom.
I am neither a widow nor a retiree.
And Mireille doesn't need anyone to find her foreign friends.
She collects them.
In one year of university, she managed to meet a Canadian, a Chilean,
An Algerian woman, an Israeli man, a Syrian woman, a Tunisian man, an Egyptian man,
An Italian woman, a Japanese woman, a Danish woman.
Three English people, one German woman, two Americans and one Romanian man.
A Hungarian, a Turk, a Greek, a Spaniard, a Russian and a Swiss.
And you're forgetting a Swede.
Mireille talks about their country house.
She is very attached to it because she worked there a lot.
We can say that we worked on that street house.
Oh la la!
That's probably why I became so attached to it.
She has grown attached to this house. She loves it very much.
Attached has first and foremost a concrete meaning.
For example, the cowboy ties up his horse.
Whether in a plane or a car, you must fasten your seatbelt.
Please fasten your seatbelts.
In Greek mythology, Prometheus was chained to a rock.
They are tied up.
The goat is tied up too.
And then, there is a moral dimension.
Mireille is attached to her country house, not physically, but morally.
She loves him, she loves him very much.
She is very attached to her little sister, she loves her very much.
Marie-Laure is very attached to Uncle Guillaume, she likes him a lot.
It has to be said that he spoils her a lot.
She is very close to her uncle.
Aunt Georgette is very fond of Fido.
It's true, we do get attached to these little creatures.
Listen again to what Mireille says.
In that respect, we can say that we worked on this street house.
Oh la la!
That's probably why I became so attached to it.
That's why I became so attached to it.
It really highlights the intensity.
Yes, you're right, people are so stupid.
"Why did you set fire to my cognac? It's so much nicer. Oh! It's so much nicer. Oh!"
"Oh, I would love to know the trick. Oh, I would love to know the trick."
You remember that in high school, there is a lot of material to study.
There is so much material that we don't have time to do art history.
"There are so many other subjects to study."
While Mireille is talking about her attachment to their country house, the doorbell rings.
Marie-Laure gets up and goes to see what it is.
I wonder what it could be.
Marie-Laure returns, very calm, and goes to sit down again.
So, what was it?
The brother of the nun from earlier.
What is this all about?
It's simple.
The doorbell rang a little while ago.
And Marie-Laure went to see, it was a nun, a funny nun actually, with a big black mustache.
A strange nun who was offering lottery tickets.
This time, it's not the sister, but someone who looks like her.
A man with a big black mustache, like the one our sister had earlier.
So, it must be his brother.
It must be the sister's brother.
That's clear, isn't it?
Okay, now listen carefully to the dialogue between Mrs. Belleau and Marie-Laure.
Next, you will try to explain things to Mrs. Belleau, who doesn't seem to understand very well.
So, what was it?
The brother of the nun from earlier.
What is this all about?
Yes, he had the same moustache as her.
Now, answer Mrs. Belleau as if you were Marie-Laure.
So, what was it?
The brother of the nun from earlier.
The brother of the nun from earlier
What is this all about?
Yes, he had the same mustache as her.
Yes, it's not bad.
But let's start again.
Pay close attention to the nun from earlier.
The brother of the nun from earlier
Let's go
So, what was it?
The brother of the nun from earlier
Top article
What is this all about?
Yes, he had the same mustache as her.
That ring of the doorbell, that was
the brother of the nun from earlier.
The nun from earlier.
Just now.
You remember that earlier
may have a past meaning.
Tout à l'heure means a short time ago.
That's recent history.
Here too.
Do you know the age of petrified water? Since when?
Since earlier.
And here too.
I called the courteous one earlier.
Or even here.
"Madam, it's the gentleman from earlier!"
"When I told her that Mom was looking for her earlier, it wasn't true. It was a joke."
But "tout à l'heure" can also mean "in a short time".
So it can indicate an immediate future, as in this example.
"Aren't you going to the museum?"
"Yes, if so, earlier."
"I'm leaving tomorrow. Well, in a little while. I'm leaving tomorrow. Well, in a little while."
The gentleman who just rang the bell asked Marie-Laure if she had a sister who looked like a movie actress.
He asked me if I had an older sister who looked like a movie actress.
Mireille was immediately interested.
And what did you say?
Well, I told him no, of course not, to that question.
Well, that question! What a stupid question! The answer is obvious.
What nerve! It might have been the chance of a lifetime to make films.
Now, it's a failure.
What nerve! Mireille is not happy.
She thinks Marie-Laure has a lot of nerve.
What nerve! What audacity!
Marie-Laure shouldn't have said that.
Look here.
It's Marie-Laure who thinks Mireille has some nerve.
because she took advantage of his absence to take his place.
Marie-Laure!
Yes !
Mom is calling you.
I know, I'm going.
Well, well, you've got some nerve! What nerve?
Come on, shoo, get out of here, this is my spot.
That's outrageous. Come on, get out of here. This is my spot.
It might have been the chance of a lifetime to make films.
Now, it's a failure.
The chance of a lifetime.
Mireille may have had a unique opportunity,
an opportunity to make films.
And now, it's a failure.
She lost that chance.
She missed the opportunity.
You can miss an opportunity, you can fail an exam.
Oh darn, I'm stuck.
You can mess up your life, you can also miss a train.
Mireille had long wanted to be an actress
Do you remember when she was little?
She wanted to be a nurse by day and an actress by night.
Do you know what I wanted to be when I was little?
I wanted to be a nurse and an actress
Nurse by day and actress by night
I dreamed of going to Hollywood
She dreamed, she imagined
She hoped to go to Hollywood
Playing the unknown woman on the Orient Express
A mysterious heroine on the Orient Express, the train that travels from Europe to the Orient.
A train full of mysteries and intrigue.
Watch this advertisement that plays on the myth of the Orient Express.
It was in January 1934, on the Orient Express, that I was going to meet the one I would never forget.
Of the woman I called the Oriental, all that would remain for me now would be an image and a scent.
L'Orientale, an unforgettable fragrance.
When she was little, Mireille dreamed of travelling, of staying in luxury hotels.
But now she's aged.
And she becomes like all those French people who dream of having a little house of their own.
To own a house, even a very modest one, even a very small one.
These little houses that are called my dream, my goal, destiny, that's life, my rest, my work, murmurs the waves.
Minouche, Robert is making fun of her.
I see a cottage and a heart.
I see. Your dream is the banal cliché: a cottage and a heart.
A thatched cottage is a very modest little house with a thatched roof.
In the past, there were many thatched cottages in the countryside.
But today, it has become very rare.
And a heart is the seat of love and other feelings.
A cottage and a heart, that's a dream of happiness
in a small, very modest house,
Even if you're poor, with someone you love.
Mireille protests.
Our house isn't really a cottage.
First, the roof is not thatched, but tiled.
There are essentially three types of roofs in France.
Thatched roofs, very rare today.
Next, the tiled roofs.
Tiled roofs are found mainly in the south of France.
That's a tiled roof.
And then there are the slates.
These are slate roofs.
Slate is lighter than tile, but it costs more.
It is considered more elegant than tile.
The roofs of castles are almost always made of slate.
The roofs of the houses are made of tiles or slate.
And the walls are solid.
That is to say, in stone, brick or cinder block, in cement block
Made of hard materials, like stone
Stone is hard
Many houses are made of stone
Castles and churches are also generally made of stone.
But we also build with bricks.
There are many brick houses.
And there are also old brick castles.
There are also some brick churches,
such as, for example, Albi Cathedral.
Many modern houses are also built out of cinder blocks and cement blocks.
But wood is not used much in construction, except for mountain chalets.
Generally, we build with permanent materials. That's the verb "to build".
Listen, let's see if you recognize the verb "to build".
My father was an architect and one day he built a villa by the sea for a famous surgeon.
We use wood for mountain chalets, but apart from that, we build with solid materials.
Apart from that, apart from the chalets, listen to Guylaine.
It's raining, I'm exhausted, but apart from that, it's fine.
In France, we build with durable materials because we like things that last, things that last a long time.
Stone is solid, it lasts a long time
Look at the Pont du Gard, it has lasted for almost 20 centuries, almost 2000 years.
The Carré house in Nîmes too
Stone lasts longer than wood
Roses are very pretty, but they don't last.
Chocolates don't last either.
Ebello's country house is solid, it's made of stone
And Mireille certainly hopes it will last a very long time.
Of course, it's beautiful local stone.
And the walls are at least two or three hundred years old.
And I hope they will still be standing for my great-grandchildren.
Stand up, remember?
Here, Mireille is standing
And here she is sitting
She is lying down here.
Standing
Sat
Lying down. Standing, sitting, standing, sitting, lying down. Standing, sitting.
So you work standing up then? Like me, you also work standing up.
Look at this wall, it's still standing. This piece of wall is still standing.
The Bélots' country house is very interesting, but Robert is more interested in housing for foreign students in Paris.
I read in Le Monde that there are over 300,000 students in Paris. Where do they live?
Well, it depends.
It depends. There are several cases, several possibilities.
First, there are the students whose parents live in Paris.
These people generally live with their parents.
It's simpler, it's more convenient, and above all, it's cheaper.
Mireille, for example, lives with her parents.
And then there are the international students.
That also depends.
There are foreign students who live in the university residence.
There are foreign students who live in the hotel.
They rent a room in a hotel, like Robert, for example.
And then there are also students who live with private individuals.
He rents a room from private individuals. A private individual could be Mr. Pellot or Aunt Georgette, for example, someone who is not a hotelier.
A hotelier rents rooms as a profession. A private individual can rent a room, but it is not their profession.
You can rent a room in a hotel or in a private house.
Similarly, there are taxis and there are private cars.
That's a taxi and that's a private car.
Let's see, let's ask this young girl if she is a student and where she lives.
Are you a student?
Yes, I'm at university.
Where do you live?
In the Parisian suburbs.
The university campus?
Are you renting a room?
Or do you live with your parents?
No, I live with my parents
There are many foreign students
Who live in families
At private homes
They take up residence with a family
They have a room with a toilet.
A toilet is a small bathroom
But without a bathtub
There is essentially a sink
and they have one or all meals with the family.
Half board or full board.
I thought French families were very closed off.
That's quite true in a way.
In a sense, that's somewhat true, but it's not entirely true.
There are many families who receive strangers
because they think it's good for the children.
It's interesting for their children to meet foreigners.
Sometimes also because they are alone in a large apartment,
a widowed lady, for example, or a retiree,
a gentleman who no longer works, who is retired.
Sometimes because they need money.
They don't have enough money.
Look at this poor man, he needs money.
Hey buddy, you wouldn't happen to have five bucks so I can fill it up, would you?
Look at Mireille here, she needs a book.
Hey, can you pass me that book?
And then, she needs a sheet of paper.
Give me that sheet of paper, over there.
And then, she needs a pencil.
I need a pencil. Won't you get me one?
What else do you need? Do you need anything else?
You are an artist.
I forgot.
What do you have against artists? We need them.
Tipou, you know I need you.
This conversation about foreign students staying with a family gives Robert some ideas.
The Bello family would not intend to receive strangers by chance.
But Ms. Bello disagrees.
First, their apartment isn't too big for them.
You know, we don't have a big apartment, we only have this one room.
Including the kitchen and bathroom.
And besides, Ms. Bello is not retired, since she still works at the Ministry of Health.
And she's not a widow either, since Mr. Bello is there.
He is not dead, he is still alive.
I am neither a widow nor a retiree.
And Mireille doesn't need anyone to find her foreign friends.
She collects them.
She has a lot of them.
She is very sociable.
She has many friends of all nationalities.
Oh well, never mind.
Robert will have to remain a Latin man.
Oh, that's a shame.
Now let's see what you have to say.
Look, listen, think, and speak.
Does Mireille hate her sister or is she attached to her?
She is attached to her.
Now, Marie-Laure will tell you something strange.
What are you saying?
What is this all about?
What did you say?
Your sister took your place while you were away.
You are outraged. What do you say?
Well, well, you've got some nerve! What nerve? Go on, get out!
Is this roof thatched or tiled?
Thatched.
Thatched, very nice. Is this roof slate or tile?
And tiles.
It's tiled, that's right. Is this roof thatched or slate?
Made of slate.
Slate roof. Are the walls here made of wood or stone?
Made of stone.
And here, are they made of wood or bricks?
Brick.
Made of brick, very good. And this chalet, is it made of wood or brick?
Made of wood, made of wood, is what Mireille is sitting, standing, or lying down, standing, standing?
Here, sitting, sitting, and here, lying down, lying down, and that's a taxi or a car.
A special car, a special car, in your opinion, that's...
a hotel or a private house a private house a private house
But what are you doing here, Mr. Guignol? I'm sleeping, Miss Mireille, but
No, Mr. Guignol, that's not right at all.
You can't sleep in my dining room.
You're dreaming.
Actually, Miss Mireille, I was dreaming.
I dreamt that I had a small, very modest house,
almost a cabbage patch, which was called my dream.
Yes, well, that's it.
Go sleep in the house of your dreams,
but not in my dining room.
Go away!
Oh no, we're not at home anymore.
MFP subtitles.
Subtitles ST' 501
the Ministry of Culture and Communication,
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.
French subtitles?