Subtitles ST' 501
and fly away.
Very soon, you will see what happens
and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
After afternoon drinks,
Everyone says hello, except Mireille and Robert.
They decide, after consulting the training guides,
to see the film "Love in the Afternoon"
the following day, “In the Afternoon”.
They stop to meet at a cafe near the theatre.
Thursday evening, at the Bélots' house, the meal finally comes to an end.
What if we went to the living room?
That's a very good idea.
Very good, it's delicious.
Do you want mint with a linden tree?
No, thank you.
And you, will you have your herbal tea?
Yes, please.
Perhaps you would like some alcohol, Mr. Taylor?
Yes of course.
I'll see what I have.
That's a lovely painting. Is it by a family member?
Yes, it's other people.
I have Grand Marnier and Cognac.
Colette, and you?
A small Grand Marnier.
A Grand Marnier.
THANKS.
Mireille, would you like something?
Yes, me too, a Grand Marnier.
Mr. Taylor, a Grand Marnier, please.
Yes, you have to try it, it's very, very good, you'll see.
Hubert, and you?
No, I prefer cognac, if you don't mind.
Ah, cognac.
It's very good, very, very good.
THANKS.
So.
Thank you, thank you.
To your health
I'm not taking anything
Do you want some alcohol, darling?
I raise my glass particularly
to the lady of the house
a cognac
Oh yes
He is very, very good.
hold
that's quite strong
It's getting late
Have you seen what time it is, Marie-Laure?
Yes
Go to bed, right now!
Say good evening
Good evening
Good evening, Marie-Laure
Good evening, the question
Good evening
Good evening, my dear
Will you come and say good evening to me?
Yes. Hurry up.
After kissing her parents goodbye, Marie-Laure went to bed.
Colette left around 11pm to return to Provins.
Oh yes, 11 o'clock.
I have to get out of here, I'm going to miss my train.
Goodbye, Hubert.
Bye.
Goodbye, Robert.
Good evening.
Hi, Colette.
Samirai, I'm calling you.
OK.
Good day sir.
Bye.
Goodbye, Colette.
Thank you very much, Mr. and Mrs. Bello. I believe they apologized shortly afterwards.
We should probably go to bed, yes, excuse us, we took
the habit of going to bed early
On Madam, tributes and thank you, sleep well, I hope we didn't
Too tired, they're having a delicious meal. Goodnight, Mom, you'll wake me up tomorrow.
Morning before leaving. Yes, darling. Good. Good evening. Good evening, Hubert. Finally, Hubert is taking his leave. It's after 11 p.m. Good evening, because I'm going to leave too.
So, shall we talk on the phone?
Sir...
Robert and Mireille are left alone.
I suppose it's too late to go to the cinema now.
No, I'm afraid of it.
But do you want us to go tomorrow morning?
Tomorrow morning?
No, morning, afternoon.
Yeah, if you want.
What are we going to see?
I don't know.
Do you see a periscope over there?
What is this ?
It's like the official show guide.
Hey, here's one.
This is a program of shows.
It's theatre, dance, cinema, exhibition, concert, in short, everything.
It shows all the films that are playing in Paris.
Classified by neighborhood and by genre.
By genre?
Because in France, even films are either masculine or feminine.
Oh, don't be an idiot. I mean, they're classified as adventure films, westerns,
dramatic comedies, psychological dramas, musicals, erotic films, animated films,
And there's even a short summary of each film. Really? What do you see that's interesting? Let's see.
What we're giving away this week. Nagisa Oshima's "The Ceremony," original version. How are we
Japanese? A bit rusty. What else? The Red Female Detachment, original version
Chinese, the great Yugoslav silence, be serious, I must be able to
to understand, but there are always subtitles
Here's an American slice, you think you'd understand? Oh, but that's not right, it's
Forbidden to those under 18, that's enough, that's enough anyway.
It's the one from last week, so what, so what, it's no longer good.
Programs change every week, let's check on the unit.
"Spends the afternoon on July 14th" by Nas, that's a beautiful title.
It must be very informative, but you know, I'm afraid you'll be disappointed.
One of Eric Romere's six moral tales, it doesn't matter, it must be very
Interesting, let's see. Do you want to go? Yes, okay, then let's meet at
1:30 pm on the rotunda terrace, it's right next door
You just have to take the metro and get off at Vavin, it's right across the street.
You can't go wrong, of course, so see you tomorrow, at... how do you say it?
La Rotonde, boulevard Montparnasse, metro 20-20.
Okay, at La Rotonde, at 1:30 pm.
I will have to understand you.
Okay, good evening.
The timer button is there, on the right. Do you see?
Where?
There, the little light.
To be ?
You have two minutes to get down.
Two minutes? Why?
Do I need to get down in two minutes?
What is this all about?
Yes, when you press the button,
The light stays on for two minutes, and then it goes off.
We're used to the way the economy works in France. You need to understand that.
Those French are crazy.
No, we're not crazy. We're saving energy.
Okay, hurry up, it's going to go out.
It will turn off.
Good evening.
It's after dinner.
After dinner,
There are people who drink coffee and sometimes alcohol such as cognac, armagnac, pear, raspberry or liqueurs.
Mr. and Mrs. Bello do not drink alcohol or liquor.
They also don't drink coffee or tea, because the caffeine keeps them awake.
They drink an infusion, a herbal tea, linden for example or verbena.
It's good in the evening, at bedtime, because it helps you sleep.
It's getting late. It's starting to get late.
It's getting late.
Madame Belleau sends Marie-Laure to bed. She sends her to bed.
Have you seen what time it is, Marie-Laure?
Yes.
Okay, off to bed.
Right away.
Robert is lying down here. He is in bed.
Here, Mireille is lying down, she is in bed
She is sick
Here, Marie-Laure is lying down, she is in bed
Mr. and Mrs. Bello are also going to bed
I think we should go to bed
Yes, excuse us, we've gotten into the habit of going to bed early.
Ah, I'm exhausted.
I'm going to bed
Okay, well, everyone's going to bed now.
Okay, everyone to bed
Good evening, everyone
Good evening
Goodnight, my dear, sleep well
Good evening madam, my respects and thank you, sleep well
Will you come and say good evening to me?
Yes, hurry up
Good evening
Mom, will you wake me up tomorrow morning before you leave?
You're going to sleep there
You will be very well
Good night
Mireille wants her mother to wake her up
Look at Jean-Claude here, he's falling asleep
And look at great-uncle Casimir, he's falling asleep.
Look at Marie-Laure, she's asleep.
Look at Robert, he's waking up.
A cup of coffee, madam.
Oh yes, I'd love that, it'll wake me up.
Now look at the little boy, he's going to wake up his dad.
Wake up, you're going to be late.
And here, it's the mother who gets woken up.
Mom, this is for you, Cécile. She said you needed to wake up.
Yes, hello, Cécile, what's going on?
Oh, but what time is it?
Ten past twelve, miss.
Please come back in one hour.
The belots have gotten into the habit of going to bed early.
Yes, excuse us, we've gotten into the habit of going to bed early.
They've gotten used to it.
He goes to bed early every night.
Mireille has gotten into the habit of buying her newspaper at Mrs. Rosa's.
Every morning, she buys her newspaper from Mrs. Rosa. It's a habit.
And you remember, Marie-Laure, she has a bad habit.
She should break that habit.
Oh, stop! Are you going to break that habit?
And you, are you going to stop bothering me?
Colette leaves around 11 p.m.
Oh dear, 11 a.m. I have to get out of here.
She ran away. Do you remember, Jean-Pierre?
I'm running away.
And Mireille?
Excuse me, I'm off.
She also said, I'm off.
Oh dear, excuse me, I'm off. I'm going to be late. Goodbye.
Colette is leaving to return to Provins.
She returns to Provins.
Excuse me, miss.
You remember that Robert met Mireille in the courtyard of the Sorbonne.
The next day, he returned to the Sorbonne.
He went back there.
Hubert takes his leave.
He's leaving.
I'm going to leave too.
Yes, I'm going to take some time off.
So, shall we talk on the phone?
Shall we talk on the phone?
Are you calling me?
Shall I call you?
Hello, is that you Guylaine?
Mireille calls Guylaine.
She calls him.
Hello, is that you Guylaine?
She calls Guylaine.
She calls him.
She calls him, she phones him.
Robert is not happy because it is late.
It's too late to go to the cinema.
I suppose it's too late to go to the cinema now.
No, I'm afraid of it.
But do you want us to go tomorrow morning?
Do you want to go to the cinema tomorrow?
Does Mireille say they are going to the cinema?
No, she doesn't say let's go.
She said, "Do you want to go?"
She's suggesting a possibility. She's talking about the possibility of going to the movies. She's not saying they're going. Do you want to go to the movies? "Aille" is a form of the verb "aller" (to go). It's the subjunctive mood of the verb "aller".
We already know the imperative mood, which gives an order: let's go to the cinema. We know the indicative mood, which indicates a fact, a real action: we are going to the cinema.
And now we have the subjunctive mood, which speaks of an action without indicating that it is real.
Do you want to go to the cinema? "Do you want to go to the cinema" does not indicate that they are going, have gone, or will go.
If you want us to go to the cinema, just talk about the possibility of going to the cinema.
Robert and Mireille want to go to the cinema.
Okay, very well, but where are they going to go?
What are they going to see?
What are we going to see?
I don't know.
It depends on what we're playing at the moment.
Hey, what are we showing at the film club tonight?
It depends on what we go through.
There are several ways to know what is happening.
The most modern way to get the programs is via Minitel.
And then there are the specialist publications, such as Paris Scope, the official entertainment guide, etc.
If you want to go to the cinema, what do you consult to find out the programs?
The newspapers. I read the newspapers.
Which newspapers?
Entertainment journals.
For example ?
Paris Scope.
The Paris Scope.
It includes all the shows, the theatre, all the plays currently being performed in Paris, the music, all the concerts of the week, the dance, the exhibitions,
Cinema, all the films showing in Paris this week
The films are classified by genre
Adventure, western, etc.
By genre?
Because in France, even films are either masculine or feminine.
Oh, but don't be an idiot.
Don't act like an idiot, don't be stupid
Here, it's Mireille who's acting silly.
And Marie-Laure doesn't like that
Hey, my gumballs!
What gumballs? There are no gumballs here.
Come on, don't be an idiot. Give me my gumballs.
Are there gumballs here? Impossible.
Come on, be serious.
Do you remember Marie-Laure who played the airplane?
And Mr. Bello was the bricklayer.
Mr. Bello is not really a bricklayer, but he acts like one.
Robert isn't really stupid, but he acts like an idiot.
Oh, but he's not being silly. I mean, they're categorized by adventure film.
There are all sorts of genres. Westerns, dramedies, psychological dramas, musicals, erotic films, cartoons.
What do you see that's interesting?
What do you see that's interesting? What is interesting about it?
"Do you see anything interesting? Do you see anything good? I'd like something fun. Something good, something fun. Something interesting, nothing interesting. Do you remember Hubert's uncles who run the construction company? They don't do anything interesting."
"They don't do anything particularly fascinating."
What else? There's nothing good.
What do you see that's interesting?
Mireille suggests a Japanese film.
What does it mean to be Japanese?
A little rusty.
Robert's Japanese is a bit rusty.
Not very good, not very functional.
Rust.
A rusty gate.
A rusty pump.
A rusty suit of armor.
Rusty, in poor condition.
Note that if Robert's Japanese is rusty,
It's not a problem, because there are always subtitles for films in their original version.
Mireille offers other foreign films in their original version.
Detachment, Red Feminine, original Chinese version.
The Great Silence, Yugoslavia.
Listen, be serious, I need to be able to understand.
Be serious.
Mireille is not serious.
She's having fun, she's joking around.
She offers her films in foreign languages ​​as a joke, for laughs. It's not serious.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's serious. But here, she's acting silly. She's not serious.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She hurt her fingers. But it's not serious. It's nothing to worry about.
Now, look at Marie-Laure here. She says she's in pain all over.
But Mireille thinks it's not serious. Mireille doesn't take it seriously.
Oh, my neck hurts, my fingers hurt, my legs hurt.
Oh dear, this looks very serious.
Marie-Laure does a little English at school, but it's not very serious.
I'm doing English, but it's not serious.
On apprend, why do you do, I'm very well, thank you, c'est tout.
And here, do you remember? Mireille is having fun, she's not serious.
Come on, don't be silly, give me my gumballs.
Are there gumballs here? Impossible.
Come on, be serious.
But I'm serious, I didn't see any gumballs.
Be serious, I need to be able to understand.
Be serious.
So, that's the imperative of the verb "to be".
You remember, Hubert? Be sure, my dear sir.
Rest assured that I fully share your opinion, sir.
Be serious, I need to be able to understand.
Observe.
"I can't understand. I can't understand Chinese or Japanese. That's a fact. That's the existing reality. Robert can't understand."
I need to be able to understand, I need to be able to understand, "can," that's the subjunctive.
Mireille suggests another film, but it is forbidden for people under 18 years of age.
Oh no, that's not right, it's forbidden for those under 18.
It's forbidden, no entry, you can't pass.
No entry, you cannot enter this street from this direction.
Parking is prohibited.
No entry to the lawn.
Display prohibited, it cannot be displayed.
Smoking is prohibited in this room.
Everything is forbidden.
We're showing an old Eric Romère film called Love in the Afternoon.
Robert likes the title.
That's a great title.
It must be very informative, it must be informative, we must be able to
learn a lot with this, the great universal dictionary, the redhead
For example, it's an informative book; you can learn a lot from it.
Robert might be disappointed; he might find the film less interesting than
Look at what he's imagining, this gentleman, he's going to be disappointed
You see, he's very disappointed, he's disappointed too. Oh, you know, I'm afraid you'll be disappointed too.
One of Eric Romere's six moral tales, that doesn't matter, it must be very interesting, let's go
Seeing that doesn't matter, oh well, it's not a big deal, it doesn't matter, just observe
I saw what time it is. It's too late to go to the cinema.
It doesn't matter, we'll go tomorrow.
A chicken, Mireille, please.
I'm sorry, madam, there are none left.
It doesn't matter. I'll have the duck breast.
Listen carefully to the conversation between Robert and Mireille about love in the afternoon.
Next, you will play the role of Robert.
Hey, we're spending the afternoon on love on July 14th by Nass.
Oh, that's a great title. It must be very informative.
Oh, you know, I'm afraid you'll be disappointed. It's one of Eric Romere's six moral tales.
It doesn't matter. It must be very interesting. Let's go see it.
Now, it's your turn. You are Robert.
Hey, we're spending the afternoon on love on July 14th by Nass.
Oh, that's a great title. It must be very informative.
Oh, that's a nice title.
That must be very informative.
Oh, you know, I'm afraid you'll be disappointed.
This is one of Eric Romere's six moral tales.
It doesn't matter.
That must be very interesting.
Let's go see that.
It doesn't matter.
That must be very interesting.
Let's go see that.
It doesn't matter.
That must be very interesting. Let's go see it.
Okay, do you want to go?
Yes.
Okay. Then see you at 1:30 pm on the terrace of the Rotonde.
It's right next door.
The cinema is right next to the Rotonde. It's very close.
As Robert goes downstairs, the light automatically switches off.
It's the timer, a mechanism to save electricity.
In France, we like to save money.
No, he doesn't like saving money, he spends.
But Marie-Laure is saving money
She saves her money
Now let's see what you can say
Listen, watch, think, and speak
If you sleep poorly, what is best to take before going to bed?
Tea, coffee, or herbal tea?
An infusion?
Yes, an infusion
Yes, Marie-Laure
In bed
In bed, that's it.
Your daughter is going to bed, what do you tell her?
You tell him
Goodnight my dear, sleep well
Mrs. Belleau is going to bed, what do you say to her?
You say
Sleep well
It's getting late, you're leaving, what do you say?
You say
I have to escape
You're leaving, you want to talk to Mireille tomorrow, what do you say?
You say, then, this phone Mireille wants to speak to Guylaine who is in
England, what is she doing? She's calling him, she's calling her.
He calls him, that's it. Robert is very disappointed because he is
Too late to go to the cinema tonight, what do you suggest?
You tell him, "Do you want to go tomorrow? We're showing a foreign film in its original version."
What do you need to know to understand subtitles, and why is there a need for subtitles?
You can't smoke in this room, it's forbidden, it's forbidden, according to you, Grand
Is my Larousse dictionary a fun or educational book?
Quite informative.
You're tired, the conversation bores you, you've had enough, what do you say?
Look, Mr. Guignol.
Have you seen what time it is?
Well, I think I should go to bed.
Excuse me, but I've gotten into the habit of going to bed early.
I need to go get my bed.
Okay, there you go.
Okay, good evening.
Good night.
Sleep well.
What is this?
Mr. Guignol who sleeps in my dining room?
But this Mr. Guignol is crazy.
I'm not crazy.
I'm saving energy.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
the French language, the Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
and the National Endowment for the Humanities.
For information about this and other Annenberg Media programs,
call 1-800-LEARNER and visit us at www.learner.org.