Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
black shoes, he also has one black sock, but the other one is red
He placed a pair of dark glasses next to his cup of black coffee, of course.
He blinks one eye, then the other, then both; this tic irritates Mireille tremendously.
who will get up and leave when she sees Robert sitting on the terrace of the café across the street
He looks nervously around him to the right, to the left.
He looks at his watch
Then he looks up and suddenly seems to discover that there's a café opposite.
He springs up, leaps, and takes a few steps forward.
He stops, goes back, throws a bill on the table
He takes off running again, dashing down the boulevard without looking right or left.
A screeching brake, a resounding but incomprehensible curse
Mireille closed her eyes. When she opened them, Robert was sitting next to her.
I'm not on the train, am I?
No, no. Anyway, it doesn't start for another two hours. Do you want to go?
Okay, let's go.
1:50 pm, in front of the cinema.
Two seats, please.
Wait, I have my student card.
A student seat please, that's 64 francs, but you have to
You were waiting a bit, it's not open yet, it's a shame that we
We couldn't come on Monday, why? Because it's cheaper on Mondays.
There you go, you can come in, thank you, thank you. An usher takes their ticket and their
indicates that seats here will be fine, it's not a bit too far from the screen, so here
THANKS
You have the tickets, she gave them back to you, yes, but you heard what she said
Thank you, her turn wasn't very kind, by the way, why did she thank me?
I didn't give her anything, but that's precisely why she expected us to give each other.
A tip? Oh really? You have to tip the ushers? Well, yes, it's the custom. I don't
I didn't know, you should have told me, why didn't you tell me, how do you expect me to
Just so you know, I'm not aware of it, it's not a big deal. When is it going to start?
How soon will it be? Just a little patience.
The lights go out, we switch from advertising to commercials.
café
But this coffee opens the way to the great coffees of Costa Rica, Guatemala, and Nicaragua.
Colombia is home to some of the world's finest coffees.
Having descended from the high plateaus, they crossed the mountains, traversed the valleys.
Today, here they are in Escafé, pure Colombia.
Delicate and fragrant, pure Arabica, with a powerful aroma.
Pure Colombia, pure Arabica, two great coffees by Nescafé.
A windsurfing board.
Starfish.
Bic Marine. Windsurfing boards for everyone.
Toothpaste.
Time. A razor. Bic, the razor that doesn't come apart. Simple as Bic. Cognac.
French subtitles?
Rémi Martin, fine champagne cognac, exclusively.
Mineral water.
Vitelle, you are rediscovering the vitality that is within you.
An electronic typewriter.
She was circling around me, I was scared.
At the same time, she attracted me.
I couldn't talk to anyone about it.
Do you want to know how I wrote "A Thousand Ways to Accommodate an Atom"?
With my P44 brush.
Not the end of the tunnel?
Non.
Ultra-lightweight, completely silent.
Vitelle, my mother wanted a daughter.
And finally, candy.
...
Soft music
Tender and spicy. For sale in this room.
At that precise moment, the lights come back on and the ushers become saleswomen.
Ask in the room, sweets and ice creams.
Mademoiselle.
All that is very good, but that's not why I came.
I came to see love in the afternoon.
Yes, it will come. You just need to be a little patient, come on.
Indeed, the lights go out.
I don't think it would ever start.
Hey, you'll have to explain it to me if I don't understand.
Promise?
I'll draw you a little picture.
And be quiet now.
Aren't those two going to shut up anytime soon?
Because there are some ill-mannered people out there, after all.
The film tells the story of a man in his thirties,
A young, dynamic, friendly, married executive
He meets a young, somewhat bohemian woman.
Whom he knew before his marriage
And who decides to seduce him?
He meets several times in the afternoon
He is tempted, but at the last moment
He escapes
He returns to his wife's love
In the afternoon, of course.
Finally, all of this is very moral.
All's well that ends well, as my Aunt Georgette says.
So, where are we?
We are in Montparnasse, on the terrace of the Rotonde.
Mireille attend.
Who ?
Robert, obviously.
He's not here.
He is late.
They had an appointment at 1:30.
It's a quarter to two. Robert is late. What's he doing? He must be lost.
At a table near Mireille's, there is a gentleman in his fifties.
Around fifty years old? No, no, he's not fifty, no. He, yes, he must be in his fifties.
How old are you? Almost fifty.
But him, no, he's certainly not in his fifties, no, maybe in his forties, his thirties, between 30 and 40 years old, let's say.
And so, this gentleman is strange. He's strange because he's all in black, he's dressed entirely in black.
He has a black hat, he has a black ruffle, he also has a black suit, a suit, trousers and a jacket.
Look, he's wearing a suit, a jacket and trousers.
This gentleman also has a black raincoat.
A raincoat for the rain, an odd one out.
He too is wearing an odd number, and so is she.
He too is wearing an odd number.
And he removes his odd number.
The man also has black shoes.
Shoes.
That's a shoe store.
He buys shoes in a shoe store.
He buys shoes too.
She too is trying on shoes.
Look.
Jeanne, what is it?
It's definitely a shoe store.
The strange man has black shoes.
He also has black socks.
A sock.
Shoes.
Socks. This gentleman has black socks. Actually, he only has one black sock, because the other is red. Strange, strange. He has a black mustache, black hair. And he also has black fingernails, fingernails. Robert cuts his nails. Does he have black fingernails? No.
Here Mireille is doing her nails
Those are Mireille's nails
And this is one of Mireille's uncles
A fingernail, an uncle
This gentleman also wears dark glasses
He placed his dark glasses next to a cup of black coffee.
It's not a latte, it's black coffee without milk, an espresso
This gentleman is also strange because he has a tic.
He has a nervous tic. He blinks his eyes. That's the verb "to blink".
And these are turn signals.
This tic annoys Mireille. So, she's about to leave, but she spots Robert.
Where is he, Robert? He's across the street, on the other side of the boulevard.
He went to the wrong cafe.
When he notices there's another cafe across the street,
When he realizes he's gone to the wrong café, he jumps up very quickly. He springs up. A spring. Springs. He springs up. He leaps. Now, what leaps? A panther leaps. A car with lightning-fast acceleration leaps. There you go, a car leaps.
Robert takes a few steps forward, stops, then goes back.
He turns around, he goes back because he forgot to pay
Robert is an honest boy
Look, the car is going backwards
Robert leaves, he stops, and he goes back.
And he throws a banknote on the table
He throws a candy
He throws a stone.
And this lady throws away an old sock.
She throws a bottle of poison in the trash.
He's going to throw the croissant away, you'll see.
Marie-Laure throws away an old cheese.
Marie-Laure throws away an empty packet of biscuits.
Robert throws a banknote onto the table.
Then he runs off again.
Here, he walks.
And here he runs.
He runs.
They run, they run, they run.
Run to Citroën.
They too are running. That's the verb "to run".
Robert sets off down the boulevard.
He runs, he lunges forward.
He leaps forward, he leaps into the void.
He sets off.
A screeching brake is heard.
A sudden stop.
A turn of the wheel
A punch
A kick
A hammer blow
A knife attack
A Japanese sword strike
A statue blow
A phone call
A ring of the doorbell
It's Hubert, I recognize his ring of the doorbell.
when Robert sets off down the boulevard without looking to the right or left
a screeching brake is heard
We also hear a resounding curse.
fucking shit
Fuck, get lost, you dirty bastard!
Did Robert get run over?
Is he dead?
No, he is not dead.
we can't kill him right away
We still need him
The study of the subjunctive has only just begun
Robert was not crushed
But he almost got run over.
I'm not late, am I?
No, no, in a way it doesn't start for another two hours.
Do you want to go?
Okay, let's go
Let's go
And off they go, it's our old friend the glass broom
Do you want to go?
Okay, let's go, let's go, they're going
Robert and Mireille would like two tickets, two tickets please, cinema tickets
Mrs. Bello is seating people on the train; she's showing them their seats. Here, Mireille has taken...
Marie-Laure's place, it's a shame we couldn't come on Monday, why? Because
It's cheaper on Mondays. The usherette is waiting. She's waiting for a tip. She's waiting for someone to...
She gives him a tip. She expects a tip. She expects someone to give her a tip.
gives a tip. But Robert doesn't give him a tip. He doesn't know that he should
tip the ushers. He doesn't know. And you, Jean-Claude, you are
Aware? I don't know. He doesn't know. He's not aware. Sometimes it's
It's dangerous to know. It's better not to know, listen. Why?
Didn't you alert the police? Because those people are too dangerous. You
You know I'm aware. They'd kill me too. I didn't know. You should have.
Tell me. Why didn't you tell me? How am I supposed to know? How do you expect me to
As far as I know
Robert doesn't know, he can't know
He is not aware
This is Madame Bello.
Who isn't aware?
She doesn't know, she can't know
You don't know where my Asterix is?
How am I supposed to know?
Know, it's the subjunctive mood.
From the verb to know
How am I supposed to know?
Now, it's your turn.
You're going to talk a little
Listen carefully to the dialogue between Robert and Mireille and then you will play the role of Robert.
Did she expect us to give her a tip?
Oh really, we have to tip the ushers?
Yes, that's the habit.
I didn't know. I'm not aware of that. How am I supposed to know?
Now, it's your turn. You are Robert.
Did she expect us to give her a tip?
Oh really, we have to tip the ushers?
Oh really? We have to tip the ushers?
Yes, that's the habit.
I'm not aware of that. I'm not aware of that.
I'm not aware of that.
How am I supposed to know? How am I supposed to know?
How am I supposed to know?
After the advertisement, the lights come back on in the theater and the ushers become saleswomen.
The ushers become saleswomen.
She sells candy, popsicles.
Ask in the candy room, ice cream bars.
Here is a newspaper vendor.
A saleswoman in a pastry shop.
A salesperson in a department store.
Finally, the film begins.
Robert is afraid he won't understand.
He's acting a bit like an idiot.
Hey, you'll have to explain it to me if I don't understand.
Promise?
I'll draw you a little picture.
A drawing helps you understand better, that's true.
But suggesting a small drawing is ironic.
Generally, people understand without a small drawing
Listen to Marie-Laure here
What is it?
Don't you understand? Don't you want me to draw you a little picture?
Come on, get out of here, give me back my seat!
I'll draw you a little picture.
But be quiet now
Shh! Those two aren't going to shut up anytime soon.
Shh! That means be quiet, remember?
It's the verb "to be silent".
Only water-based paint...
You will be quiet.
I will remain silent if I want to.
Water-based paint is more difficult...
But shut up!
Marie-Laure, please be quiet.
Hold on tight.
Well-behaved children should be quiet at the table.
And well-mannered people remain silent in the cinema.
Are there really some ill-mannered people out there?
Robert is ill-mannered because he talks in the cinema.
Hubert is very well-mannered.
But Marie-Laure isn't always very well-mannered.
Marie-Laure.
What ?
Stop.
You're bothering me.
Can you be rude?
Mireille isn't always well-mannered either.
Shit.
How rude of you to be!
For better or worse, Mr. and Mrs. Belleau raised three daughters.
And this gentleman, he raises dogs. He's a dog breeder.
Mr. Moric breeds purebred dogs.
And they, they raise oysters.
Oyster farming is a profession that cannot be improvised.
We also raise chickens.
The hero of Love in the Afternoon is a young executive.
An executive, a business leader, an office manager,
Someone who leads, who has responsibilities.
They are not managers, they are workers.
Ms. Belleau, who is a department head, is an executive.
They are surely managers.
This young gentleman, this dynamic and friendly young executive, meets a somewhat bohemian young woman.
She's a bit bohemian, she's a bit whimsical.
She doesn't lead a very regular life.
This lady is not bohemian at all.
This one looks a bit bohemian, yes.
This one too.
So this somewhat bohemian young woman decides to seduce the dynamic young executive.
She gets it into her head, she decides to seduce him.
The friendly young executive, etc., is tempted.
Here, it is Eve who is tempted.
The serpent tempts Eve. It is a scene of temptation.
The young, likeable executive, etc., etc., resists temptation.
He escapes temptation.
He escapes and goes to find his wife.
It's a very moral story.
Finally, all of this is very moral.
Okay, now it's your turn. Let's see what you have to say.
Look at Mireille on the rotunda terrace.
What is she doing?
She waits. Waits for whom?
Robert, obviously.
Next to Mireille, there is a strange gentleman.
What is he wearing?
He has a black hat and a black tie.
Look, Mr. Courtois is arriving. What does he have under his arm?
It's a raincoat.
What is she trying on? Socks or shoes?
Shoes.
He has black whiskers. He also has... black... black fingernails.
Look at Marie-Laure. She's finished the packet of biscuits.
And what does she do with the empty package? She... she throws it away.
What are they doing? Are they walking or running?
They are running.
Look at Marie-Laure. What is she giving to Mireille?
Blows.
And Robert, here, he makes a phone call.
And that's a real setback.
Look, is that an usherette or a saleswoman?
She's an usherette.
And this?
That's a saleswoman.
Look at Marie-Laure, here.
Is she well-mannered or badly-mannered?
Poorly behaved.
Is love in the afternoon a moral or immoral affair?
Oh, it's a moral story, a very moral one.
It might be very moralistic, but I didn't understand anything.
It's okay, don't worry, I'll explain.
I'll draw you a little picture.
Hush! Aren't those two going to shut up soon?
Oh dear, are there some badly behaved legs here?
We can no longer sleep peacefully.
Fuck! Fuck! Fuck! Fuck!
...
Subtitles ST' 501
French subtitles?