Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Robert and Mireille went to see L'Amour l'après-midi at the 14 juillet Parnasse.
They are leaving the cinema.
How about we go for a walk?
Oh yes, I'd love that. I love getting my teeth caught in that area.
Let's head over to Montparnasse.
You need to get to know the neighborhoods of artists and intellectuals.
I thought it was Saint-Germain-des-Prés.
Yes, it was first Montmartre, then Montparnasse, Saint-Germain.
Hey, Modigliani lived here.
You see, all of this is a painter's studio.
Suddenly, in front of a bookstore, Robert stops, looking worried.
He searches in his pockets.
What is it?
My passport.
What, you lost it?
I don't know, I don't have it.
Are you sure you had it? You didn't leave it in your room, did you?
You think so? I thought I had taken it.
But listen, go and see. I'm waiting for you here. Hurry up.
He'll be back soon with his seersucker jacket and his passport.
SO ?
I have it.
It was in my jacket.
Well, you see, everything's fine.
All's well that ends well, as my Aunt Georgette says.
Here we go ?
Yeah.
And they resume their stroll through Montparnasse.
And here are the literary cafes.
At the beginning of the century, one could meet Trotsky, Lenin, Fujita, Picasso there.
So, what did you think of the film? Did you like it?
Yes, of course. But if I had to choose, I think I prefer My Night at Maud's.
Yes, what an idea! Well, I never!
My night at Maud's is a bit too chaste. Nothing happens, there's no action.
These are just discussions about religion, Marxism, Pascal's wager.
I suppose there are people to call.
That's interesting, Romain, but it's not cinema.
Why? Because for you, cinema is about violence and eroticism?
What is strutting about?
No, not at all. I never said that.
But I wonder if true cinema wasn't silent film.
Do you see Charlie Chaplin's films?
Charlie Chaplin? Which Charlie Chaplin? De Gaulle?
But don't be an idiot.
Haven't you ever heard of the emigrant, the street and towards gold?
That's cinema. There's no need for a soundtrack.
Look at Griffiths, Lerus, Eisenstein, Pudovkin.
It's all in the pictures.
The editing, the interplay of close-ups and wide shots.
Oh really? So you're against talking pictures.
Against colour as well, I suppose.
Not necessarily, but there are some wonderful black and white films.
While talking, they walked past Rodin's statue.
who represents Balzac.
One day, when Marie-Laure was little,
She passed by there with her mother.
And she said, "Mom, look at the cow."
Then they walked past the garage
where Robert rented a car to go to Provins.
Oh, that's where I rented a car the other day.
when I went for a walk in Burgundy.
Ah good ?
Yes yes.
Then, they followed Boulevard Saint-Germain
up to the National Assembly.
This is where the MP prepares draft bills.
Then he sends them across the street to the Senate.
They crossed the Seine, on the Concorde bridge,
where they stopped for a moment.
To the right, over there, is the Musée d'Orsay.
It used to be a train station.
And now it's a 19th-century museum.
And in the distance, over there, you can see the Île de la Cité.
On the left, the Louvre and the Tuileries Garden.
And over there, opposite, in the background, is the Madeleine church.
That's where my mother wants me to get married, because of the staircase.
And on the left, the white house behind the trees, that's the American embassy.
That's where you'll need to go the next time you lose your passport.
You haven't lost it yet, you still have it.
Okay, I've got it.
In the middle of the square, that's the obelisk, I imagine.
Let's take a closer look.
I would like to try to decipher some hieroglyphs.
Oh no, you're crazy.
You saw the traffic, we're going to get crushed.
Let's head towards the Champs-Elysées instead.
In the walkways behind the small palace, there is calm and silence.
A few sparrows are bathing in the dust.
Two soldiers, on leave, arrive from the opposite direction.
Robert's heart-shaped jacket seems to amuse them.
Hey, did you see the butcher boy prostituting his girlfriend?
Mireille turns around and, without a word, in three precise gestures,
She sees it rolling in the dust, much to Robert's surprise.
What's gotten into you? Don't you think you're going a bit too far?
I don't like it when people make fun of others.
And then I needed to do some exercise, I missed my karate lesson on Saturday.
I'm starting to get a little confused.
I'm a little thirsty, hey, shall we go get something to drink?
If you want.
And Robert, disgusted, throws his jacket away like a circus-circus-circus-man.
What are you doing? Are you out of your mind?
She picks up the jacket.
Those Americans are crazy.
In France, we have a sense of economy.
and they will sit down
on the terrace of Fouquet
after all this exercise
Mireille is thirsty
So she suggests going for a drink.
Shall we go and have a drink?
If we were going to have a drink, that's a suggestion.
As they leave the cinema, Robert suggests he take a short walk.
How about we go for a walk?
If we walked, that's a suggestion
Hey, how about we go to the movies, huh?
What if we went to dinner on a riverboat?
What if we flew away?
What if we bought something?
How about we go for a walk?
Oh yes, I'd love that. I love running around Paris.
Let's head over to Montparnasse.
You need to get to know the neighborhoods of artists and intellectuals.
Around 1920, there were many intellectuals and artists in Montparnasse.
Lenin, Trotsky, Picasso, Fugita, and Modigliani were all there.
There are still many painters' studios in Montparnasse.
Here is a painter's workshop, a weaving workshop, an industrial design workshop, a welding workshop, an assembly workshop, a cabinetmaking workshop.
Mireille wants to talk about the film they just saw.
So what did you think of the film? Did you like it?
You liked it, that's the past tense of the verb "plaire" (to please). Do you remember?
Lacan! What an idea!
And do you like it?
Do you like it? Yes.
But if I had to choose, I think I prefer the other one.
Did you like it? Yes, of course.
But if I had to choose, I think I prefer My Night at Maud's.
This is another film by Eric Romere. It's a serious film.
Mireille thinks it's too chaste.
Nothing's happening. There are only discussions about serious topics. Marxism, religion, Pascal's wager. Pascal, a 17th-century thinker. He said that we can't know if God exists.
So you have to bet, you have to place a bet, look, we can't know where the
This heart, you have to bet, I bet it's there, but I don't really know, I'm betting, it's a bet.
You're a nurse, this bet
We know it's interesting, mind you, but it's not cinema.
Why? Because for you, cinema is about violence and eroticism?
Violence
Eroticism
No not at all
I would be very happy to see you
But I wonder if true cinema wasn't silent film.
Today, films have sound.
So I'm calm and I'm listening to you
The characters are speaking
In the past, films didn't talk. They were silent.
This little boy doesn't speak either.
Besides, he's mute. Next time, try to find me one who speaks.
She too is mute.
So, you tell me everything.
Non ?
Is it really that serious?
Very serious?
Very, very serious?
Finally, you'll tell me, won't you?
Charlie Chaplin's films were silent.
Charlot is Charlie Chaplin. General de Gaulle was also called Charles, but he wasn't called that.
Charlie Chaplin, there were some very good silent films, films without a soundtrack, that expressed themselves very well.
well thanks to the editing of the images, the interplay of general shots, wide shots and close-ups
Shots, a wide shot, a close-up, that's cinema, that's cinema, Mireille thinks so.
Well, she admires that, that's an ice cream, that's a car, there was no need for stripes
Sound? Oh really? So you're against talking pictures? You remember, you can be for them.
or against Marie Laure, for example, and for cinema is against homework then
Go to the cinema, I'm not against it, I'm against homework. Now
You are going to speak for a little while, listen to this exchange between Mireille and Robert, then you will answer.
To Mireille, as if you were Robert, what did you think of the film? Did you like it?
Yes, of course, but if I had to choose, I think I'd prefer my night at Maude's. Oh yes, what an idea!
Well, not me. My night at home is a bit too chaste. Nothing happens, there's no action.
That's interesting, mind you, but it's not cinema.
Why? Because for you, cinema is about violence? Eroticism?
No, not at all, I never said that. But I wonder if true cinema wasn't silent film.
Oh really? So you're against talking pictures. And against color too, I suppose.
Now it's your turn. You are Robert. Answer Mireille.
So, what did you think of the film? Did you like it?
Yes, of course. But if I had to choose, I think I prefer My Night at Maud's.
Oh really? What an idea.
Well, not me.
My night at Maud's is a little too chaste.
Nothing happens, there is no action.
That's interesting, mind you, but it's not cinema.
For what ?
Because for you, cinema is about violence?
Eroticism?
For what ?
Because for you, cinema is about violence?
Eroticism?
For what ?
Because for you, cinema is about violence and eroticism?
No, not at all, I never said that.
But I wonder if true cinema wasn't silent film.
Oh really? So you're against talking pictures.
And against colour as well, I suppose.
"Oh really? So you're against talking pictures. And against color too, I suppose."
While talking, Robert and Mireille passed by the statue of Balzac.
Balzac, you know, a 19th century novelist, the author of The Human Comedy, Father Goriot, The Priest of Tours, Cousin Bette.
When Marie-Laure was little, she didn't know it was Balzac. She thought it was a cow.
Walking down Boulevard Saint-Germain, Robert and Mireille arrived in front of the National Assembly.
This is where members of parliament meet to prepare bills.
Then they send them to the Senate, across the street from Mireille's house.
They send them.
Look, here they are passing the ball to each other.
They pass the ball to each other.
He throws the ball right in his face
And Marie-Laure sends her ball into Uncle Guillaume's glass
He sends a candy
He sends the suitcase
And Marie-Laure sends a kiss
She sends a letter
And the members of parliament send the bills to the Senate
It's the verb "to send".
Robert and Mireille stopped on the Concorde bridge to admire the view.
On the right, the Musée d'Orsay. It used to be a train station. Now it's a museum, a 19th-century museum.
In the background, you can see the Île de la Cité, with Notre-Dame and Sainte-Chapelle.
On the left, you can see the Louvre with the Tuileries Garden.
And further to the left, you can see the Place de la Concorde.
And at the end of the royal street, the Madeleine church.
That's where my mother wants me to get married, because of the staircase.
There's a very beautiful staircase. It's perfect for large weddings.
Madame Belleau wants Mireille to get married at the Madeleine church because of the staircase.
Because there's this staircase.
It's not easy coming here. It's because of the dogs, we're forced to live apart from them.
Thanks anyway.
There's no need to thank me. If I was running the asylum, it was only because of my sister.
Mr. Bello likes their apartment because of the view. Because there is a lovely view.
We really like this apartment because of the view. A breathtaking view of the Luxembourg Gardens.
The view is breathtaking because of the Luxembourg Gardens. Because the Luxembourg Gardens are right in front of it.
Mireille does something stupid because of Marie-Laure.
But look what I've done because of you!
Because of me! Oh, that's a good one!
It's my fault! Oh my!
That's where my mother wants me to get married, because of the staircase.
And on the left, the white house behind the trees, that's the American embassy.
That's where you'll need to go the next time you lose your passport.
When you lose your passport, Robert hasn't lost his.
Okay, I've got it.
But he's sure to lose it again.
So, when he loses it, he'll have to go to the American embassy.
Can I go watch TV?
When you've finished watching, not before.
I'll never finish.
Robert wants to take a closer look at the obelisk to try and decipher the hieroglyphs.
I would like to try to decipher some hieroglyphs.
He taught himself to read. He might even be able to decipher hieroglyphs.
It was Champollion who first deciphered Egyptian hieroglyphs.
What is in the middle of the Place de la Concorde?
The obelisk.
Who comes from where?
I don't know, you know what's on it, probably something written or engraved.
You don't know what they are? No, they're hieroglyphs that Robert wants to decipher, but Mireille
She disagrees because of the traffic on the Place de la Concorde; she's afraid of...
We're going to get run over. We're going to get run over. Watch out! We're going to run you over! Do you remember?
Robert has already almost been run over. If he crosses the Place de la Concorde, he
will get run over again because there's a lot of traffic. But in the aisles,
It's calmer down at the bottom of the Champs-Élysées.
The Avenue des Champs-Élysées, an avenue, a street, a path, a path, a path,
An alley, an alley, an alley, an alley, an alley.
The paths behind the small palace are quiet.
There are sparrows bathing in the dust.
They are swimming in the sea.
And she, she bathes in a swimming pool. He, he bathes in his bathtub. And the sparrows bathe in the dust. The dust. A cloud of dust.
Two soldiers on leave arrive. They are not on duty. They are on leave. He is on duty. He too is on duty.
They too are on duty. They too. But these soldiers aren't on duty. They're on leave. The soldiers are making fun of Robert because of his jacket. They think he looks like a butcher. A waiter, a baker's boy, a butcher.
She said, "Did you see the butcher boy walking his girl around?" A girl, a young girl, a girl, Mireille.
doesn't like it and she sends the soldier rolling in the dust, she sends him rolling in the
dust. She sends it rolling. She sends it rolling on the ground. Here, she sends Marie-Laure
Go get the photo album. Go get my album. Here, she sends him to get the snack. So go
fetch the snack. Oh, can you be a nuisance? And Madame Belleau sends her off to do her
Marie-Laure, go do your homework.
Go on, disappear.
And here, she sends them to bed.
Go to bed, go to sleep.
No discussion, off to bed.
Good evening.
When Mireille sends the soldier rolling in the dust,
The sparrows fly away.
It flies away. The ducks fly away. The plane takes off. It flies away. It takes off. It flies away. The balloons fly away.
The lions flew away. They fly away. Prices are skyrocketing.
What's gotten into you? Robert is a little surprised. He doesn't approve.
Give me back my gumballs! Do you hear? Give me back my gumballs!
Hey, what's wrong with you, are you okay?
Marie, Marie, what possessed you to come and sleep on that?
What ?
Weren't you comfortable in bed?
Mireille needed to do some exercise, because she missed her karate lesson.
And then I needed to do some exercise, I missed my karate lesson on Saturday.
She missed it, she didn't go.
Marie-Laure missed school today because she has a cold.
Today she missed school because she has a sore throat.
Mireille was starting to get rusty because she missed her karate lesson.
I'm starting to get a little rusty.
If you don't exercise, you get rusty.
This gate is rusty.
You remember that Robert's Japanese is a bit rusty.
Your Japanese?
A little rusty.
That too is rusting, rusting, rusting
Mireille suggests going for a drink because she's thirsty after all that exercise.
I'm a little thirsty, you know, shall we go get something to drink?
If you want
Hey, I'm thirsty, what can I get to drink?
I don't know what you want
A little tape
He too is thirsty
They too are thirsty.
If he wakes up, it's because he'll be thirsty, will you hear?
And he's hungry
Yeah, it's 4:30.
Why does he keep repeating that it's 4:30?
He says that because he's hungry and we haven't had a taste yet.
What if we bought something? Good idea!
He is hungry too.
I didn't eat.
To be hungry, to be thirsty.
Now listen, watch, think, and speak.
If you feel like going for a drink, what do you say?
I'm a little thirsty, hey, shall we go get something to drink?
And if you feel like going for a walk?
How about we go for a walk?
What is it? A workshop or an office?
A workshop.
If you eat an ice cream that is very, very, very, very good, what can you say?
Hmm, that's an ice cream.
And if you don't like homework, what do you say? Me, I
I'm against homework, what is Marie-Laure doing?
Send a kiss, is that a street or an alley? An alley, what's he doing?
He bathes where he works, he bathes, the sparrows bathe in a bathtub or in
Dust in dust, and that's a waiter or a butcher's boy, a boy
Boucher, is it a talking film or a silent film? Silent if you want to talk about a film you just...
So, what can you say? What did you think of the film?
I liked it again, so what did you think of the film? Did you enjoy it, sir?
Guignol, how do you find our story? Do you like it? No, Miss Mireille, it's...
It's a bit too chaste; there's no action, nothing happens. It needs a little more.
A little bit of eroticism, a little bit of violence.
But what's gotten into you, Mr. Guignol?
Hey, you're going a bit too far there, Mr. Guignol.
Whoa! Stop!
I am against violence in cinema.
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada