Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on
and be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Our four characters discuss theatrical forms,
stage versus film, immediacy versus permanence, etc.
While the man in black sends signals in Morse code with his eyes,
Jean-Pierre argues the merits of the circus
and a strange nun replaces the strange man.
The terrace of Fouquet
We hear snippets of a rather snobbish conversation.
Have you seen Godard's latest film? It's absolutely brilliant!
Do you think so?
Four young people are sitting at a table.
At the next table, a man dressed all in black is watching them intently.
Hey, did you see the eyes of the guy next to him?
So what, what's wrong with their eyes?
He has one eye that says "fuck" to the other, as if in the name of Victor.
No, no, it's both.
It's those two eyes that are saying "fuck off" to I don't know who.
How so ?
One morning.
What is this all about?
Yes, yes, look.
He blinked one eye, that's a point.
He blinked with both eyes, that's a feature.
Line, line, dot.
Point, Z.
Point, point, trait, U.
One point, T.
I thought he was flirting with Mireille, but no.
Not at all, it's a message.
Certainly.
Then he must be a dangerous spy.
Attention, he's listening to us. Let's resume the conversation as if nothing happened.
What is the future of theatre?
No good. The future is in cinema and television.
That's wrong. Nothing can ever replace the presence of a live, flesh-and-blood actor.
Hubert is right. Cinema is canned. It's mechanical.
Whereas in the theatre, the actor remains in contact with the audience.
In the theatre, a good actor constantly modifies his performance according to the audience's reaction.
Yes, but in theatre, the performance is ephemeral, whereas in cinema, it is fixed forever.
With film archives at Chaillot, Beaubourg, or with video,
You can see almost all the good films that have been made since cinema existed.
The Misanthrope, directed and performed by Molière, was surely brilliant, yes.
But no one will ever be able to see him again.
And besides, cinema has so much more considerable resources than theatre.
In cinema, you can put 2000 fig trees in a Russian plain
With cannons, cavalry charges, an army lost in the snow
The army lost in the snow, I saw that in the theatre, in Huburoi
On a very small stage, there was simply a man
With a sign that read "Polish army marching into Ukraine"
Yes, but in cinema, it's easier to play with time and space.
All kinds of trickery are possible
You can turn a monster into a prince charming
Blow up the FM tower
Set fire to the Montparnasse tower.
And then in cinema, there is the possibility of dubbing in all languages.
Oh well, I can do without that. How awful! I hate dubbed films, there's nothing more fake.
I also prefer films in their original language, with subtitles for Japanese films.
Oh, because his Japanese is a bit rusty.
For me, only cinema, musicals, and the circus are of interest.
The circus.
You have very vulgar tastes.
Tell me about ballet, modern or classical dance.
But the music hall is for voyeurs who get their kicks.
watching naked women raising their legs.
No, not at all.
The music hall is the conservatory of contemporary culture.
And I'm not talking about music hall shows
like those at the Folies Bergère or the Concert Mayol, no.
I mean, the great recitals of my time or in the past after Brassens, at Bobineau, at the Olympia.
And also the cabaret and café-theatre shows of Raymond Devoz, Villeray, Coluche, Zouk.
Hey, the guy is still listening to us.
Wow, that's strange.
What, what is it?
He's no longer here.
In her place, there is a nun, all in black, who is reading the cross.
It looks like she's doing Morse code with her wimple.
Mireille and Robert are still on the terrace of Fouquet.
They talk about shows, cinema, and theatre.
But it's difficult to understand what they're saying.
You need to listen with sustained attention.
Because Fouquet is a large café on the Champs-Élysées.
There's a lot of traffic, a lot of people passing by, people talking nearby.
Have you seen Godard's latest film? It's absolutely brilliant!
Do you think so?
Wow, awesome!
They're great!
Jean-Pierre notices a strange man.
Hey, did you see the eyes of the guy next to him?
A guy, remember?
A guy with a black raincoat and a black hat.
He's a funny guy, you'll see.
Observe. A man, a guy, a dude.
Mantis, a guy, there!
Did you see the eyes of the guy next to him?
So what, what's wrong with their eyes?
He has one eye that says "fuck" to the other, just like my uncle Victor.
Uncle Victor has one eye that says "fuck" to the other.
Her eyes disagree.
One of them tells the other to go to hell.
Look, here they agree, but here they no longer agree.
She's had enough. She says "oh damn" and goes off in another direction.
Oh shit!
So Uncle Victor has one eye that says "screw you" to the other.
He's cross-eyed, but the guy next to him doesn't have one eye that's saying "screw you" to the other, no, it's
Different from him, it's his eyes, his two eyes that say "darn" in Morse code, the Morse code.
You know how to send messages using Morse code with dots and...
lines, two lines, two dots, that's z, two dots, one line, that's u, and a line
It's T.
Listen to the dialogue between Hubert and Mireille
and then you will play the role of Hubert.
What is it?
Did you see the eyes of the guy next to him?
So what, what's wrong with their eyes?
He has one eye that says "fuck" to the other, as if in the name of Victor.
No, no, it's both.
It's those two eyes that are saying "fuck off" to who knows who.
How so ?
One morning.
What is this all about?
Now it's your turn. You are Hubert.
What is it?
Did you see the eyes of the guy next to him?
But what? What's wrong with their eyes?
He has one eye that says "fuck" to the other, as if in the name of Victor.
No, no, it's both.
It's those two eyes that are saying "fuck off" to who knows who.
How so ?
One morning.
The strange guy next to him is doing Morse code with his eyes.
He blinks one eye, that's a point.
He blinks both eyes, it's a line. He blinks. That's the verb "to blink." To blink, to flash, as in "blinking," remember?
Sometimes, we blink to get someone's attention. It's quite vulgar and not recommended.
"Look, he's winking to get a girl's attention. He's flirting with her. Let's see if you understand. Here, sir, you want to flirt with the young lady? Very well! But remember, in class, like that, to learn French, it's very good. But not in real life. It's too vulgar."
He must be a spy.
Definitely. So he must be a dangerous spy.
A spy.
A dangerous spy.
Mom, I saw a spy.
Then he must be a dangerous spy.
Attention, he's listening to us. Let's resume the conversation as if nothing happened.
As if nothing had happened.
Look at Jean-Pierre here.
He tries to flirt with Mireille, but she doesn't pay attention to him.
She continues reading as if nothing had happened.
Jean-Pierre thinks that cinema and television will be very successful in the future.
She reads the future.
Jean-Pierre sees great development in cinema and television in the future.
The future lies in cinema and television.
The future is in cinema. The future is on television.
The road is ours.
Paris is mine.
Paris belongs to Robert. And the future is in the movies.
The future lies in cinema and television.
Jean-Pierre thinks that cinema and television will replace theatre.
The motorcycle replaced the horse.
The train replaced the stagecoach. The airplane replaced the ocean liner. Robots may replace factory workers. But nothing will ever replace the presence of a live, flesh-and-blood actor.
The advantage of theatre is that the actor is alive, in flesh and blood.
It's not an image, it's bones, a bone, bones, it's bones and flesh
This isn't an image, a photograph; he is here, in the flesh.
Here's my little sister Marie-Laure, and here she is in the flesh!
In the theatre, the actor is alive. He is there, he is present.
He can observe the audience's reactions.
It's alive.
Whereas cinema is like canned food.
Do you remember? Like peas.
Do you prefer theatre or cinema?
I think I prefer cinema.
You have the music, the image, the text all at once.
For me, cinema is a complete art form.
I feel like I believe more in what's happening on the screen
than what is happening on stage.
One of the advantages of cinema is that we have great resources at our disposal.
You can do lots of things that are impossible in the theatre.
With special effects, you can make the Eiffel Tower explode or make it shine.
We can set fire to the Montparnasse Tower or the Eiffel Tower.
Beer steins can disappear.
You can make sauerkraut disappear.
You can make a cheese disappear.
You can take off from a plane on the Champs-Élysées.
Or we could make the Arc de Triomphe disappear.
We can put Mireille on Robert's hand, who is not very tall.
Or transforming a monster into a prince charming.
It's all a hoax.
In cinema, you can put 2000 extras in a Russian plain.
A plain of mountains, a plain.
You can put 2000 extras on a Russian plain with cannons, cavalry charges, an army lost in the snow.
The army lost in the snow, I saw that in the theatre, in Huburoi, on a very small stage.
There was simply a man with a sign that said "The Polish army is marching into Ukraine".
Mireille saw that in a play by Alfred Jarry, "Hubu Roi".
On a very small stage, the army lost in the snow was represented by a stick figure.
With a sign that read "The Polish army is marching into Ukraine."
And there you have it. No need for extras to represent the Polish army.
Here's an actor and here are some extras.
One actor, some extras.
And then in cinema, there is the possibility of dubbing in all languages.
A film can be dubbed into any language.
Mireille doesn't like dubbing.
I could do without that. How awful.
She could do without it.
Marie-Laure doesn't like lessons.
But chocolates, no, they can't live without them.
Gumballs can't do without them either.
Mom, can I go buy some gumballs?
No, you're not going out at this hour.
Go do your homework
Oh, but I'm out of gumballs!
You'll do without it
I can't live without cinema.
I go there almost every day, I see 4 or 5 films a week
I love cinema, but could I do without it?
Mireille would do without dubbed films.
She hates it.
I hate dubbed films. There's nothing more fake.
She hates it because it's untrue.
That's not true. It's artificial.
Look at her hair. It's fake. It's artificial.
That's also wrong. That's not correct.
Damn, missed it!
Mireille doesn't like dubbed films.
She prefers films in their original version, with subtitles.
Jean-Pierre, what he loves is the circus.
The circus with clowns and animals.
The circus is what the Roman people loved.
Hubert finds it vulgar.
It's a show for the people.
The circus.
You have very vulgar tastes.
Tell me about ballet, modern or classical dance.
He doesn't like the circus, he likes dancing.
He doesn't have the same tastes as Jean-Pierre.
It's a matter of taste.
To each their own.
He doesn't like roses.
Roses? It's like blue hair in green, it's difficult to pull off.
You can't understand.
As for me, roses, well, to each their own.
Hubert doesn't like musical shows either.
Lido, the Folies Bergère.
It's for voyeurs who get their kicks from watching naked women raise their legs.
It's for voyeurs, people who like to see, to watch.
Voyeurs get their kicks from watching naked women.
They're having a blast.
They like it.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She's having a blast.
Are you enjoying yourself?
Yes, I'm having a blast.
They're having a blast over there.
Robert is having a great time.
He's having a great time too.
She's enjoying herself too.
They're having a blast too.
He's having a great time too.
Voyeurs get their kicks from watching naked women
Here is a man dressed
And here's a naked man
The lady with the unicorn is dressed
But the statue of truth is naked
The Statue of Liberty is dressed
But the Venus de Milo is naked
Bareheaded
Barefoot
Bare hands
And he's completely naked.
Jean-Pierre defends the musical.
Musical theatre is the conservatory of contemporary culture.
What he calls the conservatory of contemporary culture,
Obviously, these are not shows like the Lido or Folie Bergère, no, no.
But shows with songs,
like those of Jacques Brel, Georges Brassens, and Yves Montand.
Or perhaps shows where stories are told,
like those of Raymond Devos, Zouk, Coluche, Villerey.
While the four young people were talking,
The funny guy who used to do Morse code while blinking has disappeared
and was replaced by a nun who uses Morse code while wearing her wimple.
One can be bareheaded, or wear a hat, or a beret.
or a helmet, or a headdress, or a scarf, or horns, or a cornette, a hat.
What are you doing?
A beret.
A headdress.
Headdresses.
A hat.
A cap.
A helmet.
And this is a helmet.
Do you know this gentleman?
Non ?
This is Fernand Reynaud, a songwriter
who played in music halls and café-theatres.
He was very well-known.
There you go, there you go, there you go, there you go.
He was very funny.
Everyone thought he was very funny.
Coluche also made people laugh a lot.
He mocked the average Frenchman, his prejudices, his tastes.
Spain is Spanish folklore.
I don't like it.
But to each their own.
For them, it's fantastic.
Did you understand? No?
Well, we'll ask him to do it again.
Spain is Spanish folklore.
I don't like it.
But to each their own.
For them, it's fantastic
This is Raymond Devos
I've played you, talk to me about love
Ladies and Gentlemen
I never dared tell you out of modesty.
But it's crazy how much I love you
I have lived only for you, and I am ready to die for you, right here, right now, on stage, if you wish.
Let's see if you understand it.
Ladies and gentlemen, I've never dared to tell you this out of modesty, but it's crazy how much I love you.
I have lived only for you
And I am ready to die for you.
Right now, on stage
If you wish
Hello, so
Hi, so
Ah, it's you, Mulray
You recognize me by now
Yeah, it's going well, really well, really well.
And you, huh?
Hello, sir, please tell me.
Would you happen to have a little help with spelling, please?
Actually, it's not for me, it's for a friend.
Finally, let's say, it's for her, without being for her.
It's for his kid.
So, you write anything, you know how kids are,
He won't even read it.
Ah, no, I don't have any paper.
Well, listen, you just have to mark it there.
And then I'll copy it. Okay, goodbye.
Ah, it's difficult, isn't it?
Okay, let's start again.
Hello Sir.
Please tell me,
Wouldn't you happen to have a little help with spelling, please?
Actually, it's not for me, it's for a friend.
Finally, let's say, it's for her, without being for her.
It's for his kid.
So, you write anything, you know how kids are,
He won't even read it.
Ah, no, I don't have any paper.
Well, listen, you just have to mark it there.
And then I'll copy it. Okay, goodbye.
This is Marcel Marceau, a mime.
Okay, enough laughing.
Let's see if you've retained anything.
Observe, listen, reflect, and speak
Do you remember what that is?
A turn signal
And what's this gentleman doing? He's blinking. Is the year 2098 the past or the future? The future. That's a stagecoach. What did the train do?
It replaced the stagecoach.
Is that flesh or bones?
Les os.
And is that a bone or flesh?
Flesh.
In cinema, you can do all sorts of things.
Look at this.
Is the Arc de Triomphe really disappearing?
No, it's a... a... a... trick.
Is that a plain or a mountain?
A plain.
Normally, Japanese films are in Japanese.
If a Japanese film speaks French...
Damn, missed it!
That's because it's doubled.
If it's in the original version, if it's in Japanese,
To understand, Robert needs to...
subtitles.
To see clowns, acrobats, animals,
We need to go to the circus.
Hubert thinks the circus is a vulgar spectacle.
He prefers dancing.
Look at this young man.
Do you think he's bored or is he having a great time?
He's having a blast.
Does Mireille have something on her foot?
Or is she barefoot?
She is barefoot.
And here, is she wearing a hat or is her head bare?
She is bareheaded.
What do you think of Mireille's earrings?
They're great!
So, what do you think of our story, Ms. Folding?
Oh, that's absolutely brilliant!
You are so handsome, Mr. Robert!
Oh, what a charming prince!
Okay, okay, okay, that's enough, alright. Let's stop.
No, no, no, no, that's not it.
There you go.
French subtitles?
Subtitles ST' 501
at www.learner.org.