Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on
and be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Our two characters must have names.
She will be Mireille and he, Robert.
She gets working parents and two sisters, one married.
Robert is an only child.
His mother is French.
His parents are divorced, his mother remarried.
Robert just may have a few hang-ups.
Good morning, ladies, good morning, young ladies, good morning, gentlemen.
Let's continue inventing history.
Well, first of all, we need to give the young people a first name.
Well, why?
Why? It's elementary, my dear Watson.
We need to give young people a first name because everyone has a first name.
I have a first name. My first name is Pierre.
You have a first name. What is your first name?
Michael.
Well, you see, he has a first name.
You too have a first name. What is your first name?
Julia.
You see, she too has a first name.
Everyone has a first name
Me, her, him
But the young people in the story don't have first names.
This isn't going to work, it's not possible.
Young people need to be given a first name.
Because it's not easy to tell a story without a first name
So, let's give the young people a first name.
Let's see, first of all, what's the girl's name going to be?
Invented
Oh no, it's a pretty name, but it won't work, it's an American name
The girl is French, she needs a French first name
Listen, the girl's name is going to be Mireille.
Why?
Because it's a pretty name, isn't it Mireille?
It's pretty. It's a pretty name.
And besides, it's not easy to pronounce.
Here, try it. Say Mireille.
Say Mireille. Go on, go ahead.
Mireille.
Listen, Mireille.
Go ahead, try it.
Mireille.
You see, it's not easy to pronounce.
It's a pretty name, but it's not easy to pronounce.
The young man's first name will be Robert.
No, no, no, no discussion.
It's decided, the young man's first name will be Robert.
For what ?
First, because it's a first name that is both French and American.
It's a French first name and it's also an American first name.
It's a first name that is both French and American.
And besides, it's not easy to pronounce either.
Robert, it's not easy to pronounce.
Okay, now the two young people in the story have first names.
The girl's first name is...
Invented.
It's not Air Force, it's Mireille.
Oh really? Mireille, if you like.
And what is the young man's first name?
Robert ?
No, Robert.
Lobat.
Robert.
Okay, now we need to give the young people a family.
First, giving the young girl a family.
Let's see.
Will Mireille's family be poor?
Non.
So, will Mireille's family be rich?
Well, Mireille's family isn't poor, but they aren't rich either.
They are not a poor family, nor are they a rich family.
They are a wealthy family.
Let's see now.
Will Mireille have a mother?
Yes.
Is she going to have a father?
Okay, so that's settled then.
Mireille's family is neither poor nor rich.
They are a wealthy family.
Mireille has a father and a mother.
Mireille's father and mother both work.
They both work.
Mireille's father works at Renaud's.
He is an engineer at Renaud.
And his mother is a department head at the Ministry of Health.
Mireille has two sisters.
Cécile is older. She is 23 years old.
She is married. Marie-Laure is younger, much younger.
She's ten years old. Is she married, Marie-Laure?
Non.
Obviously. She's too young to be married.
Let's see, how many children do Mireille's father and mother have?
Three. They have three children. Three girls or three boys?
Three girls.
Okay, now let's give Robert a family. Let's see.
Will Robert have a mother?
Yes.
Is he going to have a father?
Okay, so Robert has a mother and a father.
Robert's parents have money.
They are even quite rich.
Robert has no sister.
And he doesn't have a brother either.
He is an only child.
Robert's parents are divorced.
His father has not remarried.
Her mother has remarried.
Poor Robert.
Only child, divorced parents, remarried mother.
He might develop insecurities.
Ah, very good. I love it.
Let's talk about Robert's complexes.
Are you talking about Robert's complexes?
Oh yes.
For what ?
Because it's going to be fun and useful for learning French.
Do you believe that? Maybe, maybe, but not today.
We don't have time. Another time.
Today, we continue to invent history.
We continue.
Look.
Here, I begin.
I continue, I continue, I continue, I continue, I continue and I stop.
Start, continue, stop.
Now, look at Marie-Laure. She's told to stop, but she keeps going.
Stop!
If you continue, it's going to end badly.
Mom, listen, if you keep going it's going to end badly. She keeps going and it ends badly for her too.
He continued, he told her to stop, but she kept going. "I'll come with you," he said. "Here, no, keep going." Okay, let's continue.
First, we will give the young people a first name.
First, to begin with, look at Marie-Laure.
Marie-Laure, are you going to work?
Yes, but first, I want to watch TV.
You'll work first, you'll watch TV afterwards.
Understood ?
She wants to watch TV first and work afterwards.
But his mother disagrees. He should work first, watch TV later.
You'll work first, you'll watch TV afterwards.
First, we need to give the young people a first name. Give it. Look.
Here, this is for you.
Uncle Guillaume gives chocolates to Marie-Laure.
Marie-Laure gives Mireille a candy.
The children give grapes to their father.
They give the little boy a pair of scissors.
They slap the little boy.
Give the dough, give the dough to Mireille.
Come on.
It's very small but it walks well.
They give the girl a lighter.
They give the keys to the man.
Young people need to be given first names.
Juliette is a first name
Victor is a first name
Jean-Paul, that's the first name
Sartre, that's the name, the family name
Simone is the first name
De Beauvoir is the name, the family name
Beatrice is the first name
Laverne is the name, the family name
Corinne is a first name
Everyone has a first name, you'll see.
What is your first name?
Jocelyne.
Patrice.
Agnes.
Vincent.
Olivier.
We need to give young people a first name because everyone has a first name.
And besides, a first name is useful.
It's useful for telling a story.
So, we need to give the young people a first name.
It's necessary.
It's necessary, it's mandatory.
Look at Marie-Laure, who is sick.
It's necessary !
Now you need to rest.
How are you ?
No, that's not going to work.
For what ?
We need glasses, you see.
Oh!
What more do we need?
Well, you need towels.
Excuse me, I have to run, I'm going to be late
I have to go now, I'm late
We need to separate
you should never point the finger
Marie-Laure, you don't work
go to work
we need to work
Young people need to be given a first name.
We must work, we must study, we must listen, we must continue, we must
We must try, we must learn, we must understand, we must see, we must be able, we must leave, we must choose, we must give young people a name.
We need to give the young people in the story a first name because without a first name, it's not easy to tell a story.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's telling Fido a story.
He tells a story
Your mother's grandfather and grandmother lived in this house.
Tell me a story
It's not easy to tell a story without a first name
Here is a young man with no first name
And here is a young man with a first name.
Here is a lady and a gentleman with children.
And here is a lady and a gentleman without children.
A lady and a gentleman with children.
A man and a woman with no children.
A man and a woman with children.
Jam with bread.
Jam without bread? You're not going to eat your jam without bread.
Why not? Where are you going to the cinema? You're not going to the cinema without me.
Why not? It's not going to work, why can't we eat without a fork? Meh.
Why not that then? Look at Aunt Georgette without
Fido. Oh really? And Aunt Georgette? Where's Fido? My goodness, Fido! Fido! Marie-Laure with her boat and
Marie-Laure without her boat and the boat without Marie-Laure. Let's see if you've got it, okay?
being a game lady with children the same lady without children with children without children with
100 to you now with 100 with his with his first you have to give the girl a first name
Ah yes, Ethel.
No, Ethel, that's not right.
That won't work because it's not a French first name.
It must be a French first name.
Mireille, yes, it's fine.
But Ethel, no, that won't do.
Eight thirty.
Oh, that's fine, I have time.
Look at Mireille here.
That's not going well.
How are you.
It's going very, very well.
It's okay, it's not okay.
How are you ?
No, that's not going to work.
For what ?
We need glasses, you see.
How are you ?
No, that's not going to work.
The knife on the right and the fork on the left.
Does everyone know that?
The girl's name will be Mireille, okay?
It's a pretty name, isn't it?
Mireille, that's pretty.
And that's a pretty scarf.
What do you think?
Yes, it's pretty.
A nice roast.
He's pretty.
A pretty young girl.
You are so pretty.
Pretty flowers.
It's pretty.
It's pretty, isn't it?
It's very pretty.
It's pretty, all these colors.
Yeah.
It's beautiful.
It's beautiful, isn't it?
Come here, pretty dog. You're a very pretty dog, you know. You're a pretty little dog.
That's a pretty dog. But that one, no, that's not a pretty dog.
She is pretty. She is not pretty.
Now you are going to speak French.
Listen to this dialogue between Mireille and her friend Jean-Michel.
You will repeat Jean-Michel's answers.
"It's going to be the story of two young people. A young man and a young woman. And the young woman's name is going to be..."
"Mireille. The girl's name will be Mireille."
"Why is that?"
"Because it's a pretty name."
Now it's your turn, you are Jean-Michel.
"And the girl's first name will be..."
"Mireille. The girl's name will be Mireille. Mireille. The girl's name will be Mireille."
Mireille. The girl's name will be Mireille.
Why is that?
Because it's a pretty name.
The young man's first name will be Robert.
It's a pretty name, and it's not an easy name to pronounce.
Robert. Here, pronounce it.
Robert. Say Robert.
Robert.
Robert. R, R, R. Listen. Robert. Robert. Look. Robert. R, R, R.
Robert is a nice name. Not easy to pronounce.
And besides, it's a French first name. And it's also an American first name.
It's a first name that is both French and American.
It's both French and American.
Look, look at this centaur.
He is both a man and a horse.
And a mermaid is both a woman and a fish.
Listen to what Mireille is going to say.
But be careful, you can't wear everything at once.
Plates first, glasses second.
You're not going to eat two chocolates at once, are you?
And why not?
Now, we need to give these young people a family.
A family. That's a family. That's a family.
No, that's not a family.
Now that's a family.
And this is a family?
No, it's not a family.
And this?
Now that's a family.
Mireille's family is not rich.
She's not poor either.
She is well-off.
Is she rich?
No, she is not rich.
Is she poor?
No, she's not poor either.
She is well-off. They are a well-off family.
Rich, poor, rich, poor.
He, on the other hand, is rather poor.
Now, look at this man.
Is he poor or rich?
Poor.
And this lady, is she rich or poor?
Rich.
Is this gentleman rich or poor?
He is rich, he has a servant.
They are rich, they have money.
Money.
Marie-Laure, on the other hand, has no money.
Do you have money?
But here, she has money, she is rich.
He has no money.
Mireille has a father and a mother.
These are my father and mother.
Mireille's father, her mother.
The father, the mother.
A father, a mother.
Mireille's father works.
He is working.
Robert's father also works.
Mireille's mother also works.
She works.
He is working.
He's not working there.
He eats.
Now, look at Mireille's father here.
Does he work there?
No, he's not working there.
And Ousmane, is he working there?
Yes, they work. And here?
No, they don't work here.
And you, do you work?
Mireille's parents have three children.
Robert's father and mother have a child.
Mireille's father and mother have three daughters.
Robert's father and mother have a son.
Do you have children?
Three. One tall girl and two boys.
Mommy, mommy.
Oh, how sweet my daughters are.
Three girls, one boy. Three girls, one boy.
One girl, two girls, three girls, four girls, five girls, six girls, seven girls, eight girls, nine girls, ten girls.
One child, two children, three children, four children, five children, six children, seven children, eight children, nine children, ten children.
Six girls, six children; ten girls, ten children.
Mireille has two sisters
An older sister and a younger sister
Two sisters
Marie-Laure is younger, she is 10 years old
Cécile is older, she is 23 years old
20, 21, 22, 23 years old
And how old are you?
I am 10 years old.
And how old is Mireille?
She is 19 years old.
I am 10 years old and she is 19 years old.
Are you 19 years old?
Yes, I am 19 years old.
How old are you, 15?
How old are you, my friend?
Nine and a half years old, ma'am.
10.
7.
2.
Let's see if you understood.
12, 22, 3, 13, 23, 4, 14, 24, 5, 15, 25, 6, 16, 26, 7, 17, 27,
Eight, eighteen, twenty-eight, nine, nineteen, twenty-nine, ten, twenty.
Mireille has sisters. Does she have brothers? No, she doesn't have any brothers.
Brothers, no brothers. Brothers, no brothers.
Does Robert have any sisters? No, he doesn't have any sisters.
Does Robert have any brothers? No, he doesn't have any brothers either.
He is an only child.
Is Mireille an only child? No, she has sisters.
How many sisters does she have? She has two sisters.
Mireille has two sisters
Cécile is the oldest
I believe she is married
We'll see
Are you both married?
Yes
We are married
And you, are you married?
No, I'm not married.
Non
Look at these young people, are they married?
No, they are not married.
And this gentleman and this lady, are they married?
Yes, they are married, that's obvious.
Hello? Catherine? It's Catherine.
But what's going on, darling?
Will you marry me?
I'm getting married.
Is she getting married?
We're getting married tomorrow.
Do you have children?
Oh no, no, no, I'm not married.
Fiancé ?
Oh no, no, I'm not engaged either.
Like me, then.
Mireille's father and mother are married.
Robert's father and mother are divorced.
I'm divorced twice.
Robert's mother has remarried.
This lady is also remarried.
But Robert's father has not remarried.
And you, Mr. Guignol, are you married?
Yes sir, I am married and even remarried.
Nineteen children, sir, one boy and eighteen girls, and I also have a dog.
So, I don't have time to answer your stupid questions, sir.
Goodbye, sir.
Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
French subtitles?