Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
On the terrace of Fouquet's, Mireille, Hubert, Robert, Jean-Pierre.
Waiter, the bill, please.
The boy is looking away.
Five minutes later, Hubert signaled to the boy.
So, when is that bill coming?
No effect.
After ten minutes, Mireille calls the boy.
Could you bring us the bill, please?
Right away, miss.
And they head towards another table.
Ten minutes later, Robert tries his luck.
Could we have the bill, please?
Yes, sir. There you go, sir.
That makes one hundred and thirty-five francs.
Robert hands the boy a 200 franc note.
Hubert, Jean-Pierre and Mireille turn away modestly.
The boy places his tray full of glasses on the table to give Robert his change.
When giving change...
So, 135 and 5...
40...
And ten. There you go.
He drops a coin.
Everyone rushes to pick it up.
The tray falls to the ground, the glasses shatter into a thousand pieces.
That's bad luck, then.
No, on the contrary, it brings good luck, it's white glass.
Well, all that's left for me to do is take my leave.
Thank you.
Goodbye everyone, Hubert has taken leave. Well, a lime bath then. Bye!
Jean-Pierre has left.
Robert and Mireille also get up and leave.
They walk down the Champs-Élysées.
Robert notes that several young couples, and even some older ones, are holding hands.
He wonders if he should take Mireille's hand too.
But he doesn't dare
On the sidewalk, next to a newsstand
He notices a small stall with a sign
National Lottery, draw on Wednesday
Tell me, do we ever win this lottery?
I imagine so, but I've never won anything.
I must say that I have never bought a ticket.
It's not exactly against my principles, but I don't really like it.
It's not particularly in line with my principles either, but I could really use some fresh cash.
Life seems to be expensive in France.
And then, we have to take advantage of the opportunity with all this broken white glass.
Okay, let's buy a ticket, shall we?
If that amuses you.
In any case, part of the money goes to a good cause.
Tuberculosis patients, nursing homes for the elderly,
Broken wings, shattered faces.
Go ahead, choose.
Oh no, choose yourself.
No, you.
No, not me, I never have any luck.
Yes, yes, you must be very lucky right now.
You just broke at least 12 white glasses.
I didn't break them, you did.
No, it's not me, it's you.
Actually, no, it's Hubert, I saw him.
But that doesn't matter. Go ahead.
Take any ticket as long as the last two digits add up to nine.
18, 27, 27, 36, 45, 54, 63, 72, 81, 90.
Why is that?
It's obvious. You're 18 years old.
Almost 19.
Okay. You live at 18, 8 and 1, 9.
The drinks cost exactly 135 francs.
3 and 1, 4 and 5, 9.
and I counted nine couples, young or old, holding hands.
Oh, that one!
Mireille chooses a ticket sold to benefit an organization
who takes care of abandoned babies.
Because she liked the ticket immediately.
Against the background, he wears the palisade, an adorable pink baby doll
and number 63-728-127, series MR,
That makes a lot of new things, if you look closely.
and recognizable initials.
Robert would like Mireille to keep the ticket.
Here, keep it.
Oh no, I'd be too afraid of losing it.
Are you losing things?
Not me. You're the one who loses things and loses yourself.
Not me.
But still, I'd prefer that you keep it.
Don't forget to buy the newspaper on Thursday morning.
to see the list of winners.
Yes, to see how much we've won.
Jean-Pierre asks for the bill.
Waiter, the bill, please.
But the boy doesn't pay attention to him.
The boy doesn't see him.
He doesn't look at Jean-Pierre.
He's looking elsewhere.
Here, elsewhere.
Hubert tries to get the boy's attention.
No effect.
So, when is this bill coming?
No effect. Nothing happens.
Press.
No effect.
Now there is an effect.
And there you have it, a punch that has no effect.
Hubert tries to get the boy's attention.
So, when will this bill arrive?
He's trying to catch his train.
The little boy is trying to get his father's attention.
Charlotte's sleep quality has declined.
She's going to try to sleep.
I'll try.
The boy heads towards another table.
He goes to another table.
He heads towards the chair.
They head towards the car.
They head towards the house.
Where are you going?
To be.
They head towards the house.
Robert signals to the boy.
He signals for a taxi.
She flags down a taxi.
Signs.
They are waving.
He gestures for her to come over.
He gestures for silence.
They gesture for silence.
He signals that he is going to turn.
Mireille tried to get the bill, but she was unsuccessful.
The boy did not bring the bill.
Please bring us the bill.
Jean-Pierre tried, but he didn't succeed either.
Waiter, the bill, please.
Robert tried his luck.
Could we have the bill, please?
Marie-Laure also tries her luck.
She is looking for the 10 of diamonds, but she doesn't know where it is.
So she takes her chance and she succeeds.
Let's see.
That's the 10 of diamonds.
She takes her chance there and she succeeds.
She's lucky. Jean-Pierre is taking his chance.
Excuse me, miss. Do you have a light, please?
But he did not succeed.
You can try your luck at roulette, or horse racing, or dice.
Robert tries his luck and he succeeds. The boy immediately gives him the bill.
There you go, sir. That'll be 135 francs.
Robert pays. The others turn away discreetly.
They're looking elsewhere.
They turn away.
Jean-Claude, would you please turn away discreetly?
They turn away modestly.
And you, sir, do you wish to turn away discreetly?
Here is a modest young girl.
Here is a modest young man.
To give Robert his change, the boy puts down his tray.
I take off my glasses.
The man in black placed his glasses on the table.
She placed her hand on the gentleman's.
Here, sir, would you like to place your hand on miss's?
Well, to learn French.
The customs officer places the suitcase on the table
The maid places the tureen on the table
And the boy places the glasses on the table
The boy drops a coin
Everyone rushes to pick it up
She hurries to catch their train
Look, there's a precipice.
And now Robert rushes headlong into the precipice.
He wants to jump from the sixth floor
The children rush onto the beach
They were thrown into the hole
The water looks good.
They rush into the water
They rush into the water. They rush into the water.
The phone rings. They rush to answer it.
They rush. But here, nobody rushes.
The phone rings and nobody rushes to answer.
Everyone rushes to pick up the coin.
There, they pick up Mireille's diary.
And they, they collect the toy cars
They pick up the papers
They are collecting papers
Cécile picks up the pieces
She picks up a pen
We shovel up the dead leaves.
And here, a Swiss Mercedes
pick up the two hitchhikers.
The tray falls and the glasses shatter into a thousand pieces.
Here too, the tray falls and the glasses break.
If I break it, I'll only owe you 200 francs?
But why do you want to break it?
To be sure, I want to be certain, you understand, I've already made so many mistakes.
Someone broke a window here.
When the Bélots bought their country house,
All the windows were broken. One window was broken.
He broke his leg. He broke his leg too.
And he broke both his legs.
He broke two legs. She broke one leg. In total, three broken legs.
What happened? I broke my arm.
And he has a broken nose.
To make an omelet, you need to break eggs.
No, no, no, you're going to break the bottle.
A pencil broken in two pieces.
One piece, another piece.
A piece of chalk.
A lump of sugar.
Pieces of bread.
Pieces of glass.
The boy picks up the pieces.
The glasses broke. Jean-Pierre's reaction is extremely vulgar.
Shit !
He said a word that shouldn't have been said, and it shouldn't have been said.
But there are French people who say so.
Oh shit !
An hour ago?
Shit! Shit!
Oh shit !
Oh, shit! Oh, shit! Oh, shit!
Don't walk so fast, damn it!
When you're well-mannered, you don't say that. You say "darn" or "mind."
I have to go back to the clinic tomorrow. Yes, for two days.
Two days, wow, but that's going to cost you a fortune.
Jean-Pierre is ill-mannered. But Hubert is well-mannered.
That's bad luck then.
Marie-Laure dropped the snack tray.
That's bad luck
Mireille is stuck on her exam
Oh darn, I'm stuck.
He missed his train
That's bad luck
We're on vacation and it's raining.
She died
That's bad luck
She fell pale again
Ah, that's bad luck
Oh, all these broken glasses!
That's bad luck
"No, on the contrary, it brings good luck, it's white glass."
That's not clear glass.
But that's white glass.
Well, they say that breaking white glass brings good luck.
A four-leaf clover also brings good luck.
A horseshoe also brings good luck.
But seeing a black cat, that brings bad luck.
Jean-Pierre is leaving.
Mireille is leaving
She's leaving
It's the verb "to leave".
Well, I'm leaving now.
She's leaving
Good morning
I'm leaving
Good evening, Dad
When are you coming back?
Sunday afternoon or evening
Now observe
Robert is leaving here
Goodbye, sir.
"Thank you, sir."
Here, Robert takes his leave of the courteous ones.
"What a delicious meal and what a lovely evening. I don't know how to thank you."
" See you soon. "
Jean-Pierre leaves, but Hubert takes his leave.
He's taking leave. It's a different style.
Robert notices several couples holding hands
Here is a young couple holding hands
A young couple holding hands
An older couple holding hands
They are holding hands
And here's a couple holding arms
And a couple holding each other by the waist
I've got you, you've got me by the chin
The first one to laugh will get a slap.
There are many couples holding hands
But Robert doesn't dare take Mireille's hand.
You remember in Chartres, he wanted to buy a small gift for Mireille
But he didn't dare.
He doesn't dare
What else is there?
My Val fell into the lady's bag over there.
Well, go ask her.
I don't dare.
Ah, you could have told me sooner.
I didn't dare, I was afraid of compromising myself.
The little girls don't dare go into the water.
On the sidewalk, there is a National Lottery stand.
next to a newsstand.
A newsstand.
A newsstand, a music kiosk and a lottery kiosk.
Robert wonders if it's possible to win the lottery.
Tell me, do you ever win this lottery?
I imagine so, but I've never won anything.
Here, Mireille won.
Who wins?
Here, Marie-Laure won.
You can win at racing, you can win at cards, you can win at roulette, you can win at horse races, but they, they didn't win.
But one can also win at another.
Oh, shit! Oh, shit!
But there are rivals!
Yes, there, that idiot, there, let me pass!
We won!
We won! We won! We changed!
Do you remember the nun?
She wanted to sell me lottery tickets to win an old 16th-century priory.
Robert and Mireille agree that the lottery is not very moral.
But Mireille says that part of the money goes to charitable organizations.
In any case, part of the money goes to a good cause.
For orphans, for tuberculosis patients.
Orphans, children who have no parents.
People with tuberculosis have a lung disease.
Mireille has never won anything in the lottery.
I must say that I have never bought tickets.
Perhaps that's why she never won anything.
Do you buy national lottery tickets?
Never.
Did you win the national lottery?
No, because I'm not buying tickets.
That professor is a bit dim. You don't buy tickets? Never.
And at the national lottery, you buy national lottery tickets?
Oh no, I don't believe it. You don't believe it. The lottery? No.
It doesn't work? No, it doesn't work.
We never win? Well no, I never win.
Even at the races. I was even surprised that I hadn't understood anything.
Robert and Mireille must be lucky right now.
With all this off-white glass
So, they decide to buy a ticket
Listen, next, you will play the role of Mireille
Okay, let's buy a ticket, shall we?
If that amuses you
Go ahead, choose.
Oh no, choose yourself
No, you
No, not me, I'm just not lucky at all.
Yes, you must be very lucky.
You just broke at least 12 white glasses
I didn't break them, you did.
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille.
Okay, let's buy a ticket, shall we?
If it amuses you, if it amuses you.
If that amuses you.
Go ahead, choose.
Oh no, choose yourself, oh no, choose yourself.
Oh no, choose yourself.
No, you.
No, not me, I'm just not lucky at all.
Yes, you must be very lucky.
You just broke at least 12 white glasses.
I didn't break them, you did.
No, it's not me, it's you.
Actually, no, it's Hubert, I saw him.
But that doesn't matter. Go ahead.
Take any number.
A random number. Any number.
Do you want a candy?
Oh yes.
Which one do you want?
I don't care, whichever one it is.
Take a card. Any card.
Go ahead, take any ticket as long as the last two digits add up to nine.
Provided that the last two digits add up to nine.
You can take any ticket, but the last two digits must add up to nine.
That is the only condition, the only restriction.
Hey Mum, could I watch the movie on TV tonight?
Yes, provided you have finished your homework.
Take any number as long as the last two digits add up to nine.
18, 27, 36, 45, 54, 63, 72, 81, 90.
Why is that?
But that's obvious!
The drinks cost exactly 135 francs. 3 and 1, 4 and 5, 9.
The drinks cost 135 francs. That's expensive.
But these seats are inexpensive.
And this cheese costs 47.50 francs per kilo.
Mireille chooses a ticket with a pink baby doll on it.
Here are some dolls, a doll, a doll and a celluloid baby doll.
And there you have it, a real baby doll, in the flesh.
And here are some babies in a nursery.
On the ticket, there is a pink baby doll on a pale blue background, a pale blue sweater and a dark blue sweater, a pale green skirt, a dark green skirt.
Robert would like Mireille to keep the ticket.
Here, keep it.
Oh no, not me, watch out.
Marie-Laure would really like Mireille's earrings.
Look at.
Wow, they're great.
Will you give them to me?
No, you're dreaming. That's not right, no, why would I give them to you?
But Mireille doesn't give them to him.
She keeps them.
And here, Marie-Laure gives Mireille a candy
and she keeps the others.
You take this candy and I'll take the others.
It's impossible to be that selfish.
Here, you can keep it.
She only has one candy left. So she keeps it.
Give me a chocolate.
I only have one left.
I'll buy it from you.
How much ?
50 cents.
I'm sorry. This chocolate is not for sale. I'm keeping it.
Now listen, observe, reflect, and speak.
Is the boy looking at the table where Robert and Mireille are, or is he looking elsewhere?
He's looking elsewhere.
Are Robert's friends turning away or are they taking an interest in what is happening?
They turn away.
Does the boy put down his tray or does he pick it up?
they put it
They ask, does Jean-Claude pick up the newspaper or does he...
Forget it, he'll pick it up, he'll pick it up, according to Mireille, if we break some
White glass, does it bring good luck or bad luck? It brings good luck.
Happiness. Look at Jean-Pierre. Is he leaving or is he taking his leave? He's leaving. He's leaving. And Hubert? He's taking his leave. Goodbye, my dear. He's taking his leave. Goodbye, everyone.
Why doesn't Robert take Mireille's hand?
He doesn't dare.
What is it? A newsstand or a toasted sandwich stand?
A newsstand.
A newsstand. Very well. And this?
A National Lottery stand.
A National Lottery stand. That's it.
Shall we go and buy a National Lottery ticket?
I don't like it very much.
No, it's a bit against my principles.
That's not exactly in line with my principles either.
But I would need some fresh cash.
Yes, okay, if you want.
Are you two still here?
It's getting late, come on, we need to go to bed.
Okay, take your leave.
Say goodbye.
Bye.
Bye !
HI !
...
Subtitles ST' 501
the Ministry of Culture and Communication,
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.