Subtitles ST' 501
We need to watch and get involved.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
They won the lottery. 40,000 francs.
But how to spend them?
Robert wants to travel around France.
Mireille will not commit to it, but she will be looking at the camping equipment.
They're taking a taxi.
But the man in black, already inside, tries to push Mireille.
Thursday morning at 7:15 a.m., the phone rings at the bike shop. Mireille comes in, half asleep.
We won on the device, we won, what won, us, you and
And me?
Have we won anything?
What have we gained?
400 000 francs !
Yes, it's in the newspaper!
All tickets ending with the numbers 80 to 27 win 400,000 francs!
400,000 bucks?
Does this lottery ticket win 400,000 francs?
But you only bought a tenth!
That's clever!
I'm taking the time to choose a winning ticket for the first time in my life, and you're only buying a tenth!
That's only 40,000 francs.
What is this all about?
Yes, what we bought the other day wasn't a whole ticket, it was only a tenth.
The ticket won 400,000 francs.
Each tenth earned 400,000 francs divided by 10.
That makes 40,000.
That's it, right?
You mean we only won 40,000 francs?
Yes, indeed.
Note that 40,000 francs isn't so bad.
That's already pretty good.
Now you're rich. What are you going to do with all that money?
I don't know what you're suggesting, but you could support an opera dancer.
which is from the last century where you could buy a deserted island in the Pacific, we're going to
Exploring the Amazon's springs is a common practice these days.
With 40,000 francs you won't get far, it's expensive for Amazon, no, anyway, America
France, you know, I know it a little.
But I had other plans for this summer.
I had thought of Yugoslavia, or Sweden,
or the Zambezi Falls, or the Ingoissu Falls,
or Niagara Falls.
You see, what attracted me was more the wild nature,
the great American wilderness.
Listen, we need to talk about this, but not on the phone.
Couldn't we meet up?
When ?
NOW.
No, listen, have you seen what time it is?
It's not even 7:30.
I'm not even dressed yet and I have to make Marie-Laure lunch.
Okay, so at 9am?
At, say, 10 a.m., in Luxembourg, near the Medici fountain.
Okay, fine.
So, see you soon, goodbye.
Mireille immediately called Hubert.
Hello, Hubert? What are you doing at noon?
Are you free? Shall we have lunch together?
Where?
At Angelina's on Rue de Rivoli.
Okay, if you want.
At half past noon, at Angelina's.
Kisses, see you later.
Hello.
And Mireille will prepare breakfast for Marie-Laure.
So, Marilo, is that it?
Are you ready?
Yeah, I'm coming!
I can't find my French book!
Hurry!
Marie-Laure sits down in front of her bowl of hot chocolate at the kitchen table.
And makes a slice of bread with a bit of jam on the bottom.
Jam is like culture
The less you have, the more you spread it out.
As Aunt Georgette says
Robert, on the other hand, will be there from 10:50 AM.
He paced back and forth in front of the Medici fountain.
He has already bought a map of the entire French road network, the Michelin map number 989.
Finally, at 10:10, Mireille arrives.
So, you're here, you took your time? Listen, here's what I propose.
With our 40,000 francs, we rented a car and hit the road.
And now, gently. Don't get too excited.
But, old butterfly, I haven't told you yet that I'm leaving.
You can't let me go alone. I'd get lost.
You know very well that I came to France to find myself.
You'll see, it will be a lot of fun.
We'll go wherever we want.
You can stop at youth hostels.
Apparently it's very cheap.
Camping will be possible.
And then, from time to time, with all the money we have,
We will be able to stay in the palaces.
Just to see the look on the customers' faces when they see us arrive
with our backpacks, sleeping bags and three-week-old beards.
But I have no intention of growing a beard.
And besides, I do have a sleeping bag, like all the young ladies from good families.
but I don't have a backpack
And you know, I don't have much camping equipment.
No problem, it's simple, you just have to buy some
If you want, but there's no rush.
In any case, I can't leave for another 15 days.
I have an exam to take on Monday at 8
And then I have to say goodbye to my children.
Which children?
a group of kids I look after
But if you like, in the meantime, we can go for a stroll in a department store.
If it amuses you, it doesn't commit you to anything.
Let's take a taxi.
Now that we're rolling in money, we can afford this luxury.
We're going to take a taxi.
Hey, here's one.
Mireille opens the car door and reverses with a scream.
What is it?
Nothing, it was taken, there was someone inside.
A strange-looking guy dressed all in black
I think I've seen it somewhere before.
He acted as if he wanted to grab my arm and force me into the taxi
Your sex
No, I assure you, he came towards me.
A horrible hairy hand
With mourning nails
Bizarre
When the phone rings at the bike shop, it's very early.
It's only 7:15. Mireille was still asleep. The phone woke her up. She arrives half asleep. She's still half asleep. Half.
This is a map of the whole of France.
And that's the southern half.
And that's the northern half.
That's a whole pancake.
And that's half of it.
That's a glass that's full.
And that's a glass that's half full.
That's an empty glass.
And that's a glass that's half empty.
Now, look closely.
Is that glass half empty or half full?
Okay, moving on.
Look at the Arc de Triomphe. It's sinking.
Now it's halfway in.
Centaurs are half man, half horse.
And mermaids are half woman and half fish.
And Mireille is half awake and half asleep.
Robert and Mireille won the lottery.
Yes, it's in the newspaper. All tickets ending with the number 81-27 win 400,000 francs.
They won because their number ends with 81-27.
This number here ends with 4.
This number ends with 0.
A mermaid starts with a woman's head and ends with a fish tail.
And large meals always end with speeches.
We still need to give them the means to be happy.
That's it, the show is over.
Here too, the show is over.
The lottery ticket won 400,000 francs.
400,000 francs? This lottery ticket wins 400,000 francs?
400,000 bucks.
Don't you have 5 bucks so I can fill it up?
Listen to this exchange between Robert and Mireille.
Then, you will play the role of Mireille.
We won.
But who won?
Us, you and me.
What have we gained?
400 000 francs.
Yes, it's in the newspaper.
All tickets ending with the numbers 80 to 27 win 400,000 francs.
400,000 bucks?
This lottery ticket wins 400,000 francs.
Now, it's your turn.
You are Mireille.
We won.
Us, you and me.
What have we gained?
400 000 francs.
Yes, it's in the newspaper.
All tickets ending with the numbers 80 to 27 win 400,000 francs.
400,000 francs? This lottery ticket wins 400,000 francs.
But you only bought a tenth. That's clever then.
Mireille is not happy because Robert only bought a tenth.
I'm taking the time to choose a winning ticket for the first time in my life, and you're only buying a tenth.
She took the time to choose a winning ticket.
She didn't choose just any ticket, no.
She chose a winning ticket.
She made a special effort to choose this ticket.
She took the time to choose a winning ticket.
Poor Mireille is making a lot of effort.
She is in a lot of pain.
I'm taking the time to prepare your breakfast.
You could at least take the trouble to put the bowls on the table.
The lottery ticket won 400,000 francs.
400,000 francs is a lot.
If Robert and Mireille had won 400,000 francs, they would be rolling in money.
Gold.
Here's someone who's rolling in money.
But Robert didn't buy a whole ticket.
He only bought a tenth.
So it's only 40,000 francs, but you're rolling in money, oh well, it doesn't matter
420 francs isn't so bad, 420 francs for a little girl like
Marie Laure, it's not so bad, it's actually quite good, and 40,000 francs for
Robert Emiré, it's not so bad either, 40 thousand is already quite a lot
France isn't so bad. That's already something.
Now you're rich. What are you going to do with all that money?
Now you're rich.
What are you going to do with this money?
Marie-Laure has 420 francs. What is she going to do with this 420 francs?
Buying a bicycle?
You'll be able to afford a bicycle.
With 420 francs? No, I doubt it.
Look at Marie-Laure here
She doesn't know what she did with her Asterix.
Ah, there he is!
Now it's his chocolates she can't find
What did you do with my chocolates?
I put them there
What could Robert do with that money?
Well, he could go up the Amazon.
Going up the Amazon is very common, it's fashionable.
Striped swimsuits? No, that's not done anymore.
It's no longer fashionable
Crinolines are no longer in style either; they're not done anymore.
But dark glasses, yes, those are very common.
It's fashionable
Second homes and restored old farmhouses are also becoming very common.
This has become very common lately.
Sending flowers when you're invited to dinner, that's done too. It's customary. And kissing hands, yes, that's done sometimes, but not very often anymore. But shaking hands, now that's done. It's done all the time. Observe.
Well, you'll be able to support an opera dancer.
You could support an opera dancer, although that's not very common these days.
Although it's no longer done.
I'm not interested. Unless you come, of course.
Although that's not done anymore. Unless you come.
These are restrictions. Note the subjunctive mood.
"Although it's not done anymore, unless you come. Robert doesn't really want to go up the Amazon because it's not very convenient for swimming."
Because of the piranhas, small fish that eat the flesh and leave only the bones. He would prefer to explore France because it's less dangerous.
"Wouldn't you prefer we go explore France? It would be less dangerous."
But no, Mireille has other ideas for her vacation.
I had other plans for this summer.
I had thought of Yugoslavia.
Or Sweden.
Or perhaps the Zambezi Falls.
Or the Ingoissu Falls.
Or Niagara Falls.
You see, what attracted me was more the wild nature, the great American wilderness.
The wild, the vast American wilderness attracts Mireille. She is drawn to it. She longs to go there. Here, it's a shop window that attracts her. Here, it's she who attracts Jean-Pierre. Jean-Claude is drawn to something. There is something that attracts him.
Magnets attract iron objects
And sugar attracts ants.
Robert would like to see Mireille right away
But it's too early
It's not even 7:30.
I'm not even dressed.
She is not dressed
She is in a dressing gown
Here, she is dressed
Here, he is dressed
He is not dressed here.
Here, Mireille is not dressed.
But here, she is dressed.
I'm not even dressed yet and I have to make Marie-Laure lunch.
Mireille is taking care of Marie-Laure's breakfast.
She makes her lunch.
Marie-Laure spreads the jam on her bread.
There's almost no jam left in the jar.
So, she is forced to spread it out.
She spreads it out.
You can spread jam on it.
You can spread paint.
You can spread out a map.
Lace, to show them off.
That's a display of lace.
A display of gloves.
Here is a display of fruit.
One can also showcase one's culture and knowledge.
Look at Marie-Laure here.
She shows off her knowledge of geography.
The Alps, the Pyrenees, the Jura, the Ardennes, the Vosges mountains, the Massif Central.
Marie-Laure, Mont Blanc, altitude?
4807 meters.
People who are not very cultured, who don't know much, show off what they do know.
Jam is the same thing.
If you have a lot, you don't spread it out.
If we have less of it, we spread it out.
So, Marie-Laure, is that it? Are you ready?
Marie-Laure is not ready. She is not ready to leave.
But the scouts are always ready.
Dinner is ready.
Dinner's ready. Let's eat right away.
Here, Marie-Laure is ready to leave.
Robert is also ready to leave.
He has already bought a card.
He is waiting for Mireille.
He paces back and forth.
One step, two steps.
50 steps in one direction, 50 steps in the other.
He's pacing back and forth too.
Finally, Mireille arrives.
She arrives, but she is late.
It took her a while.
You took your time.
She's not in a hurry.
She takes her time.
Marie-Laure too.
Mireille is in no hurry.
But there's no rush.
There's no rush.
Marie-Laure, go do your homework.
Oh, but there's no rush.
Mireille thinks Robert is in too much of a hurry.
And now, take it easy, don't get too excited.
Gently.
Wait for me.
Oh, gently now.
back towards the back gently, gently, and gently, but gently she has
Gently, don't get too excited, a minute, a minute, a minute, there's a butterfly, that's it
Very pretty, but it doesn't wait, it's hard to catch.
Wait, wait, just a minute, and just a minute, okay, well, I'm going to do a
A trip to Luxembourg and, just a minute, you're the one doing the dishes
Today Robert suggests staying in youth hostels. A hostel is
Cheaper than a big hotel, youth hostels are very cheap, as is camping.
It's cheaper than a hotel, obviously. Camping is cheaper than going down to...
When you travel to France, do you stay in luxury hotels?
modest hotels, often at friends' houses or in small hotels, you do
Camping? No, you sometimes stay in youth hostels, no, Robert doesn't want to.
staying in luxury hotels from time to time just to see the faces of
customers to have fun like this here Marie Laure wants the earrings of
Mireille, not to keep them, no, no, no, just to see, just to see
The school's not for little girls, there's nothing to see, and then
From time to time, with all the money we have, we'll be able to go down to the
Palaces just to see the look on the guests' faces when they see us
landing with our backpacks, our sleeping bags and our three-inch beards
weeks a one-week beard a two-week beard a three-week beard
weeks but Mireille has no intention of letting it grow
The customers will make a funny face, Mireille doesn't have one
backpacks, but there's an easy solution, it's simple: just buy one, there isn't
If you buy nothing to eat, you just have to go to a restaurant. The car is...
If it breaks down, we can just ask Uncle Guillaume to lend us one of his.
Mireille has an exam by next Monday, but from Monday to next Monday.
Monday in eight days today next Monday of Monday in eight
Mireille is looking after a group of kids, kids, there are kids, a girl.
But I'm not a kid.
A kid, a kid, a kid, a kid, kids.
What are you doing ?
I'm taking care of my doll.
Oh, you're taking care of your doll.
Yes, I'm taking care of my doll, so what?
What exactly are you doing here? But I am in the service of Miss Winchester, she has
asked me to take care of his appointments while he was away. Here's your breakfast.
Oh, that's kind. Very kind. Really kind.
Mireille is willing to go for a walk in a shop.
Take a walk.
Aunt Georgette is taking Fido for a ride.
Okay, I'm going to take a trip to Luxembourg.
Robert takes a stroll down Rue Mouffetard.
But if you want, we can go for a walk in a department store.
If that amuses you.
It doesn't commit you to anything.
We are not obliged to buy anything.
With their 40,000 francs, Robert and Mireille are rolling in money.
They can afford a taxi. They can afford this luxury.
Look what I bought myself. You'll be able to buy yourself a bicycle.
Mireille bends down to get into the taxi.
He bends down to pick up the newspaper.
She bends down to pick up some papers.
Robert bends down to pick up a coin.
She bends down to pick up a pen.
Mireille bends down and then steps back.
He's backing away.
The car is reversing.
Back off!
He's backing away.
Move back towards the back.
Gently, gently.
Mireille stepped back because she saw a horrible hairy hand.
He's hairy. He's hairy too.
This hairy hand had mourning nails, all black.
This is a man in mourning.
A man in mourning.
A woman in mourning.
She is dressed entirely in black.
Now, observe and speak.
Is this glass completely empty or half empty?
Half empty.
Does this number begin with a 4 or does it end with a 4?
It ends with a 4.
Is this gentleman rolling in money or does he need money?
He's rolling in money.
Are swimsuits like that still fashionable or are they outdated?
That's no longer done.
Does sugar repel ants or attract them?
That attracts them.
Is Mireille ready to go out or is she not dressed?
She is not dressed.
What does Marie-Laure do with the jam?
She pulls them.
Look at Robert. Is he standing up or is he bending down?
They bend down.
And these people, do they stay in a luxury hotel or do they go camping?
They are camping.
What are you doing, Mr. Guignol?
I'm camping, Miss Mireille.
What? You're camping?
Yes, I go camping.
I can't afford palaces, Miss Mireille.
But really, Mr. Guignol, camping in the Luxembourg Gardens.
I can't go on the roads, me, Miss Mireille.
You need a car to travel on the roads.
I'm not rolling in money, Miss Mireille.
Okay, good evening, Miss Mireille. Good evening.
...
MFP subtitles.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada