Subtitles ST' 501
and absorb it.
Very soon, you will see what happens
and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Mireille tells Hubert that she won the lottery.
He is strongly disliked by the lottery.
despite the fact that he was known for gambling on horses.
Robert and a shoe salesman have a problem with sizes.
And Ante Georgette tells the story of the one who drifted away.
Before going to meet Hubert, Mireille will take a stroll through Place Vendôme.
She arrives at Angelina's place on Rue de Rivoli where Hubert is waiting for her for lunch.
You'll never guess, I'll give you a thousand guesses, since I'll never guess, tell me everything.
We immediately won the lottery, which is what Robert and I, by Jove, it's a disgrace!
The lottery is one of the most immoral institutions of our sad era; there is no
The lottery and horse racing are worse, but what's so shameful about the lottery?
First, it discourages the key virtues of our capitalist society.
Work, the economy, savings.
And besides, it encourages laziness.
Instead of relying on their work, people now rely only on their luck.
They live in anticipation of Thursday morning.
But I thought you were betting on the races at Longchamp, weren't you?
It's not the same thing.
Because I work to improve the knight race.
Meanwhile, Robert bravely tries to do some shopping.
It's in the shoe department at La Samaritaine.
Are you looking for boots?
No, I would like shoes that I can wear for driving and for walking.
Something that is sturdy, but not too heavy.
What is your shoe size?
Comment ?
What size shoe do you wear?
Ah, I wear size 11.5.
You guys at 11.5, you're joking.
You wear at least a size 43. I'd even say a 44.
I assure you, the last time I bought shoes,
It was in Boston this winter, it was 11.5.
Look, these are the ones I have on my feet.
Well, they had to be elastic.
They have grown since this winter.
From 11.5.
You're American, you don't devalue the dollar, but you've certainly devalued your shoe sizes.
Sit down so I can take your measurements.
44, exactly. That's what I thought.
I don't make mistakes often, I have a good eye for it.
A compass in the eye?
Doesn't that bother you when taking measurements?
Mireille arrives at Aunt Georgette's, still very excited.
Good morning.
Oh!
So, what did your father tell me?
Did you win the lottery?
Yes !
Winning the national lottery, my dream.
Today, it's only for young people.
Well,
The old folks have nothing left but to die in their corner
or sort lentils.
Okay, wait, I'll help you.
Ah no, there, no.
Ah, it was Georges who liked them, the lentils.
Georges ?
No, not your cousin, no.
Georges.
His name was Georges de Pignorolle.
You didn't know him.
Your parents didn't like him, they didn't want to see him.
What a handsome man.
Tall, dark-haired, distinguished.
I met him one evening on the Boulevard des Italiens.
We had a coffee, we understood each other.
We wanted to open a dog grooming salon together.
We had pooled our savings to buy a very good store.
Your father disagreed.
He was very unpleasant to Georges.
Georges couldn't stand it.
He left.
I never saw him again.
So, tell me, how much did you win in the lottery?
40 000 francs ?
What are you going to do with all that money?
I don't know.
I called Cécile earlier to tell her the news.
She advises me to keep the money for when I get married.
Her husband says I should buy some land.
But he says it's the safest investment.
Dad would like me to buy paintings that will be worth millions in ten years.
And what do you advise me to do?
Yeah, for me, it's all very selfish.
If I were you, I would make a donation to the animal shelter.
At the animal shelter, what is this?
The Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, let's see.
And then, you could help me with my dog ​​cemetery.
Right, Fido?
Do you want mountain boots?
No, I'm afraid it will be too heavy.
However, for walking, high-top shoes would be better, not low-top shoes.
This is what you need.
These are high-top shoes; they provide excellent ankle support.
But it's very flexible, very light.
You have non-slip seats.
With this, you can't slip.
Try them, you'll see.
How do they look on you?
Not bad, but the one on the left is a bit useful to me.
Oh, it's nothing, you get used to it.
How much are they worth?
450 francs.
The one on the right is really very good, but the one on the left is really useful to me.
And if I only took the one on the right, how much would it be?
450 francs, I'm sorry sir, but we don't sell them separately.
Really ?
Okay, so never mind, I'll take the pair.
The one on the right is really very good. I feel very comfortable there.
You don't need sandals, espadrilles, or slippers?
No, thank you. Not today.
Mireille has something extraordinary to announce.
It's so unexpected that she's sure Hubert will never guess.
Hubert, you'll never guess. I'll give you a thousand guesses.
I'll give you a thousand guesses. I bet you one to a thousand that you won't guess. I'll give you a thousand guesses.
We won the lottery.
Hubert doesn't like it. He's against the lottery.
It's a disgrace. The lottery is one of the most immoral institutions of our sad era.
Only the lottery and horse racing are worse.
The lottery is an immoral institution.
The lottery and the horse racing too
Lotto is a game, it's also a form of lottery.
And the tiercé is a bet on horse races
We're betting on three horses
According to Hubert, the lottery is immoral
That's not good
But the lottery, the horse races, that's even more immoral. It's worse. Six out of twenty has homework, that's not good. It's even bad. But two out of twenty is worse. Look at the traffic here. Bad. But here, it's worse.
Lotteries are immoral. Lotto and horse racing are even worse.
But only the lotto and the trifecta are worse than the lottery.
Only the lottery and horse racing are worse.
Listen to the dialogue between Mireille and Hubert. Then, you will play the role of Hubert.
Hubert, you'll never guess. I'll give you a thousand guesses.
Well, since I'll never guess, just tell me right now.
We won the lottery.
Who, us?
Robert and I, Pardy.
It's a disgrace.
Now it's your turn. Answer in Hubert's place.
Hubert, you'll never guess. I'll give you a thousand guesses.
Since I'll never guess, just tell me right now.
Since I'll never guess, tell me right away.
We won the lottery
Who, us?
Robert and I, Pordy
It's a disgrace, it's a disgrace
It's a disgrace
The lottery is one of the most immoral institutions of our sad era.
Only the lottery and horse racing are worse.
This discourages the core virtues of our capitalist society.
Work, the economy, savings.
Work is generally considered a virtue.
Working is good.
Being hardworking is a quality.
Charity, too, is a virtue.
Courage, too, is a virtue.
In the Christian tradition, it is said that virtuous people go to heaven.
And those who are not virtuous will go to hell.
In a capitalist society, saving is considered a virtue.
You need to save money to build up capital.
It needs to be deposited in a bank or savings bank.
What would you do if you inherited a lot of money?
Okay, firstly, I would put a lot of money in the bank. In addition to that, I would save it for my wedding.
We save money.
If we had too much, we would already be putting some in the bank.
And you, sir?
Oh, the same thing, at the bank.
Are you running a savings promotion?
Ah, of course, we put it in the bank, we make that money work for us.
Well, I'll put it in the, what, bank.
Work, economy, and saving are the fundamental virtues of capitalist society.
Lotteries discourage work and encourage laziness.
He doesn't like to work, he's lazy.
Look, everyone else is working, but Guillaume isn't.
He's rather lazy. Laziness is not good.
We must not encourage laziness. No, we must discourage laziness.
Look here. The karate instructor is encouraging his student.
Here, the spectators are cheering on the cyclists.
But he is discouraged.
She too is discouraged.
The lottery discourages work
People don't work because they're waiting to win the lottery.
They are counting on their luck
And Marie-Laure is counting on Mireille to do her duty for her.
Hey, look, I don't understand anything, what do I need to put?
I'm not the one who's going to do your homework.
Don't rely on me, do it yourself.
Marie-Laure forgets everything, you can't count on her
Didn't you buy the bread?
I forgot
We really can't count on you
People who buy lottery tickets rely on their luck
They live in anticipation of Thursday morning.
Because the lottery draw takes place on Wednesday
And you can find the winning numbers in Thursday's newspaper.
The 307! The 307!
Hubert criticizes the lottery.
Yet, he plays the races.
He bets on horses.
More...
It's not the same thing.
People buy lottery tickets to win money.
That's selfish.
Hubert, on the other hand, does not play the races to win money.
He's doing it for a good cause.
Because I work to improve the horse breed.
He is working to improve the horse breed.
Meanwhile, Robert is trying to buy shoes
He doesn't want boots for horseback riding
He wants shoes for walking
If you want to buy shoes in a store
You can be sure that you will be asked
What is your shoe size?
Or
What size shoe do you wear?
But people don't always know their shoe size.
They don't always know their shoe size.
What is your shoe size?
Oh, I have no idea. The question comes up every time I go into a shoe store, maybe around size 41 or 42.
In the United States, Robert wears a size 11.5 shoe. In the American system, his shoe size is 11.5. But in the French system, 11.5 is a very small shoe size.
In fact, Robert has big feet. In the French system, he wears a size 44. That's a large shoe size.
So that's a size 44.
a small shoe size
a large shoe size
Robert insists
the last time he bought shoes
it was 11.5
Look, those are the ones I have on my feet.
Well, they must have been elastic.
they have grown since this winter
Robert's shoes
grew up
Robert used to be small
and now he is tall
Finally, it is bigger.
The big ones.
Robert's shoes must have grown, probably because they were elastic.
That's elastic. Of course, it's elastic.
The salesman takes Robert's measurements.
Sit down so I can take your measurements.
He measures Robert's foot. Robert wears exactly a size 44.
That's what the seller had said.
44, that's right, that's what I thought.
I'm not often wrong, I have a good eye for detail.
He has a good eye for detail.
A compass, a compass, for taking measurements
The seller doesn't need a compass because he has a compass in his eye.
Mireille also has a good eye for detail.
How much do you think that is?
I'd say 83, between 83 and 85 cm, let's see 84, there you go, you have a good eye for it obviously
If you have a compass in your eye, it must be annoying even when you just have a tiny grain of dust.
A compass is bothered, but for him it's a fly that bothers him, and for him it's the
The light is bothering me, no, stop it, it's bothering me, it's the light that's bothering me
Stop, I'm telling you it bothers me, I'll draw you a little picture, but be quiet.
Now these two aren't going to shut up anytime soon, what ill-mannered people there are!
Even if you talk in the cinema, it bothers others; here it's Mireille who's bothering Marie-Laure, here it's
Jean-Pierre, who's bothering Robert, what do you want now? You're not going to, it's you guys today.
Hello, it's kind of you to have come. I was just thinking about you.
Move aside, you can see you're in the way.
Mireille went to tell Aunt Georgette that she had won the lottery.
But Aunt Georgette already knew that.
So, what did your father tell me?
Did you win the lottery?
Yes.
Did you win the lottery? Ah, that doesn't surprise me.
Only young people have a chance there.
Everything is for young people. There's nothing but young people.
Hey, what is it now?
Can't you fix that for me?
I'm fed up. Mireille, fix this for me.
Mireille, do my homework for me.
Mireille, give me a taste. There's only some for you.
I have other things to do than take care of you.
Today, it's only for young people.
Today, it's all about young people.
Everything is for the young. Nothing for the old.
Old people have no choice but to die in their corner.
Nobody cares about the old people. They can just die.
What are you doing? You're crazy! Are you out of your mind? You're going to kill him!
Mind your own business!
Look, he's got a flat tire.
Old people have no choice but to die in their corner.
A corner. Aunt Georgette is sorting lentils.
Not that one.
No, not that one.
beans, split peas, lentils, sorting lentils, these lentils make it
thinking of a certain Georges who loved them so much, those Georges who...
He loved lentils; what a handsome, tall, dark-haired, distinguished man I had met on the boulevard.
We were Italians, we had a coffee, we understood each other, we wanted to go up together
a dog grooming salon; we had pooled our savings to buy
a very good shop a hair salon a hair salon a salon
Your father didn't agree with the dog grooming; he was very unpleasant.
Georges couldn't stand it, he left. Mireille called
I called Cécile earlier to tell her the news.
to tell him the news, the news of course being that she has
won the lottery, Aunt Georgette, you know the news
Mireille won the lottery, you know, the new Mireille has a new
My boyfriend's name is Robert, he's American, Cécile's husband, and she advises...
Mireille wanted to buy a plot of land, a plot of land to build a house on. A plot of land
It's a good investment because the value of the land increases. Paintings are also a good investment.
Good investment. Aunt Georgette thinks investing is selfish. But it's good.
It's all so selfish. Marie-Laure is selfish; she keeps all her chocolates for herself, she doesn't want
Not giving them to the children is selfish. You give me a chocolate, they're mine, you can have them.
Give me one, what a selfish Aunt Georgette is advising Mireille to give some
donate the money to the animal shelter (SPA) or give him money.
for his dog cemetery and then you could help me with my dog ​​cemetery, here's one
A cemetery, a cemetery in Paris, a Basque cemetery, a military cemetery in northern France, a marine cemetery, a cemetery, a car cemetery.
Aunt Georgette runs a dog cemetery.
And what is Robert doing in the meantime?
He's still trying to buy shoes.
Do you want mountain boots?
No, he doesn't want hiking boots. He's afraid they'll be too heavy.
However, for walking, he would prefer high-top shoes, not low-top shoes.
The salesman offers Robert some very flexible shoes.
That's not flexible. But that, yes, that's flexible.
These shoes are very flexible because the upper is made of canvas and the sole is made of rubber.
The sole isn't that thick.
No, it's not very thick, but it's very solid.
The soles of the patogases are quite thick.
These are non-slip soles.
You remember, skidding.
Warning, danger of skidding.
The car skids.
The cyclist skids.
He skids.
He too went off the rails.
He slipped. Him too.
But with non-slip soles, you can't slip.
Robert tries on the shoes.
How do they look on you?
They suit her quite well.
The one on the right actually suits her very well.
Does this little black skirt suit you?
I think the other one suits you better.
Oh, does that look good on you?
Oh no, it's a change for you, but it suits you very well.
The shoe on the right fits him well, but the shoe on the left doesn't fit him so well.
She's squeezing it, it's too small.
It's tight.
He tightens the screws.
This shirt is tight.
Don't tighten it too much.
Pull in your stomach.
It's a greenhouse.
Do you remember sardines? They're packed tightly together.
And the people are packed in there too, packed like sardines.
Robert would only want to take the right shoe, which fits him so well, and not take the left shoe, which is too tight.
But that's not possible.
Frankly, I'm sorry, sir, but we don't sell them separately.
Oh well. Robert will take the pair. Too bad. It's a shame.
So what do we do? What if they don't come?
Never mind, I won't start until everyone is here.
Robert takes the pair of Patogas.
You don't need sandals, espadrilles, or slippers?
Sandals, no. Robert doesn't need sandals.
Espadrilles, no. Robert doesn't need espadrilles.
Slippers, no. Robert doesn't need slippers.
No, thank you. Not today.
Now, observe, reflect, and speak.
6 out of 20 for an assignment is bad.
But 2 out of 20 is...
Worse.
Are courage and charity flaws or virtues?
Virtues.
Does the lottery encourage laziness or hard work?
Laziness.
Are these shoes for walking or for horseback riding?
For walking.
When you go to buy shoes in a store, what are they asking you?
What size shoe do you wear?
Look at Robert over there. What's he doing?
He grew up.
Is this elastic or rigid?
Elastic.
What is the seller doing?
He is taking action.
What happened to the goldfish?
He died.
Where does this young woman work?
In a hair salon.
Are these shoes rigid or flexible?
Flexible.
Is that the sole or the upper part of the shoe?
The sole.
Look at this woman. Is the jacket too big for her or is it too tight?
She squeezes it.
Now you want to announce some extraordinary news to Mireille.
What do you tell him?
Miss Mireille, you'll never guess!
Since I'll never guess, tell me right now, Mr. Guignol!
Well, I'm going to take a little nap, Miss Mireille!
You're a lazybones, Mr. Guignol!
French subtitles?
...
MFP subtitles.
the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of Culture and Communication,
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust et le National Endowment for the Humanities.
French subtitles?