Subtitles ST' 501
and get involved.
Very soon, you will see what happens
and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
Uncle Guillaume encourages Mireille
to spend their lottery money on memorable food.
But Mireille prefers Robert's plan
to travel around France.
Robert continues to have misunderstandings
with the employees, this time on clothing.
And he takes a disgusting taxi route.
MFP subtitles.
Listen, we need to celebrate this, right?
And Uncle Guillaume invites Mireille to have tea at the Grande Cascade.
Four hours, is that okay with you?
Yes.
Okay, then, perfect, shall I come and pick you up?
No, no, I'll manage.
Are you sure?
Okay, then, at four o'clock.
Okay, see you later. Goodbye.
At four o'clock, Mireille arrives at the Grande Cascade tea room.
So, you won 40,000 francs?
What are you going to do with it?
I wonder about that.
Aunt Georgette would like me to give her money for her dog cemetery.
That's definitely her.
She's the spitting image of Georgette, that's true.
There are millions of children dying of hunger all over the world.
And all he cares about is ensuring a decent burial for deceased dogs.
What an old camel, that Georgette.
Oh, you're not being nice, uncle.
Aunt Paulette has another idea.
Yes ?
She says I should buy her old car.
Whoa there, watch out.
It's a very beautiful car, but it hasn't been driven since the exodus of 1940.
And as for a car, I can always lend you one.
You don't need to buy a car.
That includes insurance, gas, and repairs.
You'd be better off using your old uncle's.
Philippe advises me to buy shares on the stock exchange.
Ouch, watch out.
Ah yes, the stock market is falling right now.
It might not be a good investment.
Personally, I'd advise you to have a few good feasts.
with friends.
You could try all the restaurants
three stars in Paris.
You should keep the menus; they'll give you memories.
for your old age.
The good memories are still
the safest bet.
You know very well that I have to be careful
to my liver.
Another one of your mother's inventions.
Your liver isn't any worse than the 55 million
other French people.
You'll just have to do a treatment
other bichis.
You know very well that since Pétain,
Dad doesn't want to hear about Vichy at home anymore.
You still have Vittel, Evian, Badoit, Vals and Volvic left.
No, anyway, I have to say that the idea of ​​spending
three or four hundred francs for a meal,
I find it almost immoral.
No, you know, I think I'll take a trip to France instead.
with my American boyfriend.
You know, Robert, besides, the money is partly his.
He was the one who paid for the ticket.
Robert, in the men's clothing department.
We'll take care of you.
Non.
I would like a jacket.
Or a sports jacket, perhaps.
Something I could wear in the city.
And also for camping.
Do you have a particular color in mind?
No, not really.
I don't really care.
French blue, perhaps.
And above all, something that isn't too messy.
What size are you?
Honestly, I don't know.
Let me see, if you please, I'll take your chest measurement.
THANKS.
124.
Here, this one should suit you.
That's your size.
It's not really dark blue.
This is the only one we have in your size.
We're out of blue. This one is yellow and white.
That's what I thought, yes.
Here, give it a try.
It fits you like a glove. It's exactly what you need.
I still don't like the color. Well, with this, I won't go unnoticed.
You'll be able to see me from afar.
If I get lost, I'll be easily found.
I would also like a pair of trousers.
You need to do 88 as detailed.
Oh no, 83.
Here.
These are very nice corduroy trousers.
The color would go very well with your jacket.
Non.
Here, this is an article made of polyester.
It's a very beautiful fabric.
It holds the crease very well.
It is...
It's both, how should I put it...
How should I put it...
Well, I would simply say...
Sporty and dressy.
Do you want to try it?
No, no, it's time to go, I'll take it.
You don't need a shirt?
It's very good for the trip.
It washes very easily and dries in a few minutes.
No, thank you.
Underwear?
I don't have any underwear.
Underwear, then?
I don't have any more underwear either.
So, what are you wearing?
You're not wearing anything underneath?
Yes, I do wear those kinds of little things...
Yes, that's what I was saying, briefs.
But I think briefs are for ladies.
Oh yes, we also have some for the ladies. But they're with lace. It's more feminine.
Uh, no thanks. With or without lace, I have everything I need.
As he left the store, Robert spotted a taxi that seemed to be waiting. He got in and gave the address of the Latin home.
The taxi starts immediately and speeds through Parisian traffic with alarming speed and clumsiness.
It advances in fits and starts.
It is a succession of short accelerations and longer accelerations.
Intrigued and vaguely worried, Robert seeks the cause of this phenomenon.
He notices that it is indeed the driver's foot that is causing irregular jerking to the accelerator.
This foot is wearing a black shoe, over which appears a red sock.
On closer inspection, Robert realizes that it is actually the end of a pair of long red wool underpants.
Intrigued and worried, Robert is even more so when he sees in the rearview mirror that the driver blinks one eye then the other in perfect synchronization with the acceleration.
Suddenly, Robert realizes that they are passing by the Saint-Lazare train station.
"But where are you going? I told you Rue du Somme-Rare, it's the opposite direction."
The driver does not respond, but gives a tremendous burst of acceleration.
Robert, being a cautious young man, takes advantage of the interval between two accelerations to jump out of the moving taxi.
And this one drives off, flashing its turn signals in Morse code.
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
birthday. Here, we're celebrating Marie-Laure's birthday. Here, we're celebrating July 14th. It's
The national holiday in France. Here, we're celebrating the arrival of a new director. Here, we're celebrating
Christmas. Here too, we celebrate Christmas. And here, we celebrate the New Year, the New Year.
New Year's Day. And look at them, they won the lottery, so they're going to celebrate.
Listen to the conversation between Mireille and Uncle Guillaume, then you will play the role of
Uncle Guillaume, I just won forty thousand francs in the national lottery, no joke.
But that's fantastic! And there you go, rich! Listen, we have to celebrate this! Now it's your turn, you are...
Uncle Guillaume, I just won forty thousand francs in the lottery.
national seems, but that's fantastic and
Well, listen, we need to celebrate, it seems, but it's fantastic!
Well, listen up, we need to celebrate!
Uncle Guillaume invited Mireille for tea.
They too are having tea.
It looks delicious.
It's a little bit of a mix of Earl Grey and Darjeeling.
Uncle Guillaume invited Mireille to a very chic place.
A restaurant and tea room in the Bois de Boulogne, near the Longchamp racecourse.
Uncle Guillaume asks Mireille what she's going to do with the money she earned
What are you going to do with it?
Well, I wonder.
Aunt Georgette would like me to give her money for her dog cemetery
Uncle Guillaume makes fun of Aunt Georgette
Ah, that's her, she's the spitting image of Georgette.
Ah, that's definitely her, she's the spitting image of Georgette!
That's her to a T, it looks just like her.
Look at that, it's Aunt Georgette
And does this look like him?
Yes, that's her exactly.
Look how much Cécile resembles Mireille in this photo.
That's Mireille to a T.
Spitting through, from the verb to spit
Do you remember? A window spewing flames
And here's someone breathing fire
But in the subway, it is forbidden to spit, even fire.
Uncle Guillaume makes fun of Aunt Georgette
Because she runs a dog cemetery
All he cares about is ensuring a decent burial for the deceased dog
A burial site, a grave.
In a cemetery, there are graves.
This is Chopin's tomb, his burial place at Père Lachaise.
Aunt Georgette is in charge of providing decent burials.
to the deceased dogs, to the pooches.
Here's a little dog.
Aunt Georgette has a dog.
And Marie-Laure has a tutu, because she does dance.
A dog, a tutu.
Uncle Guillaume is not at all nice to his sister.
He calls her an old camel.
What an old camel, Tête Georgette!
Help me! Figure it out yourself!
Old camel!
Here's a camel.
What an old camel, Tête Georgette!
Aunt Paulette would like Mireille to buy her car.
But Uncle Guillaume disagrees.
He advises Mireille not to buy it.
Be careful.
Whoa there, watch out.
Be careful. Pay attention.
Jean-Claude, be careful.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She's suspicious.
Can you lend me 50 francs?
Will you give them back to me?
Of course I'll give them back to you.
When ?
Tomorrow morning.
On ?
She's cautious, that little girl. She's wary.
She's right. You always have to be wary.
You never know what might happen.
Look at him, he wasn't suspicious, and this is what happened to him.
One must always be wary.
Look at him, he's running calmly, he's not suspicious, and BANG!
There's a string.
Be careful, little Anne.
One must always be wary.
You shouldn't accept anything from a stranger.
That's a suspicious father.
What is that croissant?
Did your mother give you the money?
No, it was Mr. Alain who took it.
I already told you not to accept anything from a man you don't know, right?
So who lives here?
He is suspicious.
It's best if I leave.
Mireille should be wary because Aunt Paulette's car is a very beautiful car, but it is old.
And it hasn't been driven since the exodus of 1940.
In 1940, the Germans invaded France
and the population took to the roads to flee the Germans.
Mireille doesn't need to buy Aunt Paulette's old car.
You don't need to buy a car.
She can still use Uncle Guillaume's car.
You'd be better off using your old uncle's.
That's Uncle Guillaume's car.
Mireille uses Uncle Guillaume's car.
That's a pen.
She uses a pen to write.
That's a wrench.
Marie-Laure uses an adjustable wrench
That's a corkscrew.
Mr. Courtois uses a corkscrew
He uses a shovel to collect the dead leaves.
That's a hammer.
They use a hammer
He uses a hammer
And he uses an iron bar to open the door; Mireille's cousin advises him
to buy shares on the stock exchange, one buys and sells securities, shares of
Different companies, but Uncle Guillaume doesn't agree. Watch out, the stock market is falling.
It goes up, it goes down. The temperature rises, the temperature falls.
If stock market values ​​fall, it's not a good investment.
But if they go up, it's a good investment.
In general, real estate, land, houses, apartments, and construction are a good investment.
Uncle Guillaume advises Mireille to have some good feasts with friends
I would advise you to have some good meals with friends instead.
A feast, now that's a feast, a feast, a good meal with friends
Uncle Guillaume advises Mireille to go and enjoy some good meals in three-star restaurants
In the Michelin Guide, very good restaurants have one star.
The very, very good restaurants have two stars.
And exceptional restaurants have three stars.
One star
The Place de l'Étoile in Paris is shaped like a star.
You could try all the three-star restaurants in Paris.
You would keep the menus; they would give you memories for your old age.
Mireille is worried about her liver
But you know I have to take care of my liver.
Feasting is not good for the liver
The liver.
Many French people have liver problems because of goletons.
Prometheus, on the other hand, had liver problems because of the eagle.
If you have liver pain, you should drink mineral water such as Vichy water.
Then all you have to do is a Vichy water cure.
Unfortunately, Mr. Bello doesn't want to hear anything about Vichy.
He doesn't want to hear about it. He hates it.
"You know very well that ever since Pétain, Dad doesn't want to hear about Vichy at home anymore."
Not because of the water, but because of Marshal Pétain.
Because during the German occupation, Pétain had established his government in Vichy.
And Mr. Belleau was against Pétain and collaboration with the Germans.
Fortunately, there is plenty of mineral water in France.
"Well, you still have Vittel, Evian, Badoit, Vals and Volvic."
In any case, Mireille doesn't want to spend her money on food.
No, you know, I think I'm going to take a trip to France with my American boyfriend instead.
And you, what would you do if you had won the lottery?
A very beautiful trip.
I too would love to visit America.
Me too.
I think I would buy a lot of books.
Robert, meanwhile, is trying to buy a jacket to go and explore France.
Do you have a particular color in mind?
No, not really.
I don't really care.
He doesn't care, it doesn't matter.
Which one do you want?
Oh, I don't care.
Okay, so I'll take the cream puff.
Oh, that's just the one I wanted.
You need to know, do you care or not?
I don't mind. I prefer cream puffs.
Non.
You should have told me if you didn't care.
I don't mind, so I'll have the chocolate éclair.
Is that okay with you?
He doesn't mind, but he doesn't want something that's too messy.
Not white, for example.
Because white gets dirty easily.
It gets dirty easily.
White gets dirty easily.
Oyster farming is a dirty job.
It's the halls.
Replacing roof tiles is also a dirty job.
You shouldn't be afraid of getting tired or getting dirty.
The children get dirty.
Dark blue doesn't show dirt too much.
But light blue gets dirty easily.
Robert wants dark blue, but he doesn't know his size.
Excuse me, I'm going to take your chest measurement.
Listen to the conversation between the salesman and Robert.
Next, you will play the role of Robert.
Are we taking care of you?
No, I would like a jacket.
Do you have a particular color in mind?
I don't care.
Something that isn't too messy.
Now it's your turn, you are Robert.
Are we taking care of you?
No, I'd like a jacket. No, I'd like a jacket. No, I'd like a...
jacket, you're set on a particular color
I don't mind if it's not too messy.
something that isn't too messy
I don't care
Robert tries on a jacket
He puts it on to try it out.
Colette tries on a Mireille sweater
And he's trying on a t-shirt
and this lady is trying on a jacket
in a fitting room
but it doesn't suit her
she is too small
The dress fits very well here.
Turn around.
Very nice.
Oh, does that look good on you?
Oh no, it's a change for you, but it suits you very well.
This little black skirt suits me well.
But Mireille's sweater looks very good on Colette.
It fits him like a glove.
Oh, it fits you like a glove.
Like a glove.
It's exactly your size.
According to the seller, the jacket fits Robert like a glove.
"It fits you like a glove."
But Robert doesn't like the color.
"I still don't like the color. But with this, I won't go unnoticed. I'll be visible from afar. If I get lost, I'll be easily found."
Then Robert looks at the trousers.
"Here, have you got a very nice pair of corduroy trousers. Here, have you got an item made of polyester."
Loom, fabric. A fabric merchant, fabrics, fabrics. There are fabrics of
Cotton, silk fabrics, wool fabrics, there you go, wool, the wool of buttons. The
Sweaters are made of wool, but it's not fabric, it's knit. Polyester, dacron, nylon,
It's convenient because it dries quickly.
Here's a shirt drying.
Laundry drying.
A hair dryer.
Sec.
A cake, a dry cake.
A tree, a dry tree.
A humid climate, a dry climate.
Then the salesman offers Robert some underwear.
Underwear?
Robert doesn't understand because he thinks in English.
In English, briefs are for ladies.
Me, but I don't wear underwear.
So, what are you wearing?
You're not wearing anything underneath?
He doesn't want any underwear.
He doesn't want any underwear either.
So, he leaves.
And since he's rich, he takes a taxi.
The driver of this taxi is strange.
He drives very fast and very clumsily.
He is clumsy.
Jean-Claude is on the right. Oh, there, he's clumsy.
Skill, clumsiness. He's a bit clumsy.
She's clumsy. She's clumsy too.
The taxi moves forward in erratic leaps. They too are making erratic leaps.
Robert sees in the rearview mirror that the driver blinks his eyes
A rearview mirror, a rearview mirror, a rearview mirror, a rearview mirror
Okay, enough about rearview mirrors.
Are you out of your mind?
Robert took a taxi from La Samaritaine.
He wants to go to his hotel on Somrar Street
And suddenly, he realizes they are at the Saint-Lazare train station, here
It's the opposite. So Robert jumps out while it's moving. He wants to get in while it's moving. And the taxi drives off, flashing its turn signals like Morse code.
Here, the plane is getting closer, and there, it's moving away.
Now listen, watch, think, and speak.
Are they having tea or a feast?
They are having tea.
Is it a puppy or a tutu?
A little dog.
And this?
A tutu.
Is that a camel or a dog?
A camel.
A camel, very good.
Does Jean-Claude trust him or is he suspicious?
He is suspicious.
Is the stock market falling or rising?
It's decreasing.
Is that wool or cotton?
Wool.
wool
If you're at La Samaritaine, is the Saint-Lazare train station on the same side as the Latin Quarter, or is it on the opposite side?
It's the opposite, it's the opposite.
If you are French and you eat too much and drink too much wine, or do you have pain
In the liver
Oh dear, you're not well, Mr. Guignol, you're drinking too much! You need to take a Vichy water cure, Mr. Guignol!
Hey, I don't really like that.
Well then, a meat water cure, Mr. Guignol.
I don't like it much either.
But then, Mr. Guignol, there's badoit.
I don't like mineral water.
I prefer Beaujolais.
Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
and other Annenberg Media programs,
call 1-800-LEARNER
and visit us at www.learner.org.