Subtitles ST' 501
and fly away. Very soon you will see what happens and you will be
able to say a few words in French yourself. Hubert offers his little car and
himself for the trip around France. Colette decides to be the fourth.
Then Mireille invites another friend, the leftist Jean-Michel. After much
quick conversation, it allows everyone to accept what is promised to be a
a welcoming and persuasive quintet.
I don't see why I would get bored with him.
No, on the contrary, travelling in France with a foreigner,
to show him what we like,
That must be exciting.
And how do you plan to travel around France?
With a car that we will rent.
We will spend the nights sleeping,
under a tree,
amidst the flowers and small birds,
or perhaps in a good hotel.
when we feel the need to take a shower.
Oh, but a car rental,
It's going to cost you an arm and a leg.
You're not thinking about it.
Listen, I have an idea
I just bought a Méhari
A camel?
No, not a Méhari, a Méhari
A car will be perfect for the summer.
This is exactly what you need
I'll bring it tomorrow, you'll see.
That's nice, but I don't know if we should
Yes, yes, you'll see, it's a fantastic little car
It fits everywhere
We'll have a blast!
Oh, so you'd be coming with us?
Yes, of course.
A little later, Mireille calls Colette.
Hello, Colette? Are you coming to Paris this afternoon?
I absolutely must see you. It's urgent.
Okay, at 4 o'clock, at Passion du Fruit.
It's Quai de la Tournelle.
Okay, I'll wait for you. I'm giving you a kiss. Bye.
A little later, Colette and Mireille find themselves drawn together by their passion for fruit.
Good morning.
How are you ?
Okay. So, what's going on?
Well, there you have it. But first, tell me, do you have any firm plans for the summer?
No, not really.
That's amazing. So listen, I have something to propose to you.
First, I have to tell you that if you can accept, you'll make me a huge fan.
Mireille then tells Colette the story of the broken white glass, of the lottery ticket,
the travel plan with Robert and Hubert's intrusion.
You can imagine that I'm not dying to find myself alone between Hubert and my American.
If you could come with us, that would solve everything and we could really have some fun.
When would you leave? And for how long?
We would leave in about two weeks and come back, let's say, at the end of August.
Unless we have enough before then.
That could be fun.
Anyway, I have no desire to stay in Provins with my parents.
Listen, yes, in principle, I accept.
Fantastic, you saved my life.
And with four people, it will surely be more interesting.
The following Sunday, Mireille goes to see her children.
It's a group of girls and boys that she looked after last summer.
as a counselor at a summer camp.
There was also Jean-Michel as an instructor, a very friendly young man, with leftist leanings, whom the children adored.
At the end of the summer, Mireille and Jean-Michel decided to stay in touch with the group and bring them together every Sunday morning.
It was to this weekly meeting that Mireille went today.
After the meeting...
I have to tell you, I don't think I'll be able to go to summer camp this summer.
I'm exhausted, I can't take it anymore.
I need to take a real vacation. You see, I'm changing my perspective a bit.
It's true you look tired, but do you take vitamins?
No, doctor.
I also need a change of scenery.
Actually, I wanted to tell you, I won't be able to come after next Sunday.
And Mireille tells Jean-Michel about her plans for the summer.
She doesn't mention the broken white glass, nor the lottery.
but she talks about the planned trip with Robert, Hubert's intrusion, and the call to Colette.
And then suddenly...
I'm thinking about it, why don't you come with us?
That's what would take your mind off things.
Seriously, are you kidding me?
Can you picture me, between that degenerate aristocrat and that American savage?
What would I be doing in that mess?
First of all, it's not a galley, it's a mehari.
And Hubert is not degenerate at all, I assure you.
And my American is anything but a savage.
He is a very educated, very cultured boy.
You'll be able to talk to him, you'll see.
This will be very interesting for both of them.
Come on, come with us.
With five of us, we'll have a blast.
And Mireille finally convinced Jean-Michel.
Now, they need to explain to Robert that they're going to leave as a group of five.
and to Hubert that there will be five people in his little Méhari.
Well, you know, our projects are taking shape.
In fact, everything is arranged.
I have a lot of good news.
First, Hubert, our priests, Sam and Harry.
That's nice.
But I don't know if we should...
Naturally, he will come with us.
Ah.
I also thought I should be wary of that camel.
No, seriously, I don't think it works very well with three people.
That's what I thought too.
So, I invited Colette to come and she accepted.
Damn. Will there be four of us?
No, you'll see, there won't be four of us, there will be five.
Because I also invited a wonderful, super nice guy.
His name is Jean-Michel.
I'm sure you'll like it.
He's a very interesting guy.
He is a Trotskyist or a Guevarist or something like that.
With Hubert being rather right-wing, sparks are going to fly.
This will be very interesting for you.
That, I have no doubt about.
But I would still have preferred solitude for two.
There you go, she's pretty, isn't she?
Mireille, Hubert and the Méhari.
This is the camel for long summer hikes.
Simple, durable, versatile.
Do you want to try it?
So I spoke to Robert, it's settled, he agrees
But we thought that it might not work very well with three people
As well as I asked Colette to accompany us
And she was kind enough to accept
But the Méhari isn't expandable.
With four of us, we'll be packed in like sardines.
Malon, Hubert, I know you
Despite your innocent, childlike demeanor
I wouldn't be surprised if you were upset about being squeezed against Colette.
Tight as it is, my dear Mireille, I would have preferred it to be against you
Oh, and also, before I forget, I had my boyfriend yesterday.
You know, Jean-Michel, he seemed really depressed
It's good that I invited him to come too.
But that boy is a dangerous anarchist.
He's not an anarchist at all, he's a Marxist.
I thought it would balance out your outdated opinions.
But where do you want to put all those people?
The Méhari doesn't have an upper deck, I'll have you know.
Okay, we might be a little cramped, but it doesn't matter.
The crazier you are, the more you laugh, as my Aunt Georgette says.
And she doesn't laugh much, poor thing.
Are you going to let me stay home?
Yes.
Hubert thinks that Mireille shouldn't leave alone with Robert.
But why not?
But after two days, you'll be bored to death.
I don't see why I would get bored with him.
It's the verb "s'ennuyer" (to be bored). Do you remember?
Jean-Pierre is bored. He looks bored.
I'm bored.
She's bored.
I'm bored. There's nothing to do.
And he's bored there? No, he's having fun.
He's bored. But she's having fun.
Oh, because I'm having fun. I've never had so much fun.
They are having fun too.
Are they bored or are they having fun?
They are having fun.
Mireille won't be bored.
No, on the contrary, travelling with a stranger, showing them everything you love, must be exciting.
And how do you plan to travel around France?
The Hexagon is France.
Mireille and Robert are going to travel to France
They will travel across France
When you travel, you can spend the night in a hotel, in a tent, or even in the middle of a field, outdoors.
Here are fields, a field, a field, a field, a field
And they run across the field.
We will spend the nights in the open field, under a tree, surrounded by flowers and small birds.
Or perhaps in a nice hotel, when we feel the need to take a shower.
Look at Robert and Mireille there. They're hot, they're dirty, they feel the need to take a shower.
It's the verb "to feel".
Look at Mireille here, she's tired
She feels the need to rest
It's cold here, but she doesn't feel the cold.
But here, she feels the cold.
To leave, Robert and Mireille are going to rent a car.
But Hubert doesn't think it's a good idea.
Because it's going to cost them an arm and a leg.
But renting a car is going to cost you an arm and a leg.
It's going to cost a lot, a horribly lot.
The eyes of the head.
An Alpine Renault, you think that's expensive?
Probably very expensive.
It costs an arm and a leg.
Hubert has a better idea.
Listen, I have an idea.
An idea, remember?
I have an idea.
Let's play portrait.
Yes, that's an idea.
Is this a good idea?
Yes, it's funny the ideas we have when we're little.
Newton had an idea.
I, too, had some rather bizarre ideas.
What are you reading?
Lacan.
What an idea!
Hubert has just bought an old Méhari.
A méharie is a type of camel.
A Méhari is a small car.
You'll see, it's a great little car.
It fits everywhere.
Here's a small car that can go anywhere.
The camel is a frugal animal.
He doesn't drink much. He can travel dozens of kilometers without drinking.
The poet Guillaume Apollinaire said, the camel travels without drinking, I drink without traveling.
The camel is sober. Apollinaire was less sober.
The Méhari is economical. It doesn't consume much petrol. The Renault 5 is also economical.
Mireille meets Colette at La Passion du Fruit, a fruit juice bar on the quays.
Ask Colette what she plans to do this summer, and if you have any farm projects.
For this summer, firm projects are definitive, things that cannot be changed; an apple is firm, but
But that is less firm, it can change shape, we can change it, modify it.
Mireille tells the story of the lottery ticket, the travel plan with Robert, and Hubert's intrusion.
Hubert is an intruder, nobody invited him.
Jean-Pierre is also an intruder.
Mireille suggests that Colette come along because she doesn't want to be alone between Hubert and Robert.
You can imagine I'm not exactly dying to be left alone between Hubert and my American boyfriend.
If Colette agrees, it will help Mireille.
Mireille likes it when people do her favors.
Can you give me that sheet of paper?
Marie-Laure is doing him a favor
Can you lend me 50 francs?
Will you give them back to me?
Of course I'll give them back to you.
When she lends him money, she is doing him a favor.
They intend to leave in about two weeks.
One week, eight days. About eight days.
Two weeks, fifteen days. About fifteen days.
We would leave in about two weeks.
And we would come back, let's say, at the end of August.
Or before, if we've had enough.
They've had enough.
He's had enough too.
That could be fun. Anyway, I have no desire to stay in Provins with my parents.
Listen to the conversation between Mireille and Colette, then you will take on the role of Colette.
If you could come with us, that would solve everything and we could really have some fun.
And when would you leave? And for how long?
We would leave in about two weeks and come back, let's say, at the end of August, unless we have had enough before then.
That could be fun.
Listen, yes, in principle I accept you now, you are Colette, if you
If you could come with us, everything would be sorted out and we could really have fun.
When would you leave and for how long?
How long would it be for, when would you be leaving, and what would it be for?
How long would we be leaving in about two weeks and returning at the end of the year?
August or before if we have enough it could be fun listen yes in
In principle, I accept, it could be fun. Listen, yes, in principle, I accept.
That could be fun, listen, yes, in principle I agree. Mireille is happy that Collette
Accept, that's wonderful, you're saving my life, you're saving my life, she's exaggerating, him, yes, he's saving her
They saved his life, yes you saved our nephew, fasten your seatbelts!
can save your life the following Sunday Mireille goes to see her children they are
Children who were at a summer camp last summer.
Mireille was a counselor at this summer camp.
She was taking care of her children.
There was also an instructor, a very friendly instructor, Jean-Michel.
Jean-Michel and Mireille continue to take care of his children.
They bring them together every Sunday.
They are having a meeting.
This is a workers' meeting.
The workers gather to discuss.
I didn't want us to meet, it's not my business, it's yours.
Did you perhaps think we were going to do the work for you?
Is that why you held the meeting?
I'm very glad that we're all together.
Jean-Michel is very tired.
He can't take it anymore.
He's exhausted.
I'm exhausted, I can't take it anymore.
Phew! I can't take it anymore.
I'm exhausted.
She's exhausted.
She can't take it anymore.
He can't take it anymore. He's exhausted.
Ah, I'm exhausted. I'm going to bed.
Jean-Michel needs a change of scenery. I need to take a real vacation. You see, I'm changing my perspective a bit.
Mireille also needs a change of scenery. I also need a change of scenery.
It's stifling in here.
I need a change of scenery.
It feels good to get a change of scenery.
Marie-Laure is going to change her clothes.
I want to wear my pink dress. May I?
Okay, if you're up for it.
Now she's going to change her t-shirt.
Go on, go change your t-shirt.
And she changed her dress.
People like change.
Have you changed your anger water?
Yeah.
Don't you want to change the record?
Why don't you like this one?
And he, he changes gears.
Jean-Michel needs a change of scenery
because he is depressed, tired.
He looked really depressed.
She is depressed.
Autumn and winter are depressing.
Montreal, early November.
It's raining, it's snowing, it's cold.
He looked really depressed.
He's really depressed.
Phew! I don't understand this problem at all.
It's really tough.
It's good ?
Yeah, it's really great.
She's really good, listen, we have a really important appointment, but it's not sad, it's
It's really great when you get divorced because you have two houses and two Christmas anniversaries.
Going on vacation is really great when you're getting divorced. Mireille suggests to Jean-Michel that he come with them.
But now that I think about it, why don't you come with us? That'll take our minds off things.
Are you kidding me?
Jean-Michel isn't very polite. He means, "Are you making fun of me?"
Can you see me, between that degenerate, savage American aristocrat?
What would I be doing in that mess?
A galley is a boat where you have to row hard. Nobody wants to go on a galley.
Mireille defends Robert.
He is a very educated, very cultured boy.
He is very cultured. Heidegger, Freud, Lévi-Strauss, Picasso, Lacan, Leeming, Sartre, Mishima.
Sylvestre, you are a very intelligent man. You are not very cultured, but you are very intelligent, I'm sure.
Mireille finally convinces Jean-Michel. She convinces him.
One.
Non.
Yes, it does.
Come on, let's go.
Good.
Ah.
Now, Mireille explains the situation to Robert.
Well, you know, our projects are taking shape.
That's still vague, but it's taking shape.
It's taking shape.
The glass is taking shape.
The car is taking shape.
First, Hubert lends us his Méhari.
Ah.
And naturally, he will come with us.
I thought to myself that I should be wary of that camel.
Did you understand? Robert is making a pun.
Camel, camel.
He was wary of Hubert's camel, that old camel.
Ah, he's got a sharp mind, that boy.
Robert is not happy
Damn, there will be four of us.
But Mireille reassures him
This will be very interesting.
Especially because Jean-Michel is a bit of a leftist
Is he a Trotskyist or a Guevarist? I'm not entirely sure.
And Hubert is rather right-wing
Then sparks will fly.
Sparks
There are sparks!
"This will be very interesting for you."
"I have no doubt about that."
"Oh, I don't doubt it, I'm sure of it."
"But I would still have preferred solitude with someone else."
"Ah, the solitude of being alone together."
Hubert is not happy either.
Five people is too many.
"Hey, but the Méhari isn't expandable."
This table is extendable, but the mehari is not extendable.
The Méhari doesn't have an upper deck, I'll have you know.
There are buses that have an upper deck.
But the Méhari doesn't have an upper deck, I'll have you know.
It's a quarter past one, I'll have you know.
The Méhari is not expandable.
With four of us, we'll be packed in like sardines.
Malon, Hubert, I know you, despite your innocent, boyish ways.
I wouldn't be surprised if you were upset about being squeezed against Colette.
Hubert has the air of an altar boy.
He looks innocent, prudish, like an altar boy
Here is a choirboy
A child at heart
But he wouldn't mind being pressed up against Colette
What's wrong? Are you feeling unwell? Are you angry?
Yes, I'm angry.
Mireille went to the cinema and she didn't want to take me.
He's angry too.
Hey, cut off my body!
Mom !
Shut up and go to sleep. I'm very angry.
But can't you be careful, can you, you dirty little girl?
She is angry.
But he's not angry.
Okay, we might be a little cramped, but it doesn't matter.
The crazier you are, the more you laugh, as my Aunt Georgette says.
She, who never laughs, by the way.
We'll have a blast.
In five days, we'll have a blast.
They're having a blast.
But they're completely crazy, those women.
Now, let's see what you know.
Listen, watch, think, and speak.
Look at these people.
Are they bored to death or are they having a blast?
They're having a blast.
Yes, they're having a blast.
What is it? A galley or a camel?
A camel car.
An Alpine, do you think it's cheap or does it cost an arm and a leg?
It costs an arm and a leg.
Yes, it costs an arm and a leg.
What is Marie-Laure doing here?
She changes her t-shirt
She changes her t-shirt, very good
Where is he spending the night here, in a nice hotel or in the middle of a field?
In the middle of the field
Very good. In the middle of a field.
What is it? A field or a holiday camp?
A summer camp.
Look at your classmate. Does he look fit or does he look exhausted?
He looks exhausted.
Yes, I can't take it anymore.
And Jean-Michel, does he look happy or depressed?
Depressed.
What's wrong, Mr. Guignol? Are you feeling unwell? You look depressed.
I'm tired. I'm exhausted. I can't take it anymore. I've had enough.
I'm bored. I'm bored to death.
My friend Robert and I are going to do the Tour de France by car.
Come with us, Mr. Guignol.
Will that take your mind off things?
What would I be doing on the roads with two crazy young people?
No, I'm going to take a short nap.
But Mr. Guignol, come on! We'll have a blast!
Come on, join us! The more the merrier!
Yeah, I prefer to sleep! Have a good trip, come on, have a good trip!
Subtitles ST' 501
...
Gould Foundation Incorporated, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of
Culture and Communication, the General Commission for the French Language, the Jesse
B. Cox Charitable Trust, and the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Pour information about this and other Annenberg Media programs, call 1-800-LEARNER and visit
us at www.learner.org.
Subtitles ST' 501