Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Our five friends are gathered at the bike shop to talk about their trip.
So, where are we going?
Where are we going? Everywhere! We're going everywhere!
We're going to see the whole of France, as nature is celebrated there.
2000 years of history and our 40 kings.
Your 40 kings and the sweat of the people, yes.
And what about the giants of '93?
Who are the giants of '93?
The great men of the French Revolution.
You know, Danton, Robespierre, great men, pure men, tough men.
Bloodthirsty monsters.
You absolutely must see our French countryside, which is as well-maintained as gardens.
our magnificent forests, our incomparable sites,
the Chamonix needles, the Cirque de Gavarnie,
the Verdon gorges and the Tarn gorges,
the calanques of Cassis, the Baux de Provence.
Above all, they need to see our cathedrals.
But I've already seen Notre-Dame.
Do you think that once you've seen one, you've seen them all?
We also saw Chartres
Two cathedrals, but that's nothing
There are hundreds of churches to see
Amiens and Sanef, Strasbourg and its spire
Reims, where all our kings were crowned
Bourges and its stained glass windows, Mont Saint-Michel and its wonder
And these tides that advance at the speed of a galloping horse
And Albi Cathedral with its enormous walls of small pink bricks
All the wonderful Romanesque churches
Vézelay, Paray-le-Monial, Saint-Benoît-sur-Loire, Poitiers, Conques, Saint-Nectaire.
Saint-Nectaire.
Where they make the cheese.
All the fortified churches.
Agde, Les Saintes-Maries-de-la-Mer, Luse.
And all modern churches.
Yvetot, the church of Plateau d'Assis, that of Cocteau, Royan, Ronchamps.
And then, you must see our castles.
Champs, Chambord, Chaumont, Chantilly.
Chantilly.
The cream, whipped cream.
Châteaudun, Chenonceau, Chinon, Valençais.
Where they make goat cheese.
Annay, Amboise, Angers, Azel Rideau, Blois, Fontaine Bleu.
Ah, blue fountain.
Cream cheese.
Loche, langer, pierre fond, saumur.
Saumur, where there is wine.
and one of the best cavalry schools in the world.
All of this seems very interesting, exciting, admirable to me.
But it seems to me that's a lot.
We won't be able to go everywhere.
You know, France isn't very big.
Just one thousandth of the shepherds' land.
And shepherds, above the sea.
Obviously, if it's not above the sea, it's not land.
France is slightly smaller than Texas.
But what variety, what richness! There's everything in France, yeah, but I was in the middle of...
We're going to be pretty cramped with 5 of us in your room, but Harry, we're going to have rusty joints
I wonder if it wouldn't be better to do that by bike, just to get some exercise. Oh yes.
Cycling in France wouldn't be bad; Cécile and her husband have already visited the Loire Valley castles.
cycling along the Loire when they were engaged and they found it wonderful, you have to
To say that the Loire Valley is a breeze, especially going downhill...
Climbing the Col du Tourmalet or the Col de l'Isran at 2770m is another matter entirely.
The thing is, we have mountains in France, the Alps, the Pyrenees, the
Jura, the Ardennes, the Vosges mountains, the Massif Central, and you're forgetting one
in Brittany.
Ah yes, the American massif.
Armorican.
Armoricain, what is that?
It means Breton.
Armoric is Brittany.
Didn't they teach you that in geography class?
Oh, but it's not very high.
So it doesn't count.
Yes, there's no shortage of mountains.
And I absolutely insist
to go to the mountains.
I'm starting to get fed up
from the plain of Île-de-France.
Where is Île-de-France?
This is it. Paris, the provinces, it's in the Île-de-France region.
But it's not an island.
But it doesn't matter, that's what it's called.
I'm fed up with the plains too. I'm sick of it. I want to go to the mountains.
Well, that's settled, no problem. We'll go to the Massif Central. My parents have a property in the Cantat.
Where is the cheese made?
Of course, the Massif Central is just a mountainous area for cows. Is that what you call a mountain?
You should at least go to the Pyrenees.
The Pyrenees?
But there are no more Pyrenees, my dear friend.
There are no more Pyrenees?
Non.
Ah, another stupid thing from your Louis XIV.
Marie-Laure doesn't seem to understand.
But yes, you studied that in history, didn't you?
You know well the Peace of the Pyrenees, in 1659.
Louis XIV had signed a treaty with Spain.
And he said, there you go, now we're friends, buddies, buddies.
There is no longer a problem. Nothing separates France from Spain anymore.
It's as if the Pyrenees no longer exist.
There are no more Pyrenees. Ah, that's a good one.
This is the best of the year. The Pyrenees are no more.
Go ask a Tour de France rider,
when he tackles the Col d'Aubisque and the Col du Tourmalet in the same stage.
Note that, personally, if I had to choose, I think I prefer the Alps.
It's higher. La Meije, 3,983 meters.
Mont Blanc, 4,807 meters.
4,810, but come on Hubert, where did you get that from? Everyone knows that the
Mont Blanc is only 4800.7 m high, isn't it, Marie Laure? Mont Blanc altitude 4800
7m, you see, I was always taught 4810, I know that bad French who
They lacked a sense of grandeur; they tried to bring them down to 4807, but that
I will never accept cock-a-doodle-doo, let's talk less, let's talk more, where are we going? I propose we do the
Tour of France in a counter-clockwise direction, first stage Lille
Roubaix, Tourcoing, North, oh no, more plains, fields, mines, factories, what is it?
Worth seeing, but the people, miss, the real France, the France that works, yes, but for
As far as gastronomy goes, the north isn't great.
If we started with Normandy, at least there, the food is good.
Camembert cheese, crème fraîche, Izigny butter, Norman sole, Rouen duck, tripe à la mode de Caen.
Go through Normandy!
While the young people were discussing their trip, the man in black appeared behind the window.
He's washing the windows. Weird, weird.
No one notices except Marie-Laure, who watches him, a little intrigued.
Departure Monday morning at dawn. First stop Rouen.
no Tourcoing king Tourcoing king Tourcoing Rouen Tourcoing
The five friends are gathered to talk about their trip.
They are gathered. What is your name?
Mireille and Jean-Michel bring their kids together every Sunday.
They are having a meeting.
Here's a meeting.
That's a workers' meeting.
A meeting of cooks.
Where are we going? Where are we going?
Note that Hubert speaks better than Jean-Michel.
Where are we going? That's more correct, more elegant.
Where are we going?
I know a pretty good little restaurant.
They will see France as nature made it.
The sea, the mountains, the plains, the rivers.
Nature shaped France, but so did history.
First, prehistory.
And then, the story that began more than 2000 years ago, with the Gauls and the Romans.
After the Gallo-Roman period, there were 40 kings.
According to Hubert, it was these kings who made France.
But Jean-Michel disagrees.
According to him, it was not the kings, but the work of the people that made France.
Your 43 and the sweat of the people, yes.
The sweat of the people means the work of the people.
When you work hard, you get hot, you sweat, you perspire.
According to Jean-Michel, it was the work of the people that made France.
And the giants of '93, the great men of the revolution in 1793, like Danton, Robespierre.
That's a normal man. That's a giant. And that's a dwarf.
Jean-Michel says they were figurative giants because he admires them. They are illustrious men.
Big ones, pure ones, tough ones.
Hubert disagrees.
Bloodthirsty monsters.
Hubert wants to show Robert the whole of France.
You absolutely must see our French countryside, which is as well-maintained as gardens.
The campaign.
The mountain.
The sea.
Our magnificent forests
Our incomparable sites
The Chamonix Needles
In the Alps, very sharp peaks like needles
The Cirque de Gavarnie
In the Pyrenees
The Verdon Gorge and the Tarn Gorge
The Verdon gorges, the Tarn gorges, now those are gorges!
Mireille, an art history specialist, mainly wants Robert to see the cathedrals.
The great Gothic cathedrals
Like the one in Amiens, which is famous for its very high nave
There you have it, a nave
Strasbourg Cathedral, famous for its spire
There, an arrow
An arrow
Reims Cathedral, famous for its angels
and because kings were crowned there.
Bourges Cathedral, famous for its stained glass windows.
Mont-Saint-Michel, which is famous for its Gothic church known as the Marvel
and also because there are very strong tides.
At the seaside, there are tides.
The sea is rising, it's high tide.
And then the sea goes out, it's low tide.
Here comes low tide. Low tide. At Mont-Saint-Michel, the tides are very strong. The sea rises very quickly, as fast as a galloping horse. There are all the Gothic churches from the 12th or 13th century.
And all the older Romanesque churches, Vézelay, Paray-le-Mognal, Conques, Saint-Nectaire.
Ah, Saint-Nectaire, that interests Colette, because there is a famous cheese there.
You also have to see all the fortified churches, like fortresses.
Modern churches too, like the one in Yvetot in Normandy, the one in Poitiers, the one on the plateau of Assis in the Alps, the one in Royan on the Atlantic, the one in Ronchamps built by Le Corbusier.
And then, you have to see all the castles, the old castles that date back to the Middle Ages.
Angers, Loches, Chinon, Saumur, in the Loire region.
Saumur, where there is wine
Yes, Colette, there is also a very good wine in Saumur
And then, you have to see all the Renaissance castles
Amboise, where Leonardo da Vinci lived and died
Chambord
Chaumont
Chenonceau
Azé-le-Rideau
Angers, in the Loire region
And we mustn't forget Valençay
Where they make goat cheese
And Fontainebleau
Fontainebleau, the cream cheese
Et Chantilly
Chantilly, the Chantilly cream
Obviously, all of that adds up to a lot.
Fortunately, France is not very big.
Just one thousandth of the land has emerged.
To emerge?
No, Marie-Laure.
One thousand of the lands emerge.
To emerge, above the sea.
Emerge ?
Immerse.
Robert would prefer to make the journey by bicycle.
For what ?
Just to get some exercise.
He wants to exercise.
They exercise. They exercise too.
If you don't exercise, your joints will get stiff.
There it is, a joint. A rusty joint.
Cécile and her husband cycled around the Loire Valley castles when they were engaged.
But it must be said that the Loire Valley is easy going, especially going downhill.
However, to climb the Tourmalet or Iseran passes,
Two thousand seven hundred and seventy meters
That's another story.
That's another story, it's more difficult
Five times four
Twenty
Five times five
Twenty-five
Five times six
Thirty, that's all right.
Okay, and seven times four
Twenty-eight
Seven times five
Thirty-five
Okay, and nine times eight
Oh, that's a different story, it's not the same.
Cycling across France can be tough
because of the mountains.
That's because we have mountains of them in France.
That's because there are mountains of them.
Marie-Laure, please be kind and give me my glasses.
Where are they?
In one of the pockets of my jacket, right there.
Which one?
I don't know, look it up.
That's because there are pockets of them.
There are many mountains in France
Yes, there's no shortage of mountains.
The Alps
The Pyrenees
The Jura
The Vosges
The Massif Central
The Ardennes
The Armorican Massif
Armoricain, what is that?
It means Breton
Armoric is Brittany
I'm starting to get fed up with the plains of Île-de-France.
Colette is fed up with the plains of Île-de-France.
Where is Île-de-France?
This is it. Paris, the provinces, it's in the Île-de-France region.
Listen to the conversation between Mireille and Marie-Laure, then you will play the role of Mireille.
Where is Île-de-France?
Well, here. Paris, the provinces, it's in the Île-de-France region.
But it's not an island.
But it doesn't matter, that's what it's called.
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille.
Where is Île-de-France?
Well, here, Paris, Provins, it's in the Ile de France.
But it's not an island.
But it doesn't matter, that's what it's called.
Jean-Michel is also fed up with the plains.
I'm fed up with the plains too.
I'm fed up.
He's had enough, he's fed up, he's had it up to here.
There's a bowl, a full bowl, a bowl filled to the brim, he's had enough.
Marie-Laure is fed up too.
I'm fed up, I'm sick and tired of homework and lessons.
Hey, I think I'll go for a drive to Luxembourg.
He wants to go mountaineering.
Hubert suggests Cantal, in the Massif Central.
Colette agrees, because there is a cheese specialty in Cantal.
But Jean-Michel disagrees.
Cantal is not real mountain country, it's cow country.
Now that's a real mountain. That's a cow pasture.
Jean-Michel suggests the Pyrenees.
"The Pyrenees? But there are no more Pyrenees, my dear friend."
Louis XIV abolished the Pyrenees.
Marie-Laure doesn't seem to understand. Yet it's quite simple.
The Pyrenees separate France from Spain.
There were wars, but in 1659, Louis XIV made a treaty with Spain.
The Peace of the Pyrenees
And he said
Now, nothing separates France and Spain
The Pyrenees no longer exist.
Non
Jean-Michel is not convinced
Ah, another stupid thing from your Louis XIV
It's a ridiculous joke
That's a good one!
This is the best one of the year
So Marie-Laure, you're not working?
That's a good one!
I slept with
A French assignment, a math assignment, a history lesson, a geography lesson, and I'm not working.
I swear, it's the best one of the year.
It wasn't me, it was him. That's the best one yet.
Ah, this is the best one of the year. There are no more Pyrenees.
Go ask the Tour de France riders when they tackle the Col d'Aubisque and the Col du Tourmalet in the same stage.
The Tour de France riders are tackling two mountain passes on the same day.
They are tackling two mountain passes in the same day.
And Marie-Laure has to do a whole lot of homework and lessons.
I had to do a French assignment, a math assignment,
A history lesson, a geography lesson, and I'm not working.
I swear.
Here's a mountain pass.
The Aubisque pass.
Jean-Michel prefers the Alps because they are higher
La Mège, 3,983 meters
Mont Blanc, 4,807 meters
Not everyone agrees on the altitude of Mont Blanc
4,807 meters, says Marie-Laure
4,807 meters
4 810
4,810 meters, says Hubert, who has a sense of grandeur
But come on, Hubert, where did you get that from?
Where did you get that from? That's not right.
Nine times eight.
Ninety-three.
Ninety-three? Where did you get that from?
Everyone knows that nine times eight equals seventy-two.
And that Mont Blanc only has...
Four thousand eight hundred and seven meters.
I was always taught four thousand eight hundred and ten.
I know that there were bad Frenchmen who lacked a sense of grandeur
tried to lower it to 4807.
But that, I will never accept.
Cock-a-doodle-doo!
What is the highest mountain in Europe?
I think it's Mont Blanc.
And do you know the altitude of Mont Blanc?
I learned that it was 4810 meters.
But I think there's a little less of it now, it's not as high.
Ah good ?
Yes.
Has it gone down?
A little.
Hubert suggests touring France in a counter-clockwise direction.
Clockwise, counter-clockwise.
You can clearly see the movement of the clouds; you see how they rotate in the direction of the movement of the chosen ones of the world in the northern hemisphere.
First stop, Roubaix-Tourcoing Island
But Colette disagrees, the north, no
More plains, fields, mines
Factories
She prefers Normandy
At least the food is good here
Camembert cheese, fresh cream
Izigny butter, Norman sole, Rouen duck, tripe à la mode de Caen.
Everyone agrees.
Let's go with the nun Andini.
If I were you, I would play the 10 of clubs.
I'll go with the 10 of clubs.
Let's go with the nun Andini.
They'll be heading out to the water Monday morning; the fishermen will be leaving very early, at dawn.
They leave at dawn, often there are shops that open at dawn, dawn, dawn, look
Listening and speaking, that's the sea or the mountains, the sea, the sea, yes, Louis XIV, he was a king or a
shepherd a king Notre Dame de Paris is a Romanesque or Gothic cathedral
Is that a Gothic or modern church?
Modern.
What are all these people doing?
They are exercising.
And him? Does he want to continue or is he fed up?
He's had enough. He's had enough. He's fed up.
What's wrong, Mr. Guignol? Is everything alright?
I've had enough. I'm fed up. I'm sick of it.
Well, come with us.
We're going to eat tripe à la mode de Caen.
These are the best tripe
Are you going to Lyon?
No, not in Normandy, in Caen.
You know very well that the best tripe is tripe à la mode de Caen.
Oh, that's a good one!
Where did you get that from?
The best tripe is tripe Lyonnaise style.
No, no, no, not in the camp style
In the Lyonnaise style, in the Lyonnaise style
In camp style
In the Lyonnaise style, in the Lyonnaise style, in the Lyonnaise style
Subtitles ST' 501
MFP subtitles.
www.learner.org