Subtitles ST' 501
You have to look and fly away.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you will be able to say a few words in French yourself.
Our travelers continue to discuss their itinerary.
It is possible to circumnavigate France by boat
by water, shores and canals.
Hubert and Jean-Michel disagree
with the real France.
And the man in black comes to the door
with a strange story
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
I bring the castles of France.
The others aren't here?
There you go.
I'm going to open it for them.
Hello.
Hello, hello.
Go ahead.
Hello everyone.
Hello children.
But you're carrying a lot of stuff, what are you bringing?
Emilio's taste, the car journal guide, the Michelin guide with the three-star map,
Madeleines from Commercy, berlingots from Carpentras, nougat from Montélimar
and some Cambrai nonsense for Marie-Laure.
Well, I think you're spoiling her a little too much.
I hope she'll let us taste a little of it.
I don't know. We'll have to see.
If you take me with you, fine. Otherwise, I'll keep everything.
But then, Marie-Laure, you know very well that we can't take you.
You will go to Saint-Jean-de-Luz with mom and dad.
No, no, I don't want to go to Saint-Jean-de-Luz with mom and dad.
I'll go with you. I don't care.
If you don't want to take me, I'll go alone.
And I won't say where I'm going. And you'll be in a real bind.
But then, Marie-Laure, stop talking nonsense and offer everyone a candy.
Not you! What do you want, my beloved cowboy?
Nonsense from Cambrai?
Carpentras berlingots?
Montélimar nougat?
Or madeleines from Commercy?
That's stupid.
And me?
Oh, just a minute!
Is this the green guide to Normandy and Brittany that I was supposed to bring?
THANKS.
Yes, yes, yes, there is a small grocery store.
So, we all agree, we're going to Rouen first, to Tourcoing.
Okay, I've thought it through, we're not going to Rouen, nor to Tourcoing, but to Where-is-it-there?
Where is it? Where is it at? Where is it?
At sea, 20 kilometers off the coast of Brittany.
Okay, I have an idea, we put the table aside and put the map on the floor, that will be better.
Yes, yeah.
Yeah, that's an idea, let's do France by boat, France by boat, it's me, you want to lead in
boat, but no, my dear friend, nobody wants to deceive you, I wouldn't presume to
Making fun of you? No, no, it's completely serious, I'm not joking. We can very well do the
France by boat, think of the 5000 km of coastline, that's a lot of beaches, we'll all be able to swim
The days and the minute 1 it depends where I don't swim in the English Channel or in the sea
No way from the north, it's too cold, sir, you chilly person, but dear sir, in the USSR there are
People swimming in January amidst ice floes and polar bears, it's true, I don't...
I'm not sure. They probably have thermal suits. I can see that perfectly well.
How could we travel along the coast from Belgium to the Basque Country? But how?
Getting from there to the Mediterranean, that's harder for me to see. Even if Louis XIV abolished it
The Pyrenees. But he didn't actually remove them. No problem. We're going back up
the Garonne and then we take the Canal du Midi, yet another great achievement of Louis XIV
in parentheses, and we arrive at the Mediterranean.
Oh dear, some people are starting to annoy me with their Louis XIV.
That said, I acknowledge that you can go almost anywhere by boat.
with all these rivers, all these streams, all these canals.
Yes, of course. From the English Channel, we could go up the Seine,
then the Marne, from the Marne, passing into the Saône via the canal,
From the Saône, we pass into the Rhône,
and we descend gently all the way to the Mediterranean.
And we're going to eat bouillabaisse in Marseille.
This is the real bouillabaisse from Marseille.
Do you want the recipe?
But I'm thinking about it.
My family has a small sailboat in Villequier.
Perhaps we could borrow it?
Hey, wait a minute, I don't want to go drown in the prime of my life.
Why would you drown? Do you know how to swim?
Yes, but sailing in Villequier is dangerous.
For what ?
Well, you know, Victor Hugo?
Yes.
Well, he had a daughter.
And that girl, she got married.
Yeah.
And one day, she went with her husband to Villequier, on the Seine, to a family property.
And there was a boat, a sailboat.
And she went boating on the Seine with her husband.
And the boat capsized and she drowned.
So what?
And so, Victor Hugo wrote a poem.
And you, you don't want to go drown yourself at Villequier because dad wouldn't write a poem.
There you go, you've got it all figured out.
Well, I don't want to drown myself in the prime of my life either, and besides, I'm not going to
not spending the summer sightseeing on some rich kid's yacht, I'd have bad faith and
Besides, you can't discover the real France on a yacht anyway, can you?
We need to go and see the working France, we need to go and see the steelworkers and...
Lorraine, the underground miners, you have to go see how Michelin tires, Airbus, and cars are made.
Renault and the pebbles, that's France, the real France, it's the workers.
Workers aren't the ones who make Renaults, oh no! And who do you think the robots are?
And then you make me laugh with your petty arguments about France perhaps being at the forefront
Progress with the hook stitch; the hook stitch is a magnificent technical achievement.
Commercial, sure, but there are even more remarkable things, take the machined one for example.
The tidal power plant on the Rance River, for example, 1. It's not everywhere that electrical energy is generated with
The force of the tides, you make me laugh with your tidal power plant, the tidal power plant of the Rance, yes, that's it
Not bad, oh, but the Russians also have a tidal power plant that they copied from ours.
It's something to see, it's all been seen before, besides, it's not just the Russians, the whole world copies us
Because all the great discoveries originated in France.
Pasteurization, radioactivity, the tin can, the stethoscope, champagne, aviation, the telegraph, cinema, Carnot's principle, foie gras, love, freedom.
It's impossible to be that chauvinistic.
Here, something that's really great,
These are solar energy installations in the Pyrénées-Orientales.
Do you know it?
That's something.
I remember seeing it when I was little,
a solar furnace that liquefied metals in the blink of an eye.
Do you realize how much metal melts in the sun?
That stunned me.
You're bothering us with your steel industry.
Nobody cares.
Ah well, solar steelmaking,
I assure you there's something there, it's impressive.
Hey Marie-Laure, the doorbell rang, go see?
Yes
Marie-Laure will open the front door
It's the man in black
She comes back into the living room; no one paid much attention to what had happened.
What was it?
The sister's brother
Who ?
You know, the brother of the nun who came the other day
And what did he want?
He used to bring me back my gumballs
Had you lost them?
Non.
What were those gumballs he brought you?
They weren't mine, they were other gumballs.
But I don't understand any of it.
It's actually quite simple.
He told me, I'll bring you your gumballs.
But I saw that they weren't mine.
So I told him, no, they're not mine.
I gave it back to him, so he left.
But it's not very clear.
This whole business with the gumballs is quite mysterious.
Well, you, we can say you're not very talented, huh.
Everyone gets up to leave.
But it's 5 o'clock. I have to leave.
I'll accompany you.
Yes, I have to leave too.
Bye.
My phone.
Hi, Jean.
Robert is leaving too.
I'm going down too.
Where are you going?
In the garden.
Okay, fine, but you'll be back at 6 o'clock.
Do you hear? 6 o'clock sharp.
Mom and Dad aren't here tonight, so we'll eat early.
And if you're good, we'll go to the cinema.
Owl!
But six o'clock sharp, not a minute more.
Yes!
Colette arrives with a whole bunch of things in her arms.
She is loaded.
But you're carrying a lot of luggage, what are you bringing?
Mireille is also in charge here.
This lady is also in charge.
This one is also quite full.
This car is also loaded. Colette is bringing restaurant guides. The goémiot, the auto journal guide, the red Michelin guide which indicates hotels and restaurants with one, two and three stars.
And Jean-Michel brings the Michelin Green Guide, a tourist guide
Colette also brings a whole bunch of good things to eat
Small cakes, madeleines from Commercy in the East
Carpentras berlingots in Provence
Sweets and Cambrai sweets in the North
Montélimar nougat
in the Rhône Valley.
What is Montélimar's specialty?
Nougat.
And what is Cambrai's specialty?
The foolishness of Cambrai.
All of this is for Marie-Laure.
Colette spoils her.
Are you spoiling her a little too much?
Uncle Guillaume spoils her too.
Guillaume, you're spoiling her.
She is very close to her uncle
I can say that he spoils her a lot
All these good things are for Marie-Laure
But Colette hopes that Marie-Laure won't keep everything to herself.
I hope she'll let us taste a little of it
Snack, remember?
He tastes the wine
Among the courtly people, everyone tastes the wine in reverent silence.
He tastes the jam
Cécile tastes the raw salmon
He tastes the sauce
Here, have a taste!
Marie-Laure sets her conditions
If you take me with you, fine, otherwise I'll keep everything
She wants the others to take her with them
He takes the little boy away
She takes the little girl
But Mireille doesn't want to take Marie-Laure with her.
But come on Marie-Laure, you know very well that we can't take you
I don't care, if you don't want to take me, I'll go by myself.
I don't care, I don't care.
If you haven't finished your homework, you won't come to the cinema with us?
I don't care, I'll watch TV
Look at Jean-Claude, he doesn't care.
And look at the psychiatrist here
My mother wanted a daughter
He doesn't care
I don't care, if you don't want to take me, I'll go by myself.
And I won't say where I'm going, and you'll be in a real bind.
Marie-Laure talks about leaving all alone
This is ridiculous, she's talking nonsense.
But Marie-Laure, stop talking nonsense!
When I grow up, I want to be president of the republic.
But stop talking nonsense.
Well, it's not nonsense, it's good to be president of the republic
She's not serious, she talks nonsense.
It's a lady who would like to see a gentleman named Tasson
Tasson ?
I think she's in the wrong house
Not at all, Adette, don't talk nonsense.
No, you're talking nonsense, come on
No, it's not nonsense.
So let's go see, stop your nonsense and give everyone some candy
There you go, she's offering candy
What does my beloved convoy want?
You can offer sweets, you can offer flowers, perfume, cologne.
Have you changed your cologne?
Yeah, yeah.
Did you buy it? Then it was given to you as a gift.
Exactly, it was given to me as a gift.
A lady.
Mireille suggests going to Ouessant.
Ouessant, Ouessant.
at sea, 20 km from the coast of Brittany, Hubert offers to explore France by boat; it's a
The idea is to tour France by boat. Robert thinks it's a joke. France by boat, that's me.
that you want to fool him, he thinks Hubert wants to fool him, to make fun of him, there is
It's your mom who's looking for you.
What? She's not at the office?
Is she at home?
Yes, indeed.
Oh really? And what's going on?
Okay, I'll go see.
That's not true. It's a joke.
It's easy to fool her.
She's a bit naive, isn't she?
Marie-Laure likes to lead people on.
No, Hubert isn't making fun of Robert. He's serious.
No, no, it's completely serious.
No, I'm not joking.
He's serious. He's not joking.
Look, I got a 10 on my French homework.
You're kidding.
I'm not kidding, look.
She's not joking, that's true.
No, I'm not joking.
You can easily travel around France by boat.
Because there are many hills.
Imagine, 5000 kilometers of coastline.
That's a lot of beaches, we'll be able to swim every day.
Jean-Michel disagrees
No way.
Mom, can I go watch TV?
No way, do your homework.
Jean-Michel doesn't want to swim in the North Sea, nor in the English Channel.
It's too cold.
The gentleman is sensitive to the cold.
But my dear sir, in the USSR there are people who swim in January amidst icebergs and polar bears.
Jean-Michel is sensitive to the cold.
This Russian is not sensitive to the cold.
Marie-Laure thinks the Russians should have thermal suits.
Robert doesn't understand how one could travel around France by boat.
I can easily see how we could travel along the coast from Belgium to the Basque Country.
But to get from there to the Mediterranean, I see less clearly that, even if Louis XIV abolished the Pyrenees.
No problem, we go up the Garonne, then we take the Canal du Midi, yet another great achievement of Louis XIV by the way, and we arrive at the Mediterranean.
The Canal du Midi was built in the 17th century. It was a project of Louis XIV.
Another great achievement of Louis XIV, by the way.
In parentheses.
I acknowledge that you can go almost anywhere by boat, with all these rivers.
All these rivers.
All these channels.
There are four major rivers.
The Seine, which flows into the English Channel.
The Loire, which flows into the Atlantic, the Garonne, which also flows into the Atlantic, and the Rhône, which flows into the Mediterranean.
And then there are a whole bunch of rivers that flow into these rivers.
And there are still a whole bunch of canals
From the English Channel, one could go up the Seine.
Then the Marne
From the Marne, cross into the Saône via the canal
From the Saône, we pass into the Rhône
And we descend gently all the way to the Mediterranean
And we're going to eat bouillabaisse in Marseille.
There you have it, the real bouillabaisse from Marseille
Do you want the recipe?
But I'm thinking about it
My family has a small sailboat in Villequier.
Perhaps we could borrow it?
Wait a minute, I don't want to drown in the prime of my life.
Mireille is afraid of drowning
They too are afraid of drowning
Mireille is in the prime of her life
But her grandmother is no longer in the prime of her life.
Mireille explains to Marie-Laure why she doesn't want to go sailing in Villiquier.
You know, Victor Hugo?
Yes.
Well, he had a daughter.
And that girl, she got married.
Yeah.
And one day, she went with her husband to Villiquier, on the Seine, to a family property.
And there was a boat, a sailboat.
and she went boating on the Seine with her husband
and the boat capsized and she drowned.
She didn't drown.
But Victor Hugo's daughter drowned.
And then Victor Hugo wrote a poem.
Jean-Michel doesn't want to go sightseeing on some rich kid's yacht.
Jean-Michel would feel guilty.
He too has a guilty conscience.
But Marie-Laure doesn't feel guilty.
Have you done your homework?
Non
And do you watch TV?
Yes
And you don't feel guilty?
Non
Jean-Michel wants to go see the real France
Working France
Steel mills, airplane and helicopter manufacturing
Michelin tires, Renault cars,
Finally, the France of the workers.
But, according to Hubert, it's not the workers
who manufacture Renault cars.
Oh no, and who do you think it is?
Robots!
These robots perform most of the assembly work.
Hubert, for his part, is very proud of the tidal power of the Rance.
near Mont-Saint-Michel,
a factory that harnesses the power of the tides
to produce electricity.
The Russians also have a tidal power plant
That they copied from ours
According to Hubert, they copied it from the French tidal power plant
But Jean-Michel disagrees; he is not convinced.
That's your voice
You're copying me because I draw better than you.
It's all obvious.
Hubert finds Jean-Michel ridiculous
And then you make me laugh with your hurricane marks.
And Jean-Michel finds Hubert ridiculous
You make me laugh with your tidal motor.
Jean-Michel thinks Hubert is a chauvinist.
It's impossible to be that chauvinistic.
That's not possible.
You take this candy and I'll take the others.
It's impossible to be that selfish.
Here, you can keep it.
Hubert is chauvinistic because he only appreciates French achievements.
Dear sir, please be aware that good wine can only be found in France.
He claims that all great inventions originated in France.
Pasteurization, radioactivity, canned food, stethoscope, champagne, aviation, foie gras, love, freedom.
What impresses Jean-Michel are the solar energy installations in the Pyrénées-Orientales.
I remember seeing a solar furnace when I was little that liquefied metals in the blink of an eye.
If you heat a metal or glass, it liquefies.
Butter melts easily
Ice melts easily
Chocolate melts easily
But metals do not melt easily.
Do you realize how much metal melts in the sun?
That stunned me.
Stunned.
Look, he's stunned.
He too is stunned.
She is stunned.
What amazes Jean-Michel is solar-powered steelmaking.
The steel industry, the metals industry.
During this conversation, Marie-Laure receives a strange visit.
The brother of the good nun with the moustache.
What did he come here to do?
It's not very clear.
A story about a gumball.
Listen to Marie-Laure's explanation.
And then you will play the role of Mireille.
He used to bring me my gumballs.
Had you lost them?
Non.
What were those gumballs he brought you?
They weren't mine, they were other gumballs.
But I don't understand any of it.
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille.
What were those gumballs he brought you?
They weren't mine, they were other gumballs.
But I don't understand any of it.
And you, did you understand?
No, I didn't understand anything.
Well, you, we can say you're not very talented.
Me? Not talented?
That's the best one of the year.
Okay, let's see what you've understood.
Look, listen, think, and speak.
We gave you Cambray sweets, Carpentras berlingots, Montélimar nougat.
What needs to be done? We need to...
They need to be eaten.
Oh, that's so selfish. No, no, you have to...
To offer.
Who manufactures Renault cars?
Robots.
Your older sister and her friends don't want to take you on holiday with them.
What are you saying? What are you saying?
I don't care. If you don't want to take me, I'll go by myself.
Sir, look astonished.
Alright.
Have you seen what time it is?
Oh dear, it's late. I'm leaving.
I have to leave too.
Let's go.
What, let's leave?
They say, I have to leave.
What is this all about?
They say I'm leaving. I don't understand.
It's actually quite simple.
They say I'm leaving, but I have to leave.
I don't understand.
Well, you're not very good at it.
It's impossible to be that stupid.
Subtitles ST' 501
French subtitles?
Annenberg Media
Subtitling by Radio-Canada