Subtitles ST' 501
Watch and get involved.
Pretty soon you will figure out what's going on
and be able to say a few things
in French yourself.
Marie-Laure has gone out and not returned.
Mireille panics.
She and Robert search in vain,
but Marie-Laure finally comes back.
She tells a wild tale about following
a fugitive man in black,
then losing him in the catacombs of Paris.
Mireille doesn't believe a word.
Among the Bélots
It is after 6 a.m.
And Marie-Laure didn't come back.
Mireille attend
And she's worried
But what is she doing?
But that's impossible, what could she possibly be doing?
My God, something must have happened to him.
Around 7 p.m., she decided to call Robert.
Hello, Mr. Taylor, please.
Hello Robert, is that you? Is Marie-Laure with you?
Marie-Laure? No, why?
I don't know what to do, she's disappeared.
But what could have happened to him?
She was supposed to be here at 6am, it's 7:15am, and she still hasn't arrived.
My God, I was thinking maybe she left with you
No, I think she went to Luxembourg
But then she should be here, I don't know what to do
Listen, do you want me to come?
Yes
I'll be there right away
Okay, I'll wait for you, hurry up, goodbye
Fifteen minutes later, Robert arrived.
It's 7:40 am, she should have been here an hour and a half ago, I don't understand.
Did you look in his room?
But his boat isn't there.
It seems to me that she left with him earlier.
Let's go see what's happening in Luxembourg.
In Luxembourg, Robert and Mireille are searching, but there is no one left.
Right! Right! Right! Right!
Look at her boat! Marina!
Look at his boat! Oh my God, the basin, it's awful!
Robert and Mireille run towards the pool.
They spot blond hair in the water, but it belongs to a doll. It's a doll.
It's not hers, my God! Could she have passed by? What could have happened to her?
I should never have let her go. Apparently there's a strange guy who...
He was walking around the neighborhood, the concierge saw him, you think so? No, what are you going to imagine?
Listen, we're going to come back to your place and call the police.
Eight o'clock, she's been gone for three hours.
Something must have happened to him.
Marie-Laure!
But at the Belots' house, Marie-Laure is sitting on her bed.
Quietly playing with his boat.
Marie-Laure, what are you doing?
I'm fixing my boat, the ropes are all tangled up.
But where were you?
I just got back.
Oh, but it's not true, my God, it's not true!
Come on, come on, calm down.
You see, everything's fine.
All's well that ends well, right?
Nothing at all happened to him.
Do you want to eat?
I've already eaten, I want to go to bed.
Okay, that's it, go to bed. I'll come say goodnight later.
What could she have possibly done?
The important thing is that she's here.
It'll be OK ?
Yeah.
It was nice of you to come.
I was so scared.
Is it over?
Can I leave you now?
Are you sure you'll be okay?
Yeah.
See you tomorrow.
Try to sleep.
You're not going to be in great shape for your exam.
When is it, in the morning or the afternoon?
In the afternoon.
I should have finished by 6am.
And we have a meeting with the others at 6:30 am.
Where?
In Saint-Germain-des-Prés, in the small square near the church.
You know, right across from the two Magots.
Of the two cakes?
Two fools, idiot.
You idiot.
At the two Magots, the coffee.
Yes.
I think I see where it is.
Okay. See you tomorrow.
Mireille walks Robert to the door.
A little later, in Marie-Laure's room.
Are you in bed? Are you okay?
So tell me now, what happened to you?
It's a secret.
So, I can't tell you.
Anyway, it won't do any good for me to tell you.
Because if I tell you, you won't believe me.
But if
But no
Well, there you have it.
I went to play in Luxembourg
And then I saw the sister's brother
Who was walking around with a strange look on their face
He seemed to be observing the house, so I thought, what does he want? He doesn't have
He didn't seem trustworthy; was he a thief, a spy, or something? At that moment, I think he saw me.
He recognized me, so he got scared and left, so I quickly hid my boat and started
I followed him, but I hid so he wouldn't know I was following him, and he turned around.
all the time to see if I was following him, he was really scared because he suspected
Although I was following him, he left the garden, crossed the street, and went into the subway. I
I followed him of course and he got on the RER, me too, but not in the same carriage.
At Denfert, I saw him getting off, so I got off too.
He went outside and started walking.
He thought I had lost him, but he saw me.
Then he got really scared and he ran off at full speed.
He rushed into the first open door he saw.
In front of the door, there was a man in uniform shouting
Let's hurry for the last visit
I quickly entered
It was completely black, you couldn't see anything.
Then the man in uniform came in.
He closed the door and said
This way, ladies and gentlemen
Which was silly because there was only the man in black and no lady
Yes, I was there.
But he hadn't seen me
I had hidden behind
So, he didn't know I was there.
He started giving tours because he was a kind of guide
You see
Are you going there?
It's not that way, it's right here.
There were all sorts of weird things.
Skulls, bones, real ones.
And the man in black, he was really scared because he knew I was following him.
Then we went back to the stairs.
That's it, ladies and gentlemen, the tour is over.
This way to the exit.
Don't forget the guide, please.
Thank you, sir.
What are you doing here? I was waiting for you to open the door. I'm not going to spend the night here. Okay.
Okay, go on, get going.
The man in black had taken advantage of the situation to disappear.
So I went home.
On foot, because I didn't have enough money to take the subway.
And besides, I wanted to get some fresh air.
There you go, are you happy?
I wonder where you get all these far-fetched stories.
Because you don't believe me.
I knew you wouldn't believe me.
It's always the same, you never want to believe me.
Well, I'm tired. I'm going to sleep.
That's it, sleep. And don't dream too much in my darkness.
And tell me, I think it would be better not to tell Mom and Dad anything. Okay?
Okay. It's a mystery.
Here, pass me one to help me fall asleep.
Hold.
Marie-Laure was supposed to be there at 6 o'clock.
It's 6:30 and she's not home yet.
Mireille is worried.
She wonders where Marie-Laure is.
But what is she doing?
But that's impossible. What could she possibly be doing?
But what could she have possibly done?
What are you doing here?
But what are you doing here?
But what are you doing?
My God, something must have happened to him.
Eight o'clock, she's been gone for three hours.
Something must have happened to him.
But what could have happened to him?
What happened to you?
Nothing at all happened to him.
Yes, something must have happened to him.
Look.
But what happened to you?
I fell into the pool.
Look at that cyclist, something's going to happen to him.
That's it, something has happened to him.
Be careful Robert, an accident can happen so quickly.
There you go, it's happened
Oh no, nothing happened to him.
But a small misfortune befell Mireille
Shit
Look at Uncle William here
He has no idea what's going to happen to him
He too
He has no idea what's going to happen to him.
Mireille is very worried.
She is looking for Marie-Laure and she cannot find her.
She wonders where she has gone.
But my God, where could she have gone?
But what could have happened to him?
Here, it's Marie-Laure who's looking for her Asterix.
She wonders where he has gone.
But she finds it.
Ah, there he is.
He's looking for his cheese.
But where did he go?
And the sauerkraut, where did it go?
Marie-Laure's boat is not in her room.
But his boat isn't there.
So, she went to play in the Luxembourg pond.
It seems to me that she left with him earlier.
Let's go see what's happening in Luxembourg.
The boat is there, but not Marie-Laure.
Look at his boat.
She must have drowned, like Victor Hugo's daughter.
Oh my God, the basin, it's awful.
Indeed, blond hair is floating on the water.
Robert, with heroic calm, plunges his hand into the water and pulls out a doll.
It's a doll.
This is not Marie-Laure. This is not even Marie-Laure's doll.
It doesn't belong to her.
The problem is not solved. Mireille feels guilty. It's her fault.
I should never have let her go.
We're going to come back to your place and call the police.
You should always call the police in serious cases.
But when they arrive at the apartment, Marie-Laure is there, playing quietly in her room, as if nothing had happened.
Marie-Laure, what are you doing?
I'm fixing my boat, the ropes are all tangled up.
But where were you?
I just got back.
She doesn't give much detail. Strange, strange.
But Mireille isn't paying attention. She's too emotional.
But it's not true, my God, it's not true!
Robert tries to calm her down.
Calm down. You see, everything's fine.
All's well that ends well, right?
Mireille offers the solution for all tragic situations.
Do you want to eat?
But with Marie-Laure, it doesn't work.
I've already eaten, I want to go to bed.
She's very strong, that little girl.
Finally, all's well that ends well, as Robert says.
Marie-Laure is here, nothing has happened to her.
Robert arrived, and Mireille was very moved.
Everything is going very well.
It was nice of you to come.
I was so scared.
Emotions are good, they bring us closer together.
Listen to the conversation between Mireille and Robert.
Next, you will play the role of Robert.
It was kind of you to come. I was so scared.
It's over. I can leave you now.
It's going to be okay, are you sure? It's over.
I can leave you now. It'll be alright, you're sure.
It's over
I can leave you
It'll be alright, are you sure?
Well, that's it, then.
Robert left.
See you tomorrow
But he doesn't leave
He hasn't quite finished reassuring Mireille yet.
Try to sleep
He gives good advice
"You need to sleep better, Charlotte."
He is not leaving yet. His concern prevents him from leaving.
"You're not going to be in great shape for your exams."
Mireille has an exam to take tomorrow.
But with all her emotions, she's not going to be in good shape.
In good shape, remember?
Look at Guylaine here. She's not well.
But here, she's in good shape.
Jean-Claude is not in good shape here.
But here, he's in good shape.
No, but you're really in great shape, aren't you?
But he's not in great shape.
Day of a crusher.
Oh, you don't look very well.
Mireille and Robert have a meeting with their friends at the small square opposite the Deux Magots.
Your two cakes?
The two wise men, idiot.
You idiot.
At the two Magots, the coffee.
He's leaving.
Okay, see you tomorrow.
And Mireille returns to Marie-Laure's room.
She's still a little worried.
Are you in bed? Are you okay?
She wants to know what happened.
So tell me now, what happened to you?
But Marie-Laure doesn't want to tell him.
It's a secret.
So, I can't tell you.
She can't say because it's a secret.
And anyway, it's pointless for her to tell him, because if she did, Mireille wouldn't believe her.
Anyway, it won't do any good for me to tell you, because if I tell you, you won't believe me.
Yes, it does.
In fact, she really wants to tell her story.
Well, there you have it.
She went to play in Luxembourg and she saw a strange guy who seemed to be watching the house.
She said to herself
What does he want?
He doesn't look clean.
He's strange, unsettling
We must be wary.
Here, it's Marie-Laure who doesn't seem quite right.
Your earrings?
No, which earring?
The weird guy saw Marie-Laure
He recognized her
And he saw that she had seen him
So he got scared and he left
Marie-Laure decided to follow him in hiding.
But first, she hid her boat
She hides her chocolates
She hides her notebook
He too is hiding
And there, you see Marie-Laure?
No, because it's hidden behind the sofa.
She hid to scare Mireille.
Idiot!
And here, she hides to follow the man in black without him seeing her.
So I quickly hid my boat and started to follow him,
but by hiding so that he wouldn't know I was following him.
And he turned around.
He turned around.
She turns around.
He turns around.
He turns around. Jean-Claude, turn around.
Here, it's the car that flips over.
Here, Robert and Mireille are leaving the Sorbonne.
And here, Robert returns.
The man in black kept turning around.
And he kept turning around to see if I was following him.
Are you following me?
No, Mireille is not following Marie-Laure's story very well.
In any case, she doesn't believe it's true.
He was really scared because he suspected I was following him.
He was scared. He was very scared. He was terrified. Really scared. Do you remember?
She's really good.
It's good ?
Yeah, it's really great.
He was really scared because he suspected I was following him.
The man in black was afraid because he knew Marie-Laure was following him.
He suspected as much.
To suspect. Do you remember?
That, I have no doubt about.
It doesn't work. I suspected as much, I was sure of it.
She suspected it wouldn't work.
Let's return to the story of Mireille's earrings.
Marie-Laure, haven't you seen my earrings?
Your earrings? No.
Why? Did you lose them?
No, I didn't see them.
Take a good look at me. You don't look quite right.
She suspects that it was Marie-Laure who took the earrings.
And she's right.
Me?
There they are.
Yeah, I knew you'd stolen them from me.
You're crazy, completely crazy.
The normal appearance between seizures, I should have suspected as much.
Normal appearance?
So you couldn't have suspected it.
The man in black was very scared because he suspected that Marie-Laure was following him.
He suspected as much.
He entered the metro and then boarded the RER.
In Paris, there is the metro and the RER.
There are many subway lines.
Porte Cliancaux, Porte d'Orléans, Porte de la Chapelle, Méridici.
Levallois-Gallieni bridge, the metro stops often, there are many stations, there is the
So there's the metro, and then there's the RR. The RR goes further than the metro; it's faster than the metro.
And he stops less often. The man in black got off at Denfert-Rochereau. He had seen that
Marie-Laure was following him, so he got very scared and rushed into the first door.
open door that he saw. In front of the door there was a man in uniform shouting, "Hurry us up for the
On my last visit, I quickly went in; it was completely dark, like the catacombs in the basement of
In Paris, there are the metro tunnels, the sewers, there are hundreds of kilometers of galleries...
The taste of sewage, for the whole system, you remember there are sewers and there's the subway
And there are also the catacombs. Kilometers and kilometers of galleries that were dug to extract the stone needed for the construction of houses.
In the 18th century, the old cemeteries that were in the center of Paris were removed and the bones were placed in the galleries of the catacombs.
In the catacombs, there are the bones of 5 or 6 million people.
Come on, let's hurry up for the last visit.
There is a guide.
This way, ladies and gentlemen.
Don't forget the guide, please.
Generally, guides expect to be tipped at the end of the tour.
Marie-Laure was unfamiliar with the catacombs.
She saw skulls and bones.
She didn't know what it was.
There were all sorts of weird things.
She calls them things, because she doesn't really know what they are.
When you don't know what to call something, you say something.
What is this thing?
What if we bought something?
Marie-Laure almost let herself be locked in the catacombs.
But she doesn't let herself be pushed around, that little girl.
She knows how to manage.
What are you doing here?
I was waiting for you to open the door. I'm not going to spend the night here.
But when she came out, the man in black had disappeared.
She didn't take the subway because she didn't have enough money.
But also because after the catacombs, she wanted to get some fresh air.
Mireille is getting some fresh air and sunshine.
Aunt Georgette and Fido are getting some fresh air.
Marie-Laure is going to get some fresh air.
It's suffocating in here. I need a change of scenery.
Mireille does not believe Marie-Laure's story.
I wonder where you get all these far-fetched stories.
She thinks it's a tall tale.
An extravagant, not serious story
A story that cannot be listened to seriously
So we fall asleep, we fall asleep standing up
Mireille doesn't believe Marie-Laure's story.
But she doesn't know what happened
She's a little worried, she feels responsible
She doesn't want her parents to know that Marie-Laure mysteriously disappeared for several hours.
And tell me, I think it would be better not to tell Mom and Dad anything. Okay?
Okay, well, let's see what you have to say.
Look at Jean-Claude here. Does he look tired or does he look fit?
He looks fit.
He looks well. Your little sister isn't here.
She should be here. What are you saying?
God, where could she have gone?
What is this? Did Marie-Laure drown?
Non.
It's a doll.
Mireille is calling you; her little sister has disappeared.
She is very worried, what do you say?
Listen, do you want me to come?
You were very worried
Robert came to reassure you, what do you say?
It was nice of you to come.
Your little sister tells you strange stories.
You don't believe her, what are you saying?
I wonder where you get all these far-fetched stories.
Oh dear, are these tall tales ever going to end?
I'm fed up with these ridiculous stories.
I'm going to bed now.
Subtitles ST' 501
the Florent J. Gould Foundation Incorporated, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs,
the Ministry of Culture and Communication, the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust, et le National Endowment for the Humanities.
For more information on this and other Annenberg Media programs,
Call 1-800-LEARNER and visit us at www.learner.org.
French subtitles?