Subtitles ST' 501
We need to watch and get involved.
Very soon, you will see what happens.
And you'll be able to say a few words in French yourself.
What will Mireille look like?
Perhaps small, but healthy, athletic, strong.
Long fingers, oval face, long white hair, blue eyes.
She has a lively spirit and a certain pride in pleasure.
Good morning ladies, good morning young ladies, good morning gentlemen.
Today, we're going to create a portrait of the young girl in the story. Okay?
If you wish. You're the teacher. You decide.
Oh no, no, no. I'm just making a suggestion. But we'll discuss it and decide together.
Let's see. Let's try.
Okay. So, in the story, we're going to have a young girl.
Not an old lady.
Not a young woman.
Not a little girl.
But a young girl. Okay?
This young girl is going to be...
Indian.
Indian? No way.
She's not going to be Indian.
She's going to be...
French, of course.
That's it. She's going to be French. It's decided.
And what is his first name?
Ethel.
No, no, no, no. Her first name is not Ethel.
But it's a pretty name.
Perhaps, yes. It's a very pretty name, but it's not a French name. No.
The girl's first name will be...
Mireille.
That's it. Her name will be Mireille. That's decided too.
So, let's start with his physical description.
First, is it going to be big or small?
Small or large?
Big.
Small.
Let's just say it's going to be rather small.
Not small, small, small, but not very big either.
Rather small.
Does she look sturdy? No. She's rather small and she looks fragile. She looks fragile, but actually, she's not fragile at all. She's not sick. Where does her mother work? Do you remember?
at the Ministry of Health.
She is a department head.
Yes, so you can imagine.
than with a mother
who works at the ministry
of Health, Mireille
is in good health.
In fact, his health
is excellent. It is even
She's very athletic. She does
lots of sport.
She does karate.
She rides a bike, she skis,
She plays tennis.
She rides horses.
She goes ice skating, she goes canoeing, she goes hang gliding,
She goes sailing, she goes windsurfing,
She does swimming, she does fencing,
She does mountaineering, she does athletics,
Everything, really. She's definitely the sporty girl.
Will she be thin or a little plump?
Thin, obviously, since she looks fragile.
Let's look at the neck now.
Be careful, the neck is very delicate.
Will she have a long or short neck?
Let's say she's going to have a rather long and thin neck.
And the size?
Will she have a slim or thick waist?
She has a slim waist.
And what about her fingers? Will she have short, thick fingers or long, thin ones?
She has long, thin fingers.
She also has long, slender legs.
She has long, thin fingers and long, thin legs.
Let's look at the face now.
Will she have an oval, oblong, round, or square face?
What do you prefer?
Oval? Good.
Will she be blonde, brunette, redhead, or jatin?
What do you prefer?
You don't know? You don't have a preference?
Okay, so she's going to be blonde.
Damage.
For what ?
Because I prefer brunettes. I like dark hair. Or, or...
Too bad for you. She's blonde and she'll stay blonde.
Now, will she have long or short hair?
What do you prefer? Short or long ones?
Blondes.
Long hair? Very well. I agree.
She's going to have long, blonde hair.
Now, the eyes. Will she have black eyes? Will she have brown eyes? Will she have grey or green eyes? Or will she have blue eyes?
Blue eyes.
Blue? Okay, that's settled. She's going to have blue eyes. Both of them. Do you agree?
All right.
Okay, here's a physical description of Mireille.
She is rather small, she looks fragile, but her health is excellent and she is very athletic.
She is slim, has an oval face, blond hair and blue eyes.
Now, let's paint a moral portrait of Mireille.
How is she feeling?
Let's see
First, she is lively
She has a quick mind
Frankly, Mireille is the most intelligent of the three.
Yes, she's quick-witted.
She is very reasonable
She is very sociable
A little mocking, perhaps.
My sister?
Well, let's say...
Let's just say she's often mocking
But she's not mean at all.
And she has a very good character.
Her? Good character? Oh dear! No way!
Today, we are profiling Mireille.
Here is an artist painting a portrait.
Here is a portrait by Fragonard.
This is a portrait of Diderot.
In Paris, you can find portraits on the sidewalks.
A portrait.
So today we're going to look at the portrait of the young girl in the story. She's small.
She's not tall, she's short, she's short too, this lady is tall, look at this
This bird is small, that one is big. A small house, a big house, a small
house, a big house, and this one, is it small or big, it is
small and this one is big or small it is big and that's a
The girl is small and looks fragile.
like a fragile glass, like a fragile flower, like what is fragile?
another vase or a Chinese horse, the young girl looks fragile but in
In reality, it's not fragile at all; it's very solid.
Look at this glass, it looks fragile, doesn't it? But it's not fragile.
Not at all, he's very sturdy, he looks sturdy but in reality he's fragile, or is that dog?
He looks mean, but actually he's not mean at all, he's very kind. Look at this!
Sir, he looks mean, but in reality he's not mean at all; he's very kind.
Now, listen to what Mireille says.
Well, you seem to like that
Yeah
Now, listen carefully to what Marie-Laure says.
And who is that?
That's a friend from university.
He seems nice
He is very kind
And he is especially very good at skiing and tennis.
He doesn't look very athletic.
He may not look it, but he is.
The young girl looks fragile, but in reality she is very strong.
She is in good health
No, here she is not healthy, she is sick
But here, she is healthy
Sick, healthy
He looks sick here.
But now, he is in good health.
He is not in good health
But here, he is healthy
This gentleman is not in good health
But this one is healthy
Let's see
Will the girl be thin or a little plump?
Thin, a little heavy
Now, let's see, what's she like?
A little strong
A little heavyset. Thin. A little heavyset. Rather thin.
Will the girl have a thin or thick neck?
Thin, thick.
A thin neck, a thick neck.
Will she have a slim or thick waist?
Thin, thick.
The slim waist, the thick waist.
Now, observe.
Thick neck, thick waist.
The male neck, thick.
The feminine waist, thick.
Thick, thick.
Will she have a long or short neck?
Long, court
Does she have a long or short neck?
Long
Alright
Does it have a long or short neck?
Court
Alright
Will the girl in the story have short, thick fingers?
Or long and thin
Will she have short, thick legs?
Long, slender legs
Long and thin
Short and thick
Listen carefully.
A male, female finger
Male
A leg, masculine or feminine?
Female
She's going to have long, thin fingers
And the legs, long and slender.
Long and thin.
Long, long.
Fins, fines.
Will she have a round, square, oval, or oblong face?
He has a square face
She has an oval face
And he has a long face
She has a round face
And she, she has a long neck
He has round eyes
She has elongated eyes
She has a round face.
She has a slim waist.
He has a thick waist.
She has long hair.
She has short hair.
He has long legs.
Let's look at the eyes now.
The girl will have eyes. How many? How many eyes will she have? One eye or two eyes? It's up to you. You can choose. One eye, two eyes. One eye, two eyes.
She may have one eye, like a cyclops or a pirate
Or, she may have a thousand eyes, like a fly.
It's up to you, you can choose
She can have one eye, two eyes, or three eyes.
So, what do you prefer? What do you choose?
Two eyes
Okay, two eyes, very good, yes, that's the most reasonable option.
Two eyes is very good, it's a good average
So it's decided, she's going to have two eyes
Now, we need to choose the color.
Will she have black eyes?
Will she have green eyes?
Or will she have brown eyes?
Or grey? Or blue?
What do you prefer?
Eyes as black as coal?
Eyes as black as a raven, as black as jet, or eyes as green as meadows, as leaves, or eyes as brown, as brown as chestnuts,
Or perhaps grey eyes, grey like the North Sea, or mouse grey, or perhaps blue eyes, blue like the sky when it is blue, or blue like the sea, blue like the Mediterranean, blue like blue flowers.
Blue, she's going to have blue eyes, it's decided.
Okay, fine, that's settled.
She's going to have blue eyes.
Let's see if you understood correctly.
How many eyes do pirates have?
One eye. Pirates have one eye.
Red, preferably.
But this little girl has two eyes.
Two blue eyes.
She has eyes...
Funny.
"But Mireille has blue eyes."
"She has blue eyes, yes, but she could have green eyes."
"Or perhaps her eyes are cooked."
"Yes, but in the story, she's going to have blue eyes."
Look at this young girl.
She has black hair.
She is a brunette.
She has brown hair.
She has red hair, she is a redhead.
And Mireille has blonde hair, she is blonde.
She has blond hair, to have, she is blond, to be.
Let's see if you understood.
She is...
Brown.
Redhead.
This one is...
Chestnut.
...redhead.
This one is...
...blonde.
And Mireille is...
Mireille is very athletic.
She likes all sports.
She likes tennis.
She likes skiing.
She goes skiing.
She goes hang gliding.
She rides horses.
She goes ice skating.
She does karate.
She goes canoeing.
She goes kayaking.
Now pay attention. Listen carefully.
She loves sailing and she goes sailing.
She loves windsurfing and she does windsurfing.
She does swimming.
Now, pay attention. There's a slight complication.
She does fencing.
She does mountaineering.
Let's see what sports French women do. What sports do you do? I do aerobics.
I've done bodybuilding, tennis, classical dance, and karate, this young man
A man goes skiing, they go canoeing, they go hang gliding, they go windsurfing.
She goes sailing, he goes horse riding, they play tennis, he does karate, he goes mountaineering.
Mireille plays tennis, does karate, skis, windsurfs, and swims.
She is very athletic.
Now, observe. Listen carefully.
20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29
30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39
40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49
50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59
60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69
20, 21, 22, 23, 24
30, 30 and 1, 32, 33, 40, 40 and 1, 42, 43.
Mireille has long, blond hair.
She has long, thin fingers.
She has blue eyes.
She is lively.
She has a quick mind.
Ah, that's easy.
She is very intelligent, very quick-witted.
Honestly, Mireille is the most intelligent of the three.
She is very intelligent, quick-witted, and fast-talking.
Fast as a fast train
Fast as a race car
Fast as lightning
She's quick-witted and a bit sarcastic.
She likes to make fun of people
Look at her here, she's making fun of Marie-Laure
Look at yourself there
You're pretty
Oh la la
Now look at these two soldiers.
They are mocking too
They are making fun of Robert
Eddy, did you see the butcher boy walking his girlfriend around?
These soldiers are mocking too.
These children are mocking
They make fun of their father
The children are mocking
He too is mocking
Mireille is mocking
She too is mocking
Mireille is mocking, but she's not mean.
No, she's not mean at all.
She is very kind
He is mean
She is kind
A vicious dog
Beware, vicious dog
Beware, naughty child
He is mean
He too is mean
They too are wicked.
And she's mean too.
But Mireille isn't mean.
She is very reasonable
But Marie-Laure is not reasonable.
Look
Marie-Laure, you're not being reasonable
You're going to be sick
Too bad
I think I'm going to be sick
Too bad for you, too bad, yes, yes, my watch, oh oh, and my watch, my watch, my watch, too bad, too bad
Mireille is witty, intelligent, reasonable, and has a good character, look at Uncle!
Guillaume, Uncle Guillaume has a good character, but this gentleman does not have a good character, he has
This lady is also ill-tempered; she has a bad temper.
He too has a bad temper, this little girl has a bad temper, but what is it?
You think I have time to go to the movies? Oh, but you're bothering me, she has a bad temper and
Mireille, does she have a good character? Her mother says she has a good character, but she isn't
She's not mean at all and has a very good character, but Marie-Laure doesn't agree.
Her personality, no way, everything annoys her, she's mean. Hey, do you remember if you continue?
This is going to end badly, you remember? I remember that slap, you remember?
Mireille doesn't remember, and that's who I am, I don't remember, you don't remember
No, I don't remember.
Too bad, he seems nice.
He remembers.
Let's see what you remember.
Mireille has the face...
Oval.
She is...
Blonde.
She has hair...
Lenses.
She has eyes...
Blues.
She has fingers...
Longs et fins.
She has legs...
She's not mean at all.
She's reasonable, yes.
She is reasonable and has a good character.
She has a bad temper.
No, she has a very good character.
No, she has a bad temper.
You're the one with the bad temper.
I have a good character.
Ouch, ouch, ouch, ouch.
Subtitles ST' 501
the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of Culture and Communication,
the General Commission for the French Language,
le Jesse B. Cox Charitable Trust et le National Endowment for the Humanities.
THANKS.