Subtitles ST' 501
and absorb it.
Very soon, you will see what happens
and you will be able to say a few things in French yourself.
All marbles players go through,
of Uncle William who lost his fortune
to Uncle Georgette who won a battery in the lottery.
She went to the Taj Mahal with the one who left.
The man in black leaves tantalizing notes on Mireille.
Mireille, Robert, Colette, Hubert and Jean-Michel settle down on the terrace of the two mornings.
It's a strange idea to come here for a drink.
Don't you think that's a bit snobbish?
Not at all, I find it perfectly natural.
Look, this is a meeting place for the intellectual elite, and it's part of
Robert's education is a historic café, doesn't it bother you to think that
You might be sitting in Jean-Paul Sartre's chair, yes, yes, yes, I've already sat in it.
on Hemingway's chair at the Closerie des Lilas, my posterior is very honored, I'm going to have a
Well-rubbed-over posterior of literature, boy, yes sir, a corked bottle of cider if you
I'm sorry, we don't have any, sir. Miss would like a bottle of cider, since...
I'm telling you, we don't have any, sir. Figure it out yourself and find us some cider.
Normandy at that moment Mireille, who was facing the boulevard, wrote, "How curious!"
Yes, it's Jean-Pierre himself. What are you doing here? Did you come for a drink with him?
No, thank you, I'm sorry, but I can't, I'm in a hurry, there's a gorgeous girl waiting for me.
Club Med in Martinique, I have to hurry or I'll miss my flight, ciao, and he's leaving and
Well, this one hasn't changed, still as smelly as ever. Hey, look, this isn't
Your godmother, that lady with the cat, little kitty, what are you doing here? You passed by
Your exams? Did you pass? You see, I'm putting the kitty away for boarding. We're celebrating tonight for the
Bulgaria, it seems it's wonderful. I'm going to do a yogurt cleanse. Unfortunately, they don't have any.
wanted to give Minouche her visa. She's going to be bored, poor darling, all alone in Paris. You'd like
Not going to see her from time to time? Oh no, I'm sorry, I won't be able to. We're all leaving
Tomorrow morning at dawn. So, this bottle of cider. Yes, sir, I'll take care of it. Cider.
And the boy heads towards another table.
Hey, no way, it's Guylaine!
Guylaine, where are you going like that?
I'm going to England, to Brighton.
Bruce is waiting for me. Bye, I'll send you postcards.
Our Cider!
Right away, sir, I'll bring it to you.
Hey, isn't that your sister over there?
on this magnificent 10-speed racing bike?
Yes, it's Cécile and her husband.
What a surprise and what a coincidence!
Cécile, are these your bikes?
Yes, we just bought them at BHV. We're leaving for Portugal tomorrow.
By bike?
By bicycle.
Bring me back a bottle of Port. I'll pay you back.
It seems he had nothing to do with it there.
This cider! We're starting to get thirsty.
One minute, sir.
Oh, that's wonderful, Uncle Victor.
One of your uncles or something?
Over there, in the small horse-drawn carriage that just stopped at the red light.
just stopped at the red lights with the sofas among the suitcases on the gallery and
Uncle Victor, are you going to Brest? No, I'm going to Bordeaux. It's a shame they're not going.
In Brittany, we could have asked him to bring us back this bottle of cider.
Oh no, I'm sticking with my Normandy cider, tell me, waiter, this cider is coming, but
Certainly, sir, how curious, how strange, but yes, it's Uncle Guillaume.
In this old clunker, and Uncle Guillaume, what did you do? You have 604, I sold them, yes
I'm ruined, my poor little Mireille, I lost everything at the roulette table in the Monte Carlo casino.
I have nothing left, I need a change of scenery, I'm going to start my life over, I'm leaving for Kathmandu
Yes, it seems you can live there for next to nothing.
Poor Uncle Guillaume, do you want me to lend you my sleeping bag?
No, thank you, you're kind.
There's no point. I'm off.
Hey, I think I recognize those beautiful, muscular legs.
Where? Where is it?
There, the guy on the Solex bikes.
What did he do with his Alpine 310?
Yes, but he never owned an Alpine.
He's broke as a rake. He doesn't have a penny to his name.
Hey Fersen, where are you going like that?
I'm leaving for Greece.
Delphi, the theatre of Epidorus, the Parthenon.
And you, you're leaving, right?
Yes, tomorrow at dawn.
As soon as we've drunk our cider.
Cheers, Skoll.
So, how was the cider?
Yes, yes, it's coming.
Hey, put me through. Tell me I'm dreaming.
But that's not possible.
No, there's no mistake, it's definitely her
But who?
Yes, it's her.
But there, in the pale blue convertible
With sunglasses and a large Balenciaga scarf
But who, exactly?
But you can't see that?
In the convertible, next to the handsome, tanned, dark-haired guy
With the silk shirt from Bronzini
And the black beard and the dark glasses
Well, that handsome dark-haired man is in trouble.
But who is this girl?
But the girl, the girl, don't you recognize her?
That's my Aunt Georgette, you see.
No, not possible.
Yes, I assure you.
Mireille gets up and approaches the convertible.
Oh, oh, Mireille.
You'll never guess what's happening to me.
I'll give you a thousand guesses.
Since I'll never guess, just tell me right now.
Comment ?
But didn't you read it in the newspapers?
I won the lottery jackpot.
That's not true.
But how so?
Are you buying tickets now?
Do you think so? I haven't bought any for a long time.
I never won.
This is a ticket that Fido found while I was walking him along the Luxembourg Gardens fence.
Oh, that's a funny number.
Nothing but brand new ones.
99, 999, 999.
He won 500,000 bucks for that number.
And the next day, I met up with Georges.
We are going to live our lives in the East.
We are going to India.
We're going to get engaged at the Taj Mahal.
Then we will go to Iran to breathe in the roses of Ispan.
None of this is intoxicating.
She's going to get engaged at the Taj Mahal.
At his age? That's insane.
So, boy, this Norman cider.
Here it is, sir.
Finally!
Not a moment too soon. We almost had to wait, as Louis XIV would say.
Better late than never, as my Aunt Georgette would say.
Everything comes to those who wait, as my mother would say.
Give us that bottle quickly. We'll open it ourselves.
Challenge yourself, it's sparkling wine, sir.
Here, Robert, the honor is yours.
Be careful not to pop the cork, okay?
Take it easy.
Robert approaches the cork with infinite but still insufficient care.
The cork hits a gentleman squarely in the forehead, who gets up and runs away hastily, knocking over two or three chairs.
And leaving on his table a cup of black coffee, dark glasses and a notebook from which several photos escape.
And the pages are filled with notes. At the top of the first page, one can read Mireille Belleau, 18 rue de Vaugirard, Paris 6th, art history student.
Watch out, she does karate. We absolutely must catch her alone as soon as possible. Unfortunately, she's almost always accompanied by a tall, dark-haired young man.
Attack plan? Unfortunately, the rest of the notes are completely indecipherable.
Mireille, Robert and the others crossed the church square
To go and sit on the terrace of Les Deux Magots
The Café des Deux Magots opposite the Saint-Germain-des-Prés church
Everyone knows that
It's a strange idea to come here for a drink.
They have a drink
A jar of jam
And a jar of mustard
A pot of paint
A pot of grease and a flower pot.
A pot is a glass.
She takes a drink.
He has a drink in a bistro.
All these people are taking potlucks from the two Magots.
According to Jean-Michel, "Les deux magots" sounds snobbish.
Don't you think that's a bit snobbish?
Going to La Closerie des Lilas, to Les Deux Magots, is snobbish.
A Rolls Royce too, that's snobbish.
An alpine bike looks sporty.
A candlelit dinner is romantic.
This hairstyle, this makeup, it's punk.
Kissing hands is a bit old-fashioned.
Look at Uncle Guillaume.
He looks very young.
Madame Belleau also looks very young.
Jean-Michel thinks that the two magots are snobbish.
Hubert disagrees.
Not at all, I find it perfectly natural
Look, this is a gathering of the intellectual elite
And besides, it's part of Robert's upbringing; it's a historic café.
Uncle Guillaume is part of the family
But Delapierre, Georges' math teacher, is not part of the family.
Aunt Georgette is part of the family
But Jean-Pierre is not part of the family
Fortunately
And is he part of the family?
No, he is not part of the family.
He's part of the rugby team.
Learning to read, doing math, physics, history, geography, all of that is part of education.
Going to De Mago is part of Robert's education.
It's a historic cafe.
Thinking that you are sitting in Jean-Paul Sartre's chair, that's something.
Doesn't it bother you to be ten years old?
Yes, it would affect me.
When this lady sees her little boy bringing her a cake, it does something to her, she is moved.
That makes me happy.
When Robert visited Chartres Cathedral and saw a ray of light on Mireille's blond hair,
"Ah, that affected him."
I have already sat in Hemingway's chair at the Closerie des Lilas.
My posterior is very honored.
My backside is going to be thoroughly rubbed with literature.
Robert is going to get a good dose of literature.
Scrubbed. That's a well-scrubbed saucepan.
And here's a lady cleaning her windows.
And here's a piece of bread rubbed with garlic.
To make pancakes, you need a pan rubbed with fat, oil or butter.
When Robert sits down, he sits on his backside.
A kick in the backside.
And he fell on his backside.
The buttocks.
Hubert orders a bottle of cider.
"Waiter, a corked bottle of cider, please."
"I'm sorry, we don't have any, sir."
"Miss would like a bottle of cider."
"But I'm telling you, we don't have any, sir."
"Figure it out yourselves, find us some cider. From Normandy!"
Now listen to the dialogue between the boy and Hubert, then you will take on the role of Hubert.
"Waiter, a corked bottle of cider, please."
Waiter, a corked bottle of cider, please. Sir, I'm sorry.
We don't have any, figure it out yourselves, find us some cider, figure it out yourselves
We have cider, figure it out yourselves, find us some cider, it's just at that moment
Who is that person walking on the sidewalk? Jean-Pierre Bourdon. He has an appointment at
Club Med at Club Méditerranée, well, that one hasn't changed.
Still as smelly as ever, and that lady who walks by, but it's Madame Courtois, she
going on a yogurt cleanse in Bulgaria if you have liver problems, you can
I'm thinking of doing a mineral water cure or a yogurt cure.
Unfortunately, he didn't want to give me a yogurt treatment.
Minouche's visa, she's going to be bored, poor darling, all alone in Paris.
Won't you want to wash them from time to time?
Oh no, I'm sorry, I won't be able to.
We are all leaving tomorrow morning at dawn.
They will leave at dawn, very early in the morning.
Here comes the dawn.
It's hard to get up at dawn.
And these two young people are Cécile and Jean-Denis
who ride by on magnificent racing bikes.
A bicycle, a bicycle, a mini-bike, a racing bike.
Cécile and Jean-Denis
have just bought
These bikes. Yes, we just bought them
At BHV. We're leaving for Portugal tomorrow.
Colette asks them to bring her back
a bottle of Port.
Bring me back a bottle of Port.
I will reimburse you. Colette
will easily repay
Port wine, since it seems
that it costs almost nothing
in Portugal. Apparently he is
for nothing there.
And now, one of Mireille's uncles is passing by.
His uncle Victor, do you remember him?
The one who is slightly cross-eyed
His right eye is looking towards Brest
His left eye is looking towards Bordeaux
Hey, Uncle Victor, are you going to Brest?
No, I'm going to Bordeaux
He's in an old Citroën 2CV.
with a whole load of luggage on the roof rack
When you no longer have room in the trunk
You can put your belongings on the gallery
a gallery, a gallery on his gallery, Uncle Victor has fishing rods for
He went fishing and caught a fish with a fishing rod.
Fishing, there are fishing rods, rods that older people often have
We need canes. One cane, one cane, one cane, sugar canes. And now,
Who's that in that old, beat-up car? Is that Uncle Guillaume?
Yes, that's Uncle Guillaume in that old clunker. A new car, an old clunker, a
Vieux taco.
A nice car, an old clunker.
Uncle Guillaume no longer has his 604.
He was forced to sell it.
Because he is ruined.
Yes, I am ruined, my poor little Mireille.
This is a ruined castle.
And there you have it, a ruined man.
Uncle Guillaume is ruined.
Because he played roulette at the Monte Carlo casino.
And he lost.
He lost his entire fortune.
I lost everything at roulette in the Monte Carlo casino.
I'm leaving for Kathmandu.
Yes, it seems you can live there for next to nothing.
Three times nothing.
In Portugal, port wine is not expensive.
He's not responsible.
It seems he had nothing to do with it there.
And life in Kathmandu is even cheaper.
It's nothing much.
Yes, it seems you can live there for next to nothing.
At that moment, Robert notices a young man with beautiful muscular legs whom he has seen somewhere before.
What did he do with his Alpine 310?
Yes, but he's never owned an Alpine. He's broke. He doesn't have a penny to his name.
It is cut like the wheat. Wheat. A field of wheat. A harvested wheat field.
They are going to mow, they are mowing, they are mowing, they are mowing with a scythe.
Here, the wheat has been harvested.
And Jean-Claude is broke, broke as a pancake.
Without his forehead. It's cheap, it's for nothing.
Yeah, but I'm broke. I'm scared.
He's broke too, he doesn't have a penny to his name.
And now, Aunt Georgette is driving by in a beautiful little convertible.
She doesn't look like she's broke.
Mireille can't believe what she sees.
She thinks she's dreaming.
Hey, pinch me. Tell me I'm dreaming.
Pinch me.
Here, it was a crab that pinched Mireille.
A lobster claw.
Pliers.
A clothespin.
Come on, give me back my gumballs, or I'll pinch you
Ouch, that one little girl pinched me!
Mireille thinks she's dreaming; she has the impression she's dreaming.
She wants us to pinch her to wake her up
Hey, please pass me the phone, tell me I'm dreaming
Marie-Laure often dreams
Marie-Laure, you're dreaming
No, you're dreaming, that's not right, no, why would I give them to you?
But Mireille isn't dreaming, no, no, no, no, no, it really is Aunt Georgette in that magnificent convertible.
Convertible, remember?
Aunt Georgette is wearing a very beautiful, very chic scarf
He too is wearing a scarf
She too is wearing a scarf
There you go, a scarf
And next to Aunt Georgette, there is a handsome, dark-haired man, a very handsome man, very dark-haired.
A handsome, dark-haired man, yes, a handsome, dark-haired man.
Aunt Georgette's handsome, dark-haired man is very tanned.
Uncle Guillaume is also always very tanned.
Mireille is sunbathing here.
The mountains are great for getting a tan.
You can get a tan at the beach too.
Georges de Pignerole is tanned and he is wearing a silk shirt, silk
He also wears a goatee.
A neck, a collar, a necklace, a beard
A necklace, a necklace, a beard necklace, a beard necklace
Uncle Guillaume is ruined
But Aunt Georgette is rich. She won the jackpot in the National Lottery.
Did I win the lottery jackpot?
They too have won the jackpot.
The 307! The 307!
Come see! Come see! Come! Look!
Oh shit !
We won! We won!
Aunt Georgette won the jackpot with a ticket that Fido found on the ground.
That's luck.
So, Aunt Georgette goes to get engaged at the Taj Mahal.
And then, she's going to Isfahan to breathe in the roses.
Breathe.
Stop breathing.
Aunt Georgette will breathe in the scent of roses
The scent of roses is intoxicating.
Like alcohol, like wine
The sea air is intoxicating too.
Even in the mountains, the air is intoxicating.
She will get engaged at the Taj Mahal
At his age? That's insane.
He's delirious, he doesn't know what he's saying.
She's going to get engaged at the Taj Mahal.
At his age? That's insane.
That's insane. That's insane too.
But they're completely crazy, those women.
That's crazy too.
That too is crazy, that's not normal.
Finally, the cider arrives.
Take it easy.
Gently, gently.
Damn drawer!
Hey, take it easy, you're going to break everything.
Take my gumballs!
Hey, easy now, easy now!
Robert is the one who opens the bottle.
a cork
boucher
unblock
uncork a bottle of Bordeaux
it's not difficult
but uncorking a bottle of sparkling wine
That's another story.
because the Sparkling Wine
it foams
Here's some foam
foam
Sparkling wine
and the cork pops out
The cork pops out, creating a spray of cider.
Here is a sheaf of wheat, a sheaf, sheaves
A spray of cider soaks Mireille's skirt and Robert's jacket
And the cork comes and hits the boy
Thugs attacked this old lady
They hit me to make me tell them where my savings were.
He strikes his instrument
He hits him right in the face
The cork hits the boy right in the face.
And then he continues on his trajectory
The trajectory of an arrow
The trajectory of a ball
The trajectory of a cannonball
The cork hits the boy and the man in black squarely in the forehead
This man is hit right in the forehead, the forehead, the forehead. The man in black runs away, he runs away.
He ran away, and Fido, Fido ran away, the man in black ran away, knocking something over.
He knocks over the chair, he knocks over a flowerpot, there's a boat capsizing, the man in black
She left a notebook on the table; she tore a sheet of paper from her notebook—a ticket book.
a book of metro tickets, an address book, the notebook of the man in black, there are several
Photos slipping away. There are papers slipping away. They're slipping away. She, she can't
Not to escape. But this one manages to escape. Photos escape from the notebook. The photos
escape from the bag. The pages of this notebook are blackened with notes. There are many notes.
The pages are black with notes.
The miners have faces blackened with coal.
These are walls blackened with smoke.
Jean-Claude's eyes are blackened with mascara.
Okay, let's see what you've learned.
Look, listen, think, and speak.
What are Mireille and Robert doing here?
Are they doing a detox or are they just having a pot of something?
They have a drink
Look at this young man
Where does he get kicked?
Right in the forehead or in the buttocks?
In the rear
And what is it?
A bottle of cider or a pot of yogurt?
A pot of yogurt
Do you have friends who are going to Portugal?
You want them to bring you back a bottle of Port
What are you saying?
Bring me back a bottle of Port
I will reimburse you
Look at Jean-Claude here
Is he rolling in money or is he broke?
He's broke.
What do we say when we see something incredible?
Hey, put me through! Tell me I'm dreaming!
Does this gentleman have a scarf or a beard?
A beard necklace.
And what does the cork do?
He jumps.
And what is the man in black doing?
He ran away.
But who is this man in black?
Mystery and a ball of gane.
MFP subtitles.
Subtitles ST' 501
to the French Language,
la Charitable Trust de Jesse B. Cox
et le National Endowment for the Humanities.