Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Good morning, ladies, good morning, young ladies, good morning, gentlemen.
Today, we are going to profile the young man in the story, Robert.
He's American.
He's a solid boy.
You mean he's fat?
No, not at all, he's not fat, no.
It is solid, robust, sturdy.
He's not fat at all.
Obelix is ​​fat. He has a big belly.
But Robert has no belly.
He has no belly at all.
In fact, he's rather thin.
He is 1.70 m, 1.71 m tall,
and it weighs exactly 70 kg.
He is taller than Mireille.
Mireille is 1.63 m, 1.64 m, maybe no more.
At 1.70 m, Robert is taller than her
Or, if you prefer, she is shorter than him.
She is shorter than him
He is very athletic
He does water skiing, surfing, polo, and football.
American, of course, since he is American
He plays basketball, volleyball, handball, hockey, and roller skates.
Is that all?
Yes, indeed. We need to give him some time to work.
Or to take a nap.
Let's return to his physical description.
He is thin, but he is a sturdy boy.
He has broad, square shoulders.
He has a square chin.
Now, is he blond, red-haired, brown-haired, or white?
What do you prefer, madam?
A blond Robert?
Blanc.
Ah, that's a shame, that's a shame
Because I think Robert is going to be dark-haired
Yes, he is dark-haired, he has black hair
Personally, I prefer white or grey hair.
It's more serious, more distinguished
Yes, it's true, grey hair is very distinguished
But not for Robert, come on!
He is a young man, he has black hair
And what about the eyebrows? Will they be brown, red, or blond?
Blondes.
Blonde eyebrows with black hair?
No, madam, no, it won't do, it won't do at all.
With black hair, you need black eyebrows. It's elementary, you know.
Damage.
Yes, madam, it's a shame, but that's how it is. Robert is going to have black eyebrows.
Black. Is black thin or thick?
Thick. He's a solid boy.
Very well. Robert is going to have thick, black eyebrows. Well, quite thick.
Now, is Robert going to grow a mustache?
Do you prefer Robert with or without a moustache?
Which do you prefer? With or without?
Without.
Very well. It's settled. Robert is not going to grow a moustache.
But will he grow a beard?
Which do you prefer? With or without?
So, what do you decide?
A beard or no beard?
No beard.
No beard?
Okay, that's settled. Robert isn't going to have a beard.
and the eyes.
Will Robert have blue eyes?
Black?
Not really.
He's going to have brown eyes.
So there you have it, Robert has no belly.
No beard, no moustache,
no grey hair,
But he has broad shoulders.
black hair,
black eyebrows,
brown eyes.
So much for the physical. Now for the mental aspect. Let's see. Will he be quick-witted too?
No, he's going to be stupid.
Oh no, he's going to be intelligent. He's going to be quick-witted too. A little less quick-witted than Mireille, if you will.
But he's not going to be stupid, no.
He is sociable, but he talks less than Mireille.
He is also less mocking than she is.
Mireille is very mocking.
Yes, that's true then.
Robert is less mocking.
He is more lenient.
In short, they are very different.
Mireille is rather short.
Robert is taller.
She is blonde, he is brunette
She goes ice skating, he goes roller skating
She has blue eyes, he has brown eyes
She is very mocking, he is less so.
She is very lively, he is calmer
What will come of their meeting?
Ah, because you think that in the story, the young man is going to meet the young girl
Yes, perhaps. The young man will meet the young woman, or the young woman will meet the young man. Anything is possible.
What do you think the meeting will yield? Will it yield something like this? Or will it yield something like this?
Or will it turn out something like this? Or will it turn out something like this?
You little fool!
You idiot!
Seriously!
That's not right, is it?
Anything is possible. Chance plays such a large role.
Today, we are profiling the young man.
A very nice young man who is American and whose name is Robert.
Yes, Robert.
Because it's a very pretty name that is both French and American.
So this Robert, he's a solid guy.
He's not sturdy.
But Robert is solid
It doesn't mean fat, no, no, no, no
Obelix, on the other hand, is a bit fat, yes
This gentleman is also quite fat.
He too is rather fat
This gentleman is also rather fat, yes
And this lady, she's quite fat too.
She is a little overweight
She too is rather fat
This one is quite large too
That's a big lady too.
And that's a big car.
But no, that's not a big car, it's a small car.
A big car, a small car.
That's a big truck.
That's a big truck too.
And these are small trucks.
A big dog, a tiny little dog.
A small head, a big head.
Big, fat.
That's a big belly.
This gentleman has a big belly. But Robert doesn't have a belly. He's slim. He's quite tall. Oh, not very tall, but quite tall.
Let's see, we'll measure Robert. Well, he's 1.70 m. Maybe 1.71 m. 1.100 m. 1.50 m. 1.60 m. 1.65 m. 1.66 m. 1.67 m.
One meter sixty-eight, one meter sixty-nine, one meter seventy, one meter seventy-one.
He is one meter seventy-one tall and weighs seventy kilos.
You'll see, we're going to weigh Robert.
Sixty, seventy, eighty, ninety, eighty-seventy, he weighs seventy kilos.
Excuse me sir, how tall are you?
One meter sixty-seven, I think.
Would you say you're rather tall or rather short?
Rather small.
And how much do you weigh?
Ah, 69 kilos.
Would you say you're rather fat or rather thin?
Rather large.
How tall are you, miss?
1,62 m.
How much do you weigh?
45 kilos.
Would you say you're rather fat or rather thin?
Rather thin.
Let's see, let's study these numbers a little.
Listen to Marie-Laure, who can't sleep.
65, 66, 67, 68, 69, 70, 71, 72, 73, 74, 75, 76, 77, 78, 79, 80.
81, 82, 83, 84, 85, 86, 87, 88, 89, 90, 91, 92, 93, 94, 95, 96, 97, 98, 99, 100.
20, 21, 22, 23, etc.
30, 31, 32, 33, etc.
77, 78, 79, 80, 81, 82, 83, 84, 85, 86, 87, 88, 89, 90, 91, 92, 93, 94, 95, 96, 97, 98, 99.
It's simple, it's easy, you can't go wrong.
Now let's see if you can read these house numbers.
60, 61, 62, 64, 66, 68, 70, 74, 78, 81, 85, 91, 99.
Okay, and Robert weighs, how much does Robert weigh?
Seventy kilos, yes. He weighs seventy kilos.
He is one meter seventy-one tall. He is one meter seventy-one.
Mireille is one meter sixty-three tall.
He is 1.71 meters tall. She is 1.63 meters tall.
Look.
She's going ice skating.
"She goes windsurfing."
All French people go windsurfing.
Well, almost all of them.
And you, do you go windsurfing?
It's the verb "to do".
I do, you do, he/she/it does, we do, you (plural) do, they do.
Let's see, what can we do?
You can go skiing, you can go hang gliding, you can go hang gliding skiing, you can go water skiing, you can go ice skating, you can go roller skating, you can go windsurfing, you can also take a nap.
It's less tiring.
Robert, on the other hand, does sports, a lot of sports.
He is very athletic.
It is robust.
Robust like our Marcel.
He's strong.
Obelix is ​​also strong.
Robert has broad, square shoulders.
That's a shoulder.
Shoulders.
Broad shoulders.
Narrow shoulders
A wide road
A narrow road
A broad front
A narrow front
Robert has square shoulders
Those are square shoulders.
That's a square chin
He has no beard
Panoramix has a beard
This gentleman also has a beard
Victor Hugo has a square beard.
A square beard.
Robert has no beard.
He doesn't like beards because they itch.
Look at Marie-Laure. She's scratching herself.
Stop scratching yourself.
The chicken scratches the ground.
This man is scratching.
Here, Marie-Laure is scratching.
She's working. She's doing her homework.
And now she's scratching herself.
They are scratching themselves.
Robert has no beard.
He has black hair.
He is...
Noir.
No, he is not black.
It is white.
Ousmane is black.
He too is black.
She too is black.
But Robert is not black.
It is white.
It is white, but it is brown.
He has black hair.
black eyebrows,
the black moustache,
the black beard,
black, it is brown.
This gentleman
has white hair
And it's black.
He is white and he has
white hair.
But this gentleman has grey hair.
Like me. Me too.
I have grey hair. Grey hair,
It's very distinguished, isn't it?
Distinguished, you understand?
No? Jean-Claude,
Do you want to make a distinction, please?
So.
Distinguished, you understand?
Here is a very distinguished lady, but here she is less distinguished.
This one is not very distinguished, but this one is very distinguished.
A distinguished gentleman. He is less distinguished.
What's going on here? Are you messing with me?
Grey hair, white hair, it makes you look distinguished, it makes you look serious.
Here is a serious young man.
Here is a less serious young man.
A serious young girl.
That's a serious woman.
Now that's a serious man.
Here is a less serious man.
This is a man who is not very serious.
Ousmane is serious.
A serious gentleman.
And this gentleman is serious.
And that gentleman, he's not very serious.
Robert is a serious boy.
Calm. You see, he is very calm. Mireille is less calm. She is more lively.
But what is it, sir? I don't know. It's a breakdown. We'll come, you don't want us. Neither do you, stay calm.
Ah, but I am very calm.
Look, here, the mother is calm, like Robert.
Here, the mother is not calm at all.
So, I'm calm!
He says he is calm, but he is not very calm.
But Robert is calm.
He is lenient.
Look at Uncle Guillaume.
It's nothing
She didn't do it on purpose.
he is lenient
Mireille is less forgiving.
look
But that's not going to work.
you can't pay attention
You idiot, I didn't do it on purpose, you see Uncle Guillaume is more
Mireille is so indulgent, yes indeed, so thankfully now you will
To speak French, listen to this dialogue between Hubert and Mireille and you will
To play the role of Mireille, what's Robert like? Is he tall? No, he
He's not tall, he's not short either, he's blond
Roux ?
No, he's dark-haired. He has black hair and brown eyes.
And how is his morale?
He is very kind, very sociable and very forgiving.
Now it's your turn, you are Mireille.
What's Robert like? Is he tall?
No, it's not big. It's not small either.
Is he... blond?
Roux?
No, he's dark-haired. He has black hair and brown eyes.
And how is his morale?
He is very kind, very sociable and very forgiving.
Robert and Mireille are very different. They don't resemble each other.
This gentleman and this lady are very different. They don't look alike.
But this gentleman and this lady look alike. They are not very different.
But their son doesn't look like them.
"These two little girls also look alike. They look alike. But this gentleman and this lady are very different. The two young people in the story are very different. Observe."
Robert is tall. He is taller than Mireille.
Taller, taller. Robert is taller than Mireille.
Mireille is short. Mireille is shorter than Robert.
She is shorter than Robert.
Mireille is not very tall. She is shorter than Robert.
Taller, shorter. Mireille is shorter than Robert. Mireille might meet Robert. Look here. Mireille meets a friend. Mireille meets another friend. There, she meets a female friend. And there, she meets two male friends.
Look at this gentleman and this lady.
What are they going to do?
They are going to meet.
Here are people meeting.
The young girl and the young man may meet.
It's possible.
It's a matter of chance.
Look, roulette is a game of chance.
Dice are a game of chance, too. So is the lottery. The young woman and the young man might meet. It's possible. Anything is possible. Chance plays such a vast role.
Okay, let's get down to business. For example, the differences between masculine and feminine. Observe. A dark-haired boy, a dark-haired girl. A slender finger, a slender leg. A slender finger, a slender leg.
Now it's your turn.
Redhead, wheel, serious, serious, mocking, mocking, sporty, sporty, lively, lively, widow, widower.
What is this?
He is a young man.
Who is this?
This is Robert.
What is this?
She is a young girl.
Who is this?
This is Mireille.
What is this ?
He is a young man.
Who is this?
This is Hubert.
Now, let's see, in the story, who is going to be blond?
The young man or the young woman?
The young girl.
Who's going to be brunette?
The young man.
What will the young man become?
Brown.
What will the young girl become?
Blonde.
Damage.
For what ?
Because I prefer brunettes.
Too bad for you. She's blonde. Robert, on the other hand, is dark-haired.
Damage.
For what?
Because I prefer white ones.
Oh well, too bad for you. He's dark-haired and has brown eyes.
Damage.
For what?
Because I prefer blue eyes.
Oh well, too bad for you. He doesn't have blue eyes.
But Mireille has blue eyes and long hair.
Damage.
And why?
Because I prefer short hair.
Well, too bad for you. She has long hair.
Okay, well, to finish, let's recap.
Mireille and Robert don't look very much alike.
In fact, they are very different.
Mireille is short. Robert is taller.
She is blonde. He is brunette.
She has blue eyes and he has brown eyes; they might meet.
Mireille might meet Robert, it's possible, and what is the
The meeting will give, it might give something like that or
It will turn out something like this, or the encounter will produce something
Something like that, no, but that's not right, no, stop, stop, stop, or I'll arrest you, come on, come on
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
French subtitles?