Subtitles ST' 501
Good morning, ladies, good morning, young ladies, good morning, gentlemen.
Today, we are going to study Mireille's family.
First, we will study his family tree.
Look, this is a tree.
That's a tree too.
It's a dead tree.
It's a Christmas tree.
And this is also a tree, but it's a family tree.
This is Mireille's family tree.
Let's see, where is she? Do you see Mireille? Ah, there she is.
Let's study Mireille's genealogy.
Let's start with Adolphe Belleau.
In 1912, Adolphe Belleau married Eugénie Daubois
They have two children, Casimir and Anatole.
In 1937, Anatole married Jeanne Langlois
They have five children
Two girls, Georgette and Paulette, and three boys, François, Armand and Guillaume
In 1964, François Belleau married Madeleine Potier
They have three children, three daughters
Cécile, Mireille and Marie-Laure
If you examine the family tree, you will see that Mireille is the daughter of François and Madeleine Bello
Similarly, Cécile is the daughter of François and Madeleine Bello
And Marie-Laure is also the daughter of François and Madeleine Bello
Now, take Yvonne
Whose daughter is Yvonne?
Yvonne is the daughter of Armand and Arlette Bello.
Let's get back to Mireille.
Mireille is François' daughter,
Anatole's granddaughter
and the great-granddaughter of Adolphe Bello.
Let's take Georges now.
Georges is the son of Armand and Arlette Bello.
Anatole's grandson and Adolphe's great-grandson.
Let's examine Mireille's maternal family.
Mireille has a mother.
Who is Mireille's mother?
This is Madeleine Belleau.
Now, who is Louise Potier?
She is Madeleine's mother and Mireille's grandmother.
And who is Lucie Pottier?
She is the mother of Léon Pottier, the grandmother of Madeleine Bello and the great-grandmother of Mireille.
Who is Édouard Pottier?
He is the father of Léon Potier, the grandfather of Madeleine Potier and the great-grandfather of Mireille.
Now, look at Cécile and Marie-Laure.
They are Mireille's sisters, okay?
And Sophie, Sophie Potier, is she Mireille's sister?
No, she's not his sister, she's his cousin.
And Philippe Potier, is he Mireille's brother?
No, he's Sophie's brother, but he's not Mireille's brother, he's her cousin.
Look at Henri Potier, he's Sophie's father.
Is this Mireille's father?
No, it's his uncle.
And Juliette Pottier is Sophie's mother and Mireille's aunt.
Do you want to meet Mireille's family?
Well, we'll give it a try.
Mademoiselle ?
Miss, could you introduce us to your family? My family, yes, that's fine with you.
no yes yes if you want almost everyone is here let's start with my parents dad mom
Here are my father and mother. Here are my sister Cécile and her husband Jean-Denis. Everyone says they
They look like me. Marie-Laure? What? Come on. Oh, listen, I'm busy. Marie-Laure,
I'm telling you to come right away, whatever happened. Hello.
This is my little sister, Marie-Laure.
my cousin Georges and my cousin Yvonne
That's my great-aunt Amélie over there. She's 70 years old and a widow; her husband died.
In the war in 1940, my poor husband next to him is my great-uncle Casimir, he's 85
He's a widower, his wife died of cancer, that's Uncle Guillaume, a brother of Dad.
At 54, he doesn't work, he's wealthy, as my Aunt Georgette says, he has hobbies
And he's still on vacation, that's good, it's nice to have money, he has some
Lucky Uncle Guillaume, isn't he? He has a lot of connections, a lot of connections, it's useful.
He has no children. Is he married? No, he is single.
But he loves children, especially Marie-Laure.
Guillaume is extraordinary. He always finds time for the children.
Yes, yes, I know. And he always arrives with chocolates, gifts. It's easy.
When you have money, that's my aunt Georgette, my father's sister, she's 59 years old.
I think she doesn't have much money; she's not married, she's single too.
Luckily, because she hates children, even her nephews and nieces; she finds them all...
Annoying and tiring children, but deep down she's very kind and I love her very much.
My aunt Paulette and uncle Victor aren't here, nor are my grandparents.
Grandfather isn't doing very well, but I could show you some photos if you'd like, Marie-Laure.
Whatever, what is it now? Go get my album, you're bothering me, you can't go get it.
You can look for it yourself.
That's me at age 6.
That's me at 6 months old.
That's the announcement of my birth in Le Figaro.
This is the announcement of Hubert's birth; he's a friend, we have exactly the same one.
We were born on the same day, this is the birth announcement of Marie Laure.
And who is this?
That's Sophie, my cousin, on my mother's side, a potter.
Ah yes, Philippe's sister?
That's it.
And what's she like? Is your little cousin nice?
Yeah, well, she's nice.
But I prefer my cousins ​​Bélo, especially Georges.
Your cousin is pretty. How old is she?
She's 17. And has a bad temper, I'm warning you.
It's true ?
That's Marie-Laure in a tutu.
That's my Aunt Georgette with her dog.
His name is Fido.
These are my parents.
And that's my grandmother.
That's my grandfather.
That's my great-grandfather.
That's my great-great-grandfather.
That's my great-great-great-grandfather.
And that's my great-great-great-great-grandfather.
Mr. Cro-Magnon.
Besides, he looks just like him. Don't you think?
Today Mireille introduces us to her family
First she will introduce us to her parents
Here are my father and mother
I'd like to introduce you to Mr. Taylor.
Here we introduce the new head of department
I'd like to introduce you to our new head of technical services, Mr. Parcran.
Good morning
He introduces him to the young woman
Allow me to introduce myself, Jean-Pierre Landru
Almost everyone is here, look closely, everyone is here and now
Almost everyone is here, everyone is wearing sunglasses, everyone is going out
Everyone's here, that's Mireille's father, that's her father
Mireille's father, her father, that's Mireille's mother, that's her mother, Mireille's mother, her
mother and that's her grandmother, that's her great-grandmother, and yes, her grandmother, but
his great-grandmother a female cousin his cousin but a female friend his friend
Now look at this, that's Sophie, my cousin. Not bad, your cousin, Mireille's cousin.
My cousin, your cousin, her cousin.
My cousin Georges.
Mireille's cousin, my cousin, your cousin, her cousin.
Let's see if you understood.
Is that Mireille's cousin?
Yes, she's his cousin.
Yes, he's his cousin.
Is that Mireille's father?
Yes, that's his father.
Is that Mireille's mother?
Yes, that's his mother.
That's his aunt.
And that's his uncle
That's his great-uncle
And that's her great-aunt.
That's his grandfather.
And that's his great-grandfather
Let's see if you're starting to get to know Mireille's family.
That's Mireille's mother, Madame Belleau.
That's her husband. That's her daughter. And that's her son. Her son? Mrs. Belleau has a son? No, she doesn't have a son. She has three daughters, but she doesn't have a son.
Look, they have a son
That's a son and his parents
A father and his son
A mother and her daughter
She also has a daughter
I mean, is that your daughter?
No? Well, yes, she's my daughter, I'm her mother.
Yes, that's my mother
Two daughters, their parents, and grandparents
So, the grandson, the grandfather, the grandparents, the grandmother and the grandchildren.
Okay, let's get back to Mireille.
That's Mireille.
That's his father.
His father, yes, very good.
And that's his mother.
His mother, very good.
That's his sister.
Yes, that's his sister.
That's his cousin. That's his cousin. Yes, that's his cousin. And that's... Who is it? It's not his sister, is it? It's not Cécile.
Ah, yes, that's his friend. That's his friend Colette. His friends. His sister, his sisters, his parents, his cousins. That's his aunt. His Aunt Georgette. Aunt Georgette isn't married. She's single.
And that's her uncle, her Uncle Guillaume, Uncle Guillaume. Uncle Guillaume isn't married, he's single. She's single, he's single.
Aunt Amélie is a widow
That's Aunt Amélie with her husband
But her husband died
He died in the war
Aunt Amélie is a widow
A widow
Widows, not very serious
Uncle Casimir is a widower
His wife died
He is a widower
Widower, widow
Look, there's a widow
This gentleman is also single
But he is not a widower, he is divorced.
But his friend is a widower.
Uncle William is rich
He has a fortune
He has money
There's a fortune in that suitcase
Uncle Guillaume does not work
He has hobbies
She has hobbies
He has hobbies too
They too have hobbies
He also has hobbies
This gentleman has hobbies, but he has no hobbies.
And Uncle Guillaume, on the other hand, has leisure time.
He has plenty of leisure time. He has time on his hands.
He's still on vacation.
Look, they're on vacation.
They too are on vacation.
She's on vacation too.
Uncle Guillaume is still on vacation.
He has wealth. He has money.
He's lucky.
Marie-Laure is lucky too.
Choose.
And.
You're lucky.
Nine.
Three.
Five.
You're lucky.
He's lucky too.
Uncle Guillaume has connections.
He has many connections.
Uncle Guillaume loves children.
He loves children too.
Uncle Guillaume always arrives with gifts.
Marie-Laure is lucky, she always gets presents
Well, you have some gifts!
Did you see?
A gift
He buys gifts
Uncle Guillaume has no children
Mr. and Mrs. Belleau have children
You have children too, I believe.
Yes, they have four.
Do you have children?
Oh no, no, no, I'm not married.
You have three children, a grown daughter and two sons.
You can see one here, the other is next door, not far away. I have three children, girls, one
Daughter, you also have boys, two boys, but Uncle Guillaume doesn't have any children, he doesn't have
He has no children, but he has nephews and nieces. Marie-Laure, for example, is a
Uncle Guillaume's niece. Georges is Uncle Guillaume's nephew. He too has
A nephew. You saved my nephew. Oh yes, you saved our nephew. A niece,
a nephew. Aunt Georgette has nephews and nieces, but she has no children.
Luckily, because she finds children annoying, the children, the gasse
Watching Cyprien, musicians, dads, stop, you're annoying me, dad, it excites me and
I'm not doing anything, I've got the Hercules, what you're annoying is annoying
Aunt Georgette finds children annoying and tiring.
Hey Aunt Georgette, can you fix it for me?
Can you be tiring?
She finds all children annoying and tiring.
The children are annoying Aunt Georgette.
But the old professor doesn't bother him at all.
Does it bother you that I work here?
No, no, not at all.
That doesn't bother me at all.
It's the verb "to annoy".
The children are annoying their older sister.
Oh, that's clever! Super clever!
Marie-Laure is annoying Mireille.
Stop! Stop, you're boring me!
She's bothering him.
Stop, you're bothering me!
When Mireille asks Marie-Laure to go get her album, it annoys her, it bothers her.
What? What else is there?
Go get my album.
Oh, you're bothering me!
It bothers her, it annoys her, because she is busy.
Oh, wait, I'm busy!
She is busy here.
But here, it is not occupied.
Aunt Georgette is busy too.
Uncle Guillaume is not busy here.
But here, he is busy.
Let's take a look at Mireille's album.
That's a wedding invitation.
This is the wedding announcement for Cécile and Jean-Denis.
This is a death notice, for the death of great-uncle Casimir's wife.
That's a birth announcement.
This is the birth announcement for Mireille.
That's Mireille at birth.
That's the birth of Venus according to Botticelli.
That's the birth of the Virgin by Murillo.
That's a double birth
That's an announcement from the newspaper Le Figaro.
This is the announcement of Hubert's birth.
And this is a photo of Cécile
She looks a lot like Mireille
Everyone says she looks like me
They look alike
It's amazing how much you look like your grandmother
That's Mireille's great-great-great-grandfather.
Marie-Laure says that Mireille looks like her.
Besides, she looks just like her. Don't you think?
That's a picture of Sophie.
She's not bad.
Your cousin isn't bad looking.
She's not bad either.
He's not bad either.
Robert isn't bad either.
He is less well
He's not bad
She's not bad
But what do you think, that I have time to go to the cinema?
Oh, but you're bothering me!
She's not bad-looking, but she has a nasty temper.
She's 17 and has a terrible temper, I'm warning you.
There are a lot of people with bad tempers, I'm warning you.
Here, look
This man has a bad temper
He too has a bad temper.
She has a bad temper.
This police officer has a bad temper.
This one also has a bad temper.
He has a bad temper.
Okay, now listen to this conversation between Mireille and Jean-Denis,
and then you will play the role of Jean-Denis.
That's Sophie, my cousin.
Your cousin isn't bad looking.
How old is she?
She is 17 years old.
And he has a bad temper, I'm warning you.
It's true ?
Okay, now, look at this.
What is this ?
This is a photo of Marie-Laure in a tutu.
And that's Aunt Georgette and her little dog.
Repeat, rebel.
Now, pay attention. Listen carefully.
What is this?
That's a house in Brittany.
And what is this?
That's a tree.
Who is it?
That's my aunt.
She is very kind.
Who is it?
One person. Aunt Georgette, Uncle Guillaume, my cousin.
What is it? A thing, a house, a tree, a photo, a dog.
Who is that?
Who is it ?
Who is it?
Who is it? Who is it? Who is it? Who is it? It's all the same.
So who is it? I don't know, Mom. Who is that? Who is this? Is that your great-grandfather Adolphe?
Bello, what is it? We say it's good, but what isn't it? Obviously not.
With a red eye, good for you now, let's see if you can answer who this is, it's the father
Mireille's? No, that's her mother. Who is it? Her aunt? No, her uncle. And who's this?
Uh, who is it? We say, who is it? Oh, good, good. Well, who is it? Two young people.
And what is this?
Well, that's my stick.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada