Subtitles ST' 501
and get involved pretty soon you will figure out what's going on and be able
to say a few things in French yourself
lesson 9 takes us back a few years to vacation time in Brittany it's raining
Mireille her sisters and cousins decide to pass the time by playing a game of
portraits their game is interrupted by a minor accident
Two years ago, the summer holidays
at Belle-Île-en-Mer, in Brittany.
It's raining.
Mireille, Cécile, Marie-Laure,
their cousin Georges and their cousin Yvonne
are alone in a house rented jointly by the two families.
That's our lucky break.
It has been raining for three days.
Your Brittany is beautiful.
Yes, the sea is deadly when it rains.
There's nothing to be done.
Shall we play belote?
Playing belote in the house? We don't have the space.
No, Bécasse, it's belote, not pelota.
Are you deaf or something?
We're not going to play Basque pelota in Brittany.
But we can play cards.
At belote, bridge, poker, écarté.
How boring.
You can play chess or checkers.
We can play chess
Or, for the ladies, it's less complicated.
Oh no, all of this is deadly
Let's play at drawing portraits instead.
Yes, that's an idea, let's play portraits.
That's it, let's make some portraits.
How do we play the portrait game?
It's very easy
Someone describes a person in three or four sentences
For example
She is tall, she has one blue eye, she has one grey eye.
She is very kind.
And then the others, guess who they are.
Who is it?
Who ?
Tall, with one blue eye, one grey eye, and very kind.
I don't know. It's nobody.
It doesn't exist. It's an example.
Really? We're inventing people who don't exist?
No way! Can you be stupid?
When we play, we use real people.
Obviously, otherwise we can't guess. Okay, let's begin. We'll start with...
Family people, what's starting? She's yours, Yvonne, you
Start, I have no idea, but yes, let's see, it's not difficult, you take
Someone from the family, anyone, is waiting, I'm looking for
Ah, that's it, I know. He's tall, he has short gray hair, he's always tanned, he has a good character, he's always in a good mood, he's very generous, he always gives gifts, he loves...
Uncle Guillaume, that's too easy.
What does Uncle Guillaume like?
Children, Bécasse.
Okay, it's my turn now.
A fine, pointed nose, thin lips, sharp teeth, and a high-pitched voice.
Ah, that kid is so annoying!
So many Georgettes!
Okay, me now.
The great athlete, very proud of his achievements,
moved on to running, the 100 meters, the 400 meters,
in the marathon, the high jump, the pole vault,
In short, the perfect athlete.
Never miss a sporting event.
As a spectator.
On TV, obviously.
And he even plays tennis.
Once a year.
Oh dear, how mean she is, that's Dad.
Obviously, it's your father.
Okay, my turn.
With a distinguished air,
delicate hands,
blue eyes,
blond hair,
The whole portrait of his second daughter.
Oh, how gallant the little cousin is.
Okay, we're not going to say who it is.
Yes, yes, we'll say who it is.
Who it is, who it is, it's not important.
What's important is the snack.
It's 4 o'clock, past 4 o'clock.
Come on, children, it's past 4 o'clock, it's snack time.
Tell me, tell me who it is.
Oh, but shut up, you're being annoying.
Tell me who it is, I want to know who it is, na.
First, you go get the snack.
I'm not your maid, go ahead.
Listen, do you want to know who it is?
Yes.
So, go get the snack.
Ah, can you be annoying?
She is not happy.
But she's going.
Bring some Orangina and lemonade.
Orangina and lemonade.
There are raisin buns.
And raisin buns.
Bring the Breton galettes too.
Breton galettes?
There aren't any left.
Yes, there are some left.
Yes, there are at least five or six left.
There are none left.
Are you sure?
Of course I'm sure, since I'm telling you so.
Oh, you can believe me, right?
But soon, there won't be any left.
Be careful what you do!
Oh, that's clever!
It's not my fault.
Listen, it's not a big deal. Come on, don't cry.
So, who is it?
The story takes place in the past, two years ago.
That's in the past.
Let's take a trip, for example.
That's the present, today.
And that's the past. 100 years ago. That's Mireille now, today. That's Mireille 3 years ago. That's Mireille 10 years ago. That's 2 years ago. And this is in Brittany. It's the holidays.
Look at that. Is this the holidays? No.
These people are not on vacation.
And now? Is it vacation time? No.
Yes, that's what holidays are all about.
These people, on the other hand, are on vacation.
Summer holidays.
That's what holidays are, but winter holidays.
And that's what holidays in Brittany are all about.
Mireille, Cécile and Marie-Laure are on holiday in Brittany.
There are also their cousins, Georges and Yvonne.
The parents are not there. The children are alone, without their parents.
Here, Mireille and Marie-Laure are alone.
But here, they are not alone.
This gentleman is alone. But here, no, here he is not alone.
Well, Mireille and her sisters are alone in a rented house. It's a rented house, a house for rent.
If you are on holiday, winter holidays, and you don't have skis, you can rent skis.
Look at that lady, she's renting skis. If you don't have a car, you can rent one.
That car doesn't belong to Robert. Robert doesn't own a car. It's a rental car. He rents it.
This house in Brittany isn't for cycling. It's a rental property. He rents it out for holidays.
Mireille is not happy. Listen.
That's just our luck. It's been raining for three days.
Your Brittany is beautiful.
She is not happy because it is raining, it is raining, it is raining here too, it is raining there too, it has been raining for three days, look.
Today, July 6th, it is raining.
It's been raining for a day.
Yesterday, July 5th, it rained.
So it's been raining for two days now.
And the day before yesterday, July 4th, it rained.
So it's been raining for three days now.
It's been raining for a day.
It has been raining for two days.
It has been raining for three days.
That's our lucky break.
Mireille, Cécile, and Georges are unlucky.
They're unlucky because they're on vacation and it's raining.
They, yes, they, are lucky
They are on vacation and the weather is nice, it's not raining.
They are lucky
This gentleman is lucky
Mireille is unlucky, look
Damn, what's wrong?
Well, look, this is my chance, isn't it? This is my chance.
That's our lucky break.
But your Brittany is beautiful, isn't it?
Mireille says that because she's not happy.
But, in fact, yes, Brittany is beautiful, very beautiful.
Brittany is beautiful. It's a very beautiful country.
There are beautiful beaches, beautiful calvaries, and pretty little fishing ports.
When the weather is nice, it's a very beautiful country.
But, obviously, when it rains, it's less beautiful.
The sea is deadly when it rains.
It's sad, it's boring
We're bored because there's nothing to do
I'm bored, there's nothing to do
This young man is bored because he has nothing to do.
At the seaside, when it rains, what can you do?
Nothing !
We can't play ball
We can't go boating, we can't go windsurfing, we can't do anything.
Yes, we can play chess, we can play checkers, we can play cards, bridge, poker, écarté, belote.
Playing belote in the house? We don't have the space.
No, Bécasse, it's belote, not pelota.
Belote is a card game. Mireille and Marie-Laure are playing belote. Pelote, now that's something else. Pelote is a game from the Basque Country. Georges isn't very nice to Marie-Laure. He calls her a silly goose.
No, you silly goose.
"Silly, idiot, that's not very nice. That's a silly girl. People say silly girls are stupid. A silly girl is a little girl who isn't very quick-witted. That's Bécassine, a maid who isn't very quick-witted. She's a bit silly."
Is Marie-Laure a bit of a simpleton or is she deaf?
Belote and pelote are not the same thing. They are different.
Are you deaf or something?
Is Marie-Laure deaf?
Look at Jean-Claude here. He is deaf.
This gentleman is also deaf. He can't hear very well.
Mireille, Cécile and the others are bored because it's raining and they can't do anything.
But Mireille has an idea.
Okay, I have an idea.
Let's play portrait.
Yes, that's an idea. It's a good idea. It could be fun.
Here, it's Newton who has an idea.
Mireille's idea is to play at portraiture.
When you are on vacation, you can go windsurfing, you can go swimming, you can go hang gliding, you can go skiing, you can go rock climbing, or you can play belote, play hopscotch, you can play tennis.
Swimming is a sport, an activity, a sport that is good for your health.
Belote is a game, a game with rules.
Scrabble is also a game, a game with rules.
Mireille, Cécile and the others are going to play portrait.
Portraits are a game, a game with a rule.
Someone describes a person. Someone, that is to say, anyone. For example, Mireille or Cécile or Marie-Laure or Georges or you or me or this gentleman.
This lady is someone. Someone is masculine. A lady, feminine, is someone, masculine.
So, to play the portrait game, someone describes a person. For example, Mireille, Cécile, Georges, or you, or this gentleman.
That's a person.
Now, pay attention. Observe this carefully.
A man, masculine, is a person.
Female.
To play the portrait game, you have to describe someone in three or four sentences.
For example, he has a round face, blue eyes, blond hair, and a mustache.
Three or four sentences.
Someone describes a person and the others guess who it is.
We need to find out who it is.
Look, in this game too, you have to guess who it is.
Ah, it's Georges!
Oh, she guessed it!
Guess what I have.
I don't know.
A snake!
Ah!
Guess who this is, Georgette! You have to guess who it is. What can I ask you? How old is she?
You guessed who it is, the tall one with one blue eye and one grey eye, who is very kind, I don't know
Not if nobody, nobody, look at that, that's a person and that's nobody, a person
Nobody there, there's someone, there's a person, and there's nobody there. Is there someone here?
Someone? Is there someone here? No, there's no one. Ah, ah, yes, yes, yes, there is someone.
Careful, now it's going to get very complicated. Look. Is there anyone in the
Room? Yes, there are two people. And now, is there anyone in the room? No,
Now, there's no one here. Playing the role of portrait artist isn't difficult. First,
We need to choose someone.
Yes, come on, it's not difficult.
You take someone from the family.
Anyone.
Georges says we need to take someone from the family.
It's easier.
Look at Mireille here.
She takes a candy.
And Marie-Laure takes the others.
You take this candy.
And I'll take the others.
Look at Marie-Laure.
She takes a pancake and eats it.
Here, take your raincoat, it's better
Okay, so, what are you having?
I think I'll take the cream-coated puppy
Now, observe Yvonne, she is looking
I'm looking... Let's see... Ah, that's it, I know
Now look at Marie-Laure, she's looking for her Asterix.
What are you doing?
I'm looking for my Asterix.
Look at this lady.
She is searching.
She's looking for something.
Now, look at Jean-Claude.
He is searching.
Yvonne describes a person with round cheeks.
Round cheeks, like that.
Hollow cheeks.
Round cheeks.
Those are round cheeks.
And here's someone with a fresh complexion.
But no, that's not it. That's not a fresh complexion.
Yvonne describes someone who is always in a good mood.
Here is a lady who is in a good mood.
But here, she is not in a good mood.
Yvonne describes someone who is generous.
Here is a generous man. Here is a generous lady.
Georges describes someone with a pointed nose
That's a round nose
And there's a pointy nose!
Sharp teeth
Pointy ears
A pointed leaf
Thick lips
Thin lips
Mireille makes fun of her uncle
Georges and Yvonne's father.
She makes fun of him because he is proud
of his past sporting performances.
Marie-Laure is very proud of her skirt.
Look at Jean-Claude, he's proud.
The great sportsman, very proud of his past performances.
In the race, the 100 meters, the 400 meters,
In the marathon, the high jump, the pole vault, the perfect athlete, in short.
Running, here it's a cycling race, a car race, high jump, pole vault.
Marie-Laure also does rope jumping.
Mireille makes fun of Uncle Armand because he's not a real sportsman.
He doesn't really play sports, but he watches all the sporting events on television.
Now that's a real sportsman, he does sports.
But that, that's not a real sportsman.
He doesn't play sports, he watches the matches on TV.
But he watches all the matches.
He watches all the rugby matches.
He never misses a rugby match.
He watches all the tennis matches.
He never misses a tennis match.
Georges is painting a portrait of Mrs. Belleau.
He says she looks distinguished.
A distinguished air, slender hands, blue eyes, blond hair.
And that she resembles Mireille.
A complete portrait of his second daughter.
Cécile is Mrs. Belleau's first daughter.
Mireille is his second daughter.
And Marie-Laure, his third daughter.
Oh, how gallant the little cousin is.
Georges is gallant because he pays Mireille a compliment.
He says she looks distinguished.
The French think they are gallant.
They love to talk about French gallantry.
Here, look.
My respects, madam.
That's a gallant Frenchman.
Here's another gallant Frenchman.
All Frenchmen are gallant.
Finally, almost all French people are gallant.
He is not gallant.
Marie-Laure doesn't know who it is.
We take a portrait, but she doesn't know who it is.
The distinguished air, the delicate hands, etc.
She doesn't know.
So, she wants to know.
Tell me who it is, I want to know who it is.
When you're a 10-year-old girl like Marie-Laure,
You need to know a lot of things.
You need to know your multiplication table.
Note 9 x 8, 72, 10 x 8, 80.
You need to know La Fontaine's fables.
Master Crow, perched on a tree, held a cheese in his beak.
Observe this.
First, go get the snack.
I'm not your maid, go do it yourself.
Marie-Laure protests that she is not Mireille's maid.
Look here, that's a maid, that's Madame Courtois' maid.
Madame Courtois ?
Oh no, that's the right one.
That's the right one.
That's a good one too.
Bécassine is a good one.
For a snack, there are Oranginas or lemonade to drink.
And for food, there are raisin buns, biscuits, and Breton galettes.
Look, how many pancakes are there?
One, two, three, four.
There are four pancakes.
Now there are three pancakes left. There are three left. And now there are two left. Now there is one left. And now there are none left. There are none left.
There's one pancake left, there's one pancake left, there's one left, there are zero pancakes left, there are zero left, there are none left
Marie-Laure goes to get the snack and when she comes back, disaster strikes, she drops everything
Mireille criticizes
Oh, that's clever.
Look at this young girl
Notice that Mireille also makes mistakes, look
Shit
What, what is it?
But look
That's clever.
But it's not my fault
Maybe it's my fault
That's clever, can't you be careful, you dirty little girl?
It's not my fault, I didn't do it on purpose
It's not my fault, she's crying. It's raining and she's crying. Now you're going to speak French.
Listen to this dialogue between Mireille and Marie-Laure. You will repeat Mireille's answers.
Who is it? I want to know who it is! First, you go get the snack. I'm not your maid.
Go ahead, you.
Listen, do you want to know who it is?
Yes.
So, go get the snack.
Now it's your turn. You are Mireille.
Tell me who it is. I want to know who it is. No.
First, you're going to go get the snack.
Now it's your turn.
Yes, I'm not your maid. Go ahead.
Listen, do you want to know who it is?
Yes.
Now go get the snack.
Okay, to finish up, let's see what you know how to do.
How many pancakes are there?
Four.
There are four pancakes.
There are four pancakes left. Very good. And now, how many are left? There are three left. And now, there are two left. And now, there is one left. And now, there are none left.
Two young people.
There's one left.
There are none left.
It's over.
...
Subtitles ST' 501
www.learner.org