Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada
Yes, you know the person in Georges' portrait from earlier.
The slender hands, the blue eyes, the blond hair, the entire portrait of his second daughter.
You're bothering us.
But I want to know who it is.
Okay, look at Mireille. Doesn't she look distinguished?
Yes.
Does she have delicate hands?
Does she have blue eyes?
Yes.
Does she have blonde hair?
So, this is Mireille.
Can you be stupid?
Listen, the whole picture of her second daughter, does Mireille have any daughters?
Well no.
So, it's not Mireille.
She is someone who has a daughter, who looks distinguished, with slender hands, blue eyes, and blond hair, like Mireille.
So, it's Mom.
That's it.
Ah.
So, shall we continue?
Oh, that's enough.
Oh no, I like it. It's difficult, but it's fun.
Okay, so, listen.
His right eye is looking towards Brest.
His left eye is looking towards Bordeaux.
Oh dear, isn't she mean?
Poor Uncle Victor, he's hardly cross-eyed.
So, who is it?
Uncle Victor.
For what ?
Because Uncle Victor relaxes a little, his eyes are not looking in exactly the same direction, that's all.
Okay, my turn now.
He has a straight nose, always clean-shaven, he even has a shaved head, probably to hide the fact that he's going to be bald.
Uncle Henri, your portrait is too easy.
Drink me now.
A bit of a mustache, a big mouth, but no chin.
And she always talks about her late husband.
Ah, back in the days of my poor husband.
No need to continue, it's Aunt Amélie.
Your portraits are all too simplistic.
I'll do the next one.
Warning, this is going to be more difficult.
Protruding ears,
large glasses,
an enormous beard
drooping mustaches,
and above all
an enormous nose.
Monumental.
Your little man isn't very handsome.
I don't see
From stone, our math teacher
Oh, but that's not fair.
We don't know your math teacher.
He is not related
Luckily he's not related
He's as dumb as a doorknob
And there's nothing more cowish
Well, I think that's enough.
We've been playing this stupid game for two hours.
What are we showing at the film club tonight?
Hey Marie-Laure, look in the newspaper
What am I watching?
What's showing at the cinema tonight? Are you deaf or something?
See if there are any new movies.
Tonight, we're playing Claire's genius.
Claire's genius? What's that all about?
But you can't read? It's not Claire's genius, it's Claire's knee, you idiot.
By Eric Romère. Everyone knows this, it's an old film.
Claire's knee, Claire's knee. It has to be said, it's a strange title.
And why not Claire's foot, or Claire's ankle, or Claire's toe.
Hi everyone. So what are you doing?
It hasn't rained for an hour.
It's not raining anymore?
Oh no?
Not possible.
Yes, yes, I assure you, it's rising.
So, are you coming to go sailing?
No, old man, not today. Today we're taking a nap.
Wait for me, Jean-Denis. I'll come, if you want.
Oh là là, those sporty ones!
Hey, we'd chain you up, that's fine.
Mireille, her sisters and her cousins ​​are playing portrait game to pass the time.
When you have nothing to do, you have to pass the time.
To pass the time, one can read.
To pass the time, you can watch television.
To pass the time, you can play cards.
Time passes.
When you have nothing to do, when you're bored, time passes slowly.
But when you're having fun, time flies.
Time passes, time gone by
There are two times, two kinds of time
Time passing
And the weather
For example, the weather here is bad
The weather is nice here.
The weather is bad, the weather is nice
The weather is bad, it's raining.
Now it's not raining anymore
It's rising.
And now, the weather is nice.
The weather is bad.
It's rising.
The weather is nice.
Georges painted a portrait.
A distinguished air, slender hands, blue eyes.
But Marie-Laure doesn't guess who it is.
She wants to know who it is.
So she asks.
So who is it?
Mom, who is that?
Now, observe what Jean-Denis says
And who is this?
Who is it? Who is it? Who is it?
Now, observe this small scene
Who is that?
Who is it ?
Who is it?
Who is it? Who is it? Who is it? Who is it? It's all the same! So, who is it?
But I don't know! Mom, who is that?
Who is it ?
That's your great-grandfather, Adolphe Bélot.
Who is it? Who is it? Who is it? Who is it? Who is it?
Mireille is painting a portrait of Uncle Victor. Uncle Victor is cross-eyed.
I'm cross-eyed too. Look.
Yes, but Uncle Victor is different.
He has one eye looking towards Brest and the other towards Bordeaux, on the Bordeaux side, in the direction of Bordeaux.
Towards Bordeaux, on the Bordeaux side, in the direction of Bordeaux.
Uncle Henri has a straight nose.
That's a straight nose.
A hook, a hooked nose.
A straight nose
A hooked nose
Uncle Henri has a shaved face
He's not shaved there.
There, he is shaved
He has no beard, he has a shaved chin.
Here, he's shaved, but he's badly shaved.
This gentleman is also unshaven.
But this gentleman is clean-shaven.
This gentleman is also clean-shaven.
He is always very well shaved.
He too is always very well shaved, closely shaved.
And he even has a shaved head.
Uncle Henry is going to be bald.
This gentleman is bald.
This gentleman is also bald.
The gentleman on the right is not bald.
The gentleman on the left is not bald.
But the man in the middle is bald.
Uncle Henri has a shaved head.
He shaves his head because he wants to hide the fact that he's going to be bald.
Look at Marie-Laure here. She wants to hide her chocolates.
What are you doing ?
I'm hiding my chocolates.
For what ?
Because Mireille eats them all.
She's hiding something behind her back here.
Aunt Amélie has a bit of a moustache.
A little moustache, a lot of moustache, a huge moustache, drooping moustaches.
Asterix has drooping moustaches.
Aunt Amélie has no chin.
He has a big chin, a round chin.
Aunt Amélie always talks about her deceased husband.
Her husband is deceased, he is dead.
When she talks about her husband, she always says, "My poor husband, because he's dead."
When Mireille paints a portrait of Aunt Amélie, Georges says, "No need to continue, that's Aunt Amélie."
There's no point in continuing. He knows who it is, he's guessed. There's no point in continuing. Listen.
What are you looking for?
My Asterix.
There's no need to look for it, Mom reads it.
Now listen to what Mireille is going to say
Stop
I'm telling you to stop
There's no point in crying now
Too bad for you, it's your fault
Now listen to what Marie-Laure is going to say
Marie-Laure
Marina
There's no need to shout.
I am not deaf
Georges painted the following portrait
Look
Here is a number
That's 5
The next number is 6
The next number is 7
And the next number is 8
And so on
Next, next
The next number
The next house
Georges paints a portrait of his math teacher, his mathematics teacher.
He has protruding ears.
Those are ears glued on.
And there you have it, protruding ears.
Glue.
This new baby at the English court does not have his father's protruding ears.
The math teacher has ears.
I have ears too.
Everyone has ears.
Even doors have ears.
He also wears glasses.
He wears glasses too.
Large glasses.
Large black glasses.
He also has a big nose.
A huge, enormous nose, like Cyrano's nose.
A monumental nose.
A nose as big as a monument, like the Eiffel Tower, for example.
That's a big nose, a monumental nose.
With his big nose, Georges' math teacher isn't good
Besides, he's stupid, as dumb as a doorknob.
The head is intelligent
But feet aren't intelligent, they're stupid, dumb.
The head decides and the feet follow, foolishly, stupidly.
The math teacher is as dumb as a doorknob
And what's more, he's a cow, he's mean
That's a cow
The math teacher is a jerk. People usually say that police officers are jerks. Georges' math teacher is a jerk, a real jerk, extremely a jerk. He couldn't be more of a jerk. He's the absolute worst.
Look. These are protruding ears. These are very protruding ears.
And those are ears, you couldn't find any more prominent.
With his big nose and protruding ears, the math teacher isn't very handsome. He's a strange fellow.
Your little man isn't very handsome. Your little man isn't very handsome.
A man, a gentleman, a fellow, a funny fellow, a little fellow.
A Santa Claus, a snowman, a funny little man
When Georges says that it's her math teacher, Mireille is not happy, she protests.
Oh, but that's not fair, oh, but that's not fair
When you play a game, you have to follow the rules of the game.
When you play the portrait game, you have to choose someone everyone knows; that's the rule of the game.
But Mireille doesn't know Georges' math teacher.
Cécile doesn't know him either.
Yvonne doesn't know him either.
We don't know your math teacher.
Look at Mireille here
Hello, Miss Bello, how are you?
I'm fine, thank you, and you, are you well?
She knows this professor
More...
I can ?
Yes, you can.
THANKS
Aunt Georgette doesn't know him
Aunt Georgette doesn't know many people
Hello, Osman
Are you doing well ?
Yes, you're fine.
Mireille knows a lot of people, she knows a lot of people, she is very sociable.
She knows people.
She knows a lot of people.
Hi how are you ?
I'm fine, thank you, and you?
Mireille knows a lot of people, but she doesn't know Georges' math teacher.
Cécile doesn't know him either.
Marie-Laure doesn't know him either.
Yvonne doesn't know him either.
We don't know your math teacher.
Who is it? We.
We are Mireille, Yvonne, Cécile, or Marie-Laure, or Uncle Guillaume, or Balzac, or Mr. Bello, or Mrs. Bello, well, we are anyone.
In France, we speak French.
Who speaks French in France?
Well, everyone, people in general.
We speak French.
We speak French, people speak French, we speak French.
Mireille wants to go to the cinema.
She wants to go see a movie.
Hey, what are we showing at the film club tonight?
She wants to go to the cinema because it's raining, there's nothing to do, and she finds the game of portraits boring.
Well, I think that's enough.
We've been playing this stupid game for two hours.
She thinks it's a silly, idiotic, stupid, boring game.
It's been two hours.
We've been playing portrait for two hours.
It has been raining for three days.
We've been playing for two hours, and it's been raining for three days.
On that day, we don't show a new film, we play Claire's knee.
This is not a new film, it's an old film.
Yes, that's a new film, it's new.
Listen.
It's a new sweater.
What sweater?
No, it's old, I've had it for two years.
But you have a new skirt.
This skirt?
I've had it for three years.
A new sweater, a new skirt. New, new.
We're not playing a new film, we're playing an old film called Claire's Knee.
The knee, the ankle, the foot, the toe, the leg.
The right leg, the right foot, the left leg, the left foot, the left foot, the left leg.
The right foot, the right leg.
The left arm, the right arm.
And that's the Venus de Milo.
She has no arms.
She has no right arms, nor does she have left arms.
Okay, now we're going to do a portrait.
Let's see if you can guess who it is.
That big nose, that big beard,
those drooping mustaches,
Her protruding ears, her large glasses
Who is it ?
Do you see? Can you guess?
But that's Georges' math teacher.
This fellow isn't very handsome.
Professor of Stone
Okay, now, observe what Jean-Di says.
It hasn't rained for an hour.
It's not raining anymore
Oh no?
Not possible
Yes, yes, I assure you, it's rising.
Yes, yes, I assure you
Observe
It's possible
Yes, it's possible.
That's not possible
It's possible
Yes
That's not possible
And
Observe
I don't look distinguished.
And
I don't have blue eyes.
Now, observe
It's not my fault
Yes, it's your fault, you idiot.
You never pay attention to anything
No, it's not my fault
Yes, it's your fault
Non
And
It's not my fault
Yes, it's your fault
Now, look at this other scene.
Is anyone there?
No, there's nobody here.
Oh, if there's anyone
If there is anyone
Another example
It's my turn to play
Yes, it's yours.
No, it's not hers.
Yes, it's hers.
Non
And
It's mine
Yes, it's yours.
It's not mine.
Observe.
Whose turn is it?
It's your turn.
Is this mine?
No, it's not hers.
So whose is it then?
It's his.
It's mine.
It's ours.
It's your turn.
It's up to you.
It belongs to Georges.
It's his.
It belongs to Georges and Mireille.
It's up to them.
It belongs to Cécile.
It's hers.
It belongs to Cécile and Mireille, it belongs to her.
To me, to you, to him, to her, to us, to you (plural), to them, to her.
Yeah! Your turn!
It's stopped raining. The sun is rising.
Jean-Denis suggests going sailing.
So, are you coming to go sailing?
No, old man, not today.
Today, we're taking a nap.
Listen.
So, are you coming?
I'm coming, I'm coming.
I'm coming, you're coming, we're all coming.
She comes, he comes, they come
We come, you come.
So, are you coming?
I'm coming, I'm coming.
Oh la la!
Okay, I'll wait.
Waiting, I'm waiting,
You wait, he waits,
"We wait, you wait, they wait."
"You're going to call him. No, wait, wait. So, are you coming to go sailing?"
"No, old man, not today. Today we're taking a nap."
"Wait for me, Jean-Denis. I'll come, if you like."
"Wow, what an athlete! Here, take your raincoat, you'll feel better."
Mireille throws a raincoat to Cécile.
Sailors wear oilskins, but so do tourists.
When it rains, you need to take an umbrella.
That's better.
It's raining, everyone inside.
Everyone inside.
When it rains, it's best to have a raincoat.
You should take a raincoat, it's better that way.
It's best to wear a raincoat.
When it rains, what is the best thing to do?
Go sailing or play at being a portrait artist?
It's better to play at portraiture.
When the weather is nice, what is the best thing to do?
Going to the cinema or going sailing?
It's better to go sailing.
When it rains, is it better to go to the cinema or go sailing?
It's better to go to the cinema.
Let's see now.
It's raining and you want to go to the cinema.
Are you taking an umbrella?
Yes, that's better.
It's raining and you want to go sailing.
Are you taking a raincoat?
Yes, that's better.
The weather's bad, what are you going to do?
Are you going mountaineering, rock climbing, or are you going to play cards?
It's better to play cards, yes, it's better.
Now you are going to speak French
Listen to this dialogue between Jean-Denis and Georges
And you will repeat Georges' answers.
Hi everyone!
So, what are you doing?
It hasn't rained for an hour.
It's not raining anymore?
Non
That's not possible
Yes, yes, I assure you
It's rising
So, are you coming to go sailing?
No, old man, not today.
Today, we're taking a nap.
Now it's your turn, you are Georges.
Hi everyone!
So, what are you doing?
It hasn't rained for an hour.
It's not raining anymore?
Non.
That's not possible.
Yes, yes, I assure you.
It's rising.
So, are you coming to go sailing?
No, old man, not today.
Today, we're taking a nap.
Okay, now let's see what you remember.
What's the weather like here?
It's raining.
And what's the weather like here?
Is the weather bad?
No, the weather is nice.
And is the weather bad here?
No, it's rising.
Does this man have a hooked nose?
No, he has a straight nose.
Does this gentleman have a lot of hair?
No, he's bald.
And is this lady bald?
No, she has a lot of hair.
And this lady, does she have a lot of hair?
Oh no, she's bald
Does Asterix have a beard?
No, he doesn't have a beard, he has a shaved chin.
And this gentleman, is he clean-shaven?
Yes, but he has a very large mustache.
Does this gentleman have protruding ears? No, he has pinned ears. Does this gentleman have a small nose? No, he has a large nose, an enormous nose, a monumental nose.
Does that police officer look nice? No, he looks angry. Look, is there nobody here? Yes, there is someone. And here, is there anyone? No, there's nobody.
Now, say what you see.
A toe.
Well, I think that's enough.
We've been playing this stupid game for 20 minutes.
We're stopping. It's over.
Subtitles ST' 501
Subtitling by Radio-Canada